Micah 7

7

^1Woe is me! for I am as when they have gathered the summer fruits, as the grape gleanings of the vintage: there is no cluster to eat; my soul desireth the first-ripe fig. ^2The godly man is perished out of the earth, and there is none upright among men: they all lie in wait for blood; they hunt every man his brother with a net. ^3Their hands are upon that which is evil to do it diligently; the prince asketh, and the judge is ready for a reward; and the great man, he uttereth the evil desire of his soul: thus they weave it together. ^4The best of them is as a brier; the most upright is worse than a thorn hedge: the day of thy watchmen, even thy visitation, is come; now shall be their perplexity. ^5Trust ye not in a neighbor; put ye not confidence in a friend; keep the doors of thy mouth from her that lieth in thy bosom. ^6For the son dishonoreth the father, the daughter riseth up against her mother, the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law; a man's enemies are the men of his own house. ^7But as for me, I will look unto Jehovah; I will wait for the God of my salvation: my God will hear me. ^8Rejoice not against me, O mine enemy: when I fall, I shall arise; when I sit in darkness, Jehovah will be a light unto me. ^9I will bear the indignation of Jehovah, because I have sinned against him, until he plead my cause, and execute judgment for me: he will bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his righteousness. ^10Then mine enemy shall see it, and shame shall cover her who said unto me, Where is Jehovah thy God? Mine eyes shall see my desire upon her; now shall she be trodden down as the mire of the streets. ^11A day for building thy walls! in that day shall the decree be far removed. ^12In that day shall they come unto thee from Assyria and the cities of Egypt, and from Egypt even to the River, and from sea to sea, and from mountain to mountain. ^13Yet shall the land be desolate because of them that dwell therein, for the fruit of their doings. ^14Feed thy people with thy rod, the flock of thy heritage, which dwell solitarily, in the forest in the midst of Carmel: let them feed in Bashan and Gilead, as in the days of old. ^15As in the days of thy coming forth out of the land of Egypt will I show unto them marvellous things. ^16The nations shall see and be ashamed of all their might; they shall lay their hand upon their mouth; their ears shall be deaf. ^17They shall lick the dust like a serpent; like crawling things of the earth they shall come trembling out of their close places; they shall come with fear unto Jehovah our God, and shall be afraid because of thee. ^18Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and passeth over the transgression of the remnant of his heritage? he retaineth not his anger for ever, because he delighteth in lovingkindness. ^19He will again have compassion upon us; he will tread our iniquities under foot; and thou wilt cast all their sins into the depths of the sea. ^20Thou wilt perform the truth to Jacob, and the lovingkindness to Abraham, which thou hast sworn unto our fathers from the days of old.

Nahum 2

2

^1He that dasheth in pieces is come up against thee: keep the fortress, watch the way, make thy loins strong, fortify thy power mightily. ^2For Jehovah restoreth the excellency of Jacob, as the excellency of Israel; for the emptiers have emptied them out, and destroyed their vine-branches. ^3The shield of his mighty men is made red, the valiant men are in scarlet: the chariots flash with steel in the day of his preparation, and the cypress spears are brandished. ^4The chariots rage in the streets; they rush to and fro in the broad ways: the appearance of them is like torches; they run like the lightnings. ^5He remembereth his nobles: they stumble in their march; they make haste to the wall thereof, and the mantelet is prepared. ^6The gates of the rivers are opened, and the palace is dissolved. ^7And it is decreed: she is uncovered, she is carried away; and her handmaids moan as with the voice of doves, beating upon their breasts. ^8But Nineveh hath been from of old like a pool of water: yet they flee away. Stand, stand, they cry; but none looketh back. ^9Take ye the spoil of silver, take the spoil of gold; for there is no end of the store, the glory of all goodly furniture. ^10She is empty, and void, and waste; and the heart melteth, and the knees smite together, and anguish is in all loins, and the faces of them all are waxed pale. ^11Where is the den of the lions, and the feeding-place of the young lions, where the lion and the lioness walked, the lion's whelp, and none made them afraid? ^12The lion did tear in pieces enough for his whelps, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his caves with prey, and his dens with ravin. ^13Behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will burn her chariots in the smoke, and the sword shall devour thy young lions; and I will cut off thy prey from the earth, and the voice of thy messengers shall no more be heard.

Nahum 3

3

^1Woe to the bloody city! it is all full of lies and rapine; the prey departeth not. ^2The noise of the whip, and the noise of the rattling of wheels, and prancing horses, and bounding chariots, ^3the horseman mounting, and the flashing sword, and the glittering spear, and a multitude of slain, and a great heap of corpses, and there is no end of the bodies; they stumble upon their bodies;- ^4because of the multitude of the whoredoms of the well-favored harlot, the mistress of witchcrafts, that selleth nations through her whoredoms, and families through her witchcrafts. ^5Behold, I am against thee, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will uncover thy skirts upon thy face; and I will show the nations thy nakedness, and the kingdoms thy shame. ^6And I will cast abominable filth upon thee, and make thee vile, and will set thee as a gazing-stock. ^7And it shall come to pass, that all they that look upon thee shall flee from thee, and say, Nineveh is laid waste: who will bemoan her? whence shall I seek comforters for thee? ^8Art thou better than No-amon, that was situate among the rivers, that had the waters round about her; whose rampart was the sea, and her wall was of the sea? ^9Ethiopia and Egypt were her strength, and it was infinite; Put and Lubim were thy helpers. ^10Yet was she carried away, she went into captivity; her young children also were dashed in pieces at the head of all the streets; and they cast lots for her honorable men, and all her great men were bound in chains. ^11Thou also shalt be drunken; thou shalt be hid; thou also shalt seek a stronghold because of the enemy. ^12All thy fortresses shall be like fig-trees with the first-ripe figs: if they be shaken, they fall into the mouth of the eater. ^13Behold, thy people in the midst of thee are women; the gates of thy land are set wide open unto thine enemies: the fire hath devoured thy bars. ^14Draw thee water for the siege; strengthen thy fortresses; go into the clay, and tread the mortar; make strong the brickkiln. ^15There shall the fire devour thee; the sword shall cut thee off; it shall devour thee like the canker-worm: make thyself many as the canker-worm; make thyself many as the locust. ^16Thou hast multiplied thy merchants above the stars of heaven: the canker-worm ravageth, and fleeth away. ^17Thy princes are as the locusts, and thy marshals as the swarms of grasshoppers, which encamp in the hedges in the cold day, but when the sun ariseth they flee away, and their place is not known where they are. ^18Thy shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria; thy nobles are at rest; thy people are scattered upon the mountains, and there is none to gather them. ^19There is no assuaging of thy hurt: thy wound is grievous: all that hear the report of thee clap their hands over thee; for upon whom hath not thy wickedness passed continually?

Nehemiah 2

2

^1And it came to pass in the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, when wine was before him, that I took up the wine, and gave it unto the king. Now I had not been beforetime sad in his presence. ^2And the king said unto me, Why is thy countenance sad, seeing thou art not sick? this is nothing else but sorrow of heart. Then I was very sore afraid. ^3And I said unto the king, Let the king live for ever: why should not my countenance be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers' sepulchres, lieth waste, and the gates thereof are consumed with fire? ^4Then the king said unto me, For what dost thou make request? So I prayed to the God of heaven. ^5And I said unto the king, If it please the king, and if thy servant have found favor in thy sight, that thou wouldest send me unto Judah, unto the city of my fathers' sepulchres, that I may build it. ^6And the king said unto me (the queen also sitting by him,) For how long shall thy journey be? and when wilt thou return? So it pleased the king to send me; and I set him a time. ^7Moreover I said unto the king, If it please the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the River, that they may let me pass through till I come unto Judah; ^8and a letter unto Asaph the keeper of the king's forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the castle which appertaineth to the house, and for the wall of the city, and for the house that I shall enter into. And the king granted me, according to the good hand of my God upon me. ^9Then I came to the governors beyond the River, and gave them the king's letters. Now the king had sent with me captains of the army and horsemen. ^10And when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly, for that there was come a man to seek the welfare of the children of Israel. ^11So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days. ^12And I arose in the night, I and some few men with me; neither told I any man what my God put into my heart to do for Jerusalem; neither was there any beast with me, save the beast that I rode upon. ^13And I went out by night by the valley gate, even toward the jackal's well, and to the dung gate, and viewed the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and the gates thereof were consumed with fire. ^14Then I went on to the fountain gate and to the king's pool: but there was no place for the beast that was under me to pass. ^15Then went I up in the night by the brook, and viewed the wall; and I turned back, and entered by the valley gate, and so returned. ^16And the rulers knew not whither I went, or what I did; neither had I as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest that did the work. ^17Then said I unto them, Ye see the evil case that we are in, how Jerusalem lieth waste, and the gates thereof are burned with fire: come, and let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we be no more a reproach. ^18And I told them of the hand of my God which was good upon me, as also of the king's words that he had spoken unto me. And they said, Let us rise up and build. So they strengthened their hands for the good work. ^19But when Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it, they laughed us to scorn, and despised us, and said, What is this thing that ye do? will ye rebel against the king? ^20Then answered I them, and said unto them, The God of heaven, he will prosper us; therefore we his servants will arise and build: but ye have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem.

Nehemiah 3

3

^1Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brethren the priests, and they builded the sheep gate; they sanctified it, and set up the doors of it; even unto the tower of Hammeah they sanctified it, unto the tower of Hananel. ^2And next unto him builded the men of Jericho. And next to them builded Zaccur the son of Imri. ^3And the fish gate did the sons of Hassenaah build; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof. ^4And next unto them repaired Meremoth the son of Uriah, the son of Hakkoz. And next unto them repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabel. And next unto them repaired Zadok the son of Baana. ^5And next unto them the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their necks to the work of their lord. ^6And the old gate repaired Joiada the son of Paseah and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah; they laid the beams thereof, and set up the doors thereof, and the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof. ^7And next unto them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, that appertained to the throne of the governor beyond the River. ^8Next unto him repaired Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, goldsmiths. And next unto him repaired Hananiah one of the perfumers, and they fortified Jerusalem even unto the broad wall. ^9And next unto them repaired Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem. ^10And next unto them repaired Jedaiah the son of Harumaph, over against his house. And next unto him repaired Hattush the son of Hashabneiah. ^11Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hasshub the son of Pahath-moab, repaired another portion, and the tower of the furnaces. ^12And next unto him repaired Shallum the son of Hallohesh, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem, he and his daughters. ^13The valley gate repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof, and a thousand cubits of the wall unto the dung gate. ^14And the dung gate repaired Malchijah the son of Rechab, the ruler of the district of Beth-haccherem; he built it, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof. ^15And the fountain gate repaired Shallun the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of the district of Mizpah; he built it, and covered it, and set up the doors thereof, the bolts thereof, and the bars thereof, and the wall of the pool of Shelah by the king's garden, even unto the stairs that go down from the city of David. ^16After him repaired Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of half the district of Beth-zur, unto the place over against the sepulchres of David, and unto the pool that was made, and unto the house of the mighty men. ^17After him repaired the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani. Next unto him repaired Hashabiah, the ruler of half the district of Keilah, for his district. ^18After him repaired their brethren, Bavvai the son of Henadad, the ruler of half the district of Keilah. ^19And next to him repaired Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another portion, over against the ascent to the armory at the turning of the wall. ^20After him Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired another portion, from the turning of the wall unto the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest. ^21After him repaired Meremoth the son of Uriah the son of Hakkoz another portion, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib. ^22And after him repaired the priests, the men of the Plain. ^23After them repaired Benjamin and Hasshub over against their house. After them repaired Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah beside his own house. ^24After him repaired Binnui the son of Henadad another portion, from the house of Azariah unto the turning of the wall, and unto the corner. ^25Palal the son of Uzai repaired over against the turning of the wall, and the tower that standeth out from the upper house of the king, which is by the court of the guard. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh repaired. ^26(Now the Nethinim dwelt in Ophel, unto the place over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that standeth out.) ^27After him the Tekoites repaired another portion, over against the great tower that standeth out, and unto the wall of Ophel. ^28Above the horse gate repaired the priests, every one over against his own house. ^29After them repaired Zadok the son of Immer over against his own house. And after him repaired Shemaiah the son of Shecaniah, the keeper of the east gate. ^30After him repaired Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, another portion. After him repaired Meshullam the son of Berechiah over against his chamber. ^31After him repaired Malchijah one of the goldsmiths unto the house of the Nethinim, and of the merchants, over against the gate of Hammiphkad, and to the ascent of the corner. ^32And between the ascent of the corner and the sheep gate repaired the goldsmiths and the merchants.

Nehemiah 4

4

^1But it came to pass that, when Sanballat heard that we were building the wall, he was wroth, and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews. ^2And he spake before his brethren and the army of Samaria, and said, What are these feeble Jews doing? will they fortify themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of rubbish, seeing they are burned? ^3Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, Even that which they are building, if a fox go up, he shall break down their stone wall. ^4Hear, O our God; for we are despised: and turn back their reproach upon their own head, and give them up for a spoil in a land of captivity; ^5and cover not their iniquity, and let not their sin be blotted out from before thee; for they have provoked thee to anger before the builders. ^6So we built the wall; and all the wall was joined together unto half the height thereof: for the people had a mind to work. ^7But it came to pass that, when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites, heard that the repairing of the walls of Jerusalem went forward, and that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth; ^8and they conspired all of them together to come and fight against Jerusalem, and to cause confusion therein. ^9But we made our prayer unto our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them. ^10And Judah said, The strength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and there is much rubbish; so that we are not able to build the wall. ^11And our adversaries said, They shall not know, neither see, till we come into the midst of them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease. ^12And it came to pass that, when the Jews that dwelt by them came, they said unto us ten times from all places, Ye must return unto us. ^13Therefore set I in the lowest parts of the space behind the wall, in the open places, I set there the people after their families with their swords, their spears, and their bows. ^14And I looked, and rose up, and said unto the nobles, and to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, Be not ye afraid of them: remember the Lord, who is great and terrible, and fight for your brethren, your sons, and your daughters, your wives, and your houses. ^15And it came to pass, when our enemies heard that it was known unto us, and God had brought their counsel to nought, that we returned all of us to the wall, every one unto his work. ^16And it came to pass from that time forth, that half of my servants wrought in the work, and half of them held the spears, the shields, and the bows, and the coats of mail; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah. ^17They all builded the wall and they that bare burdens laded themselves; every one with one of his hands wrought in the work, and with the other held his weapon; ^18and the builders, every one had his sword girded by his side, and so builded. And he that sounded the trumpet was by me. ^19And I said unto the nobles, and to the rulers and to the rest of the people, The work is great and large, and we are separated upon the wall, one far from another: ^20in what place soever ye hear the sound of the trumpet, resort ye thither unto us; our God will fight for us. ^21So we wrought in the work: and half of them held the spears from the rising of the morning till the stars appeared. ^22Likewise at the same time said I unto the people, Let every one with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and may labor in the day. ^23So neither I, nor my brethren, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard that followed me, none of us put off our clothes, every one went with his weapon to the water.

Nehemiah 5

5

^1Then there arose a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brethren the Jews. ^2For there were that said, We, our sons and our daughters, are many: let us get grain, that we may eat and live. ^3Some also there were that said, We are mortgaging our fields, and our vineyards, and our houses: let us get grain, because of the dearth. ^4There were also that said, We have borrowed money for the king's tribute upon our fields and our vineyards. ^5Yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children: and, lo, we bring into bondage our sons and our daughters to be servants, and some of our daughters are brought into bondage already: neither is it in our power to help it; for other men have our fields and our vineyards. ^6And I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words. ^7Then I consulted with myself, and contended with the nobles and the rulers, and said unto them, Ye exact usury, every one of his brother. And I held a great assembly against them. ^8And I said unto them, We after our ability have redeemed our brethren the Jews, that were sold unto the nations; and would ye even sell your brethren, and should they be sold unto us? Then held they their peace, and found never a word. ^9Also I said, The thing that ye do is not good: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God, because of the reproach of the nations our enemies? ^10And I likewise, my brethren and my servants, do lend them money and grain. I pray you, let us leave off this usury. ^11Restore, I pray you, to them, even this day, their fields, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houses, also the hundredth part of the money, and of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, that ye exact of them. ^12Then said they, We will restore them, and will require nothing of them; so will we do, even as thou sayest. Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they would do according to this promise. ^13Also I shook out my lap, and said, So God shake out every man from his house, and from his labor, that performeth not this promise; even thus be he shaken out, and emptied. And all the assembly said, Amen, and praised Jehovah. And the people did according to this promise. ^14Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even unto the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelve years, I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the governor. ^15But the former governors that were before me were chargeable unto the people, and took of them bread and wine, besides forty shekels of silver; yea, even their servants bare rule over the people: but so did not I, because of the fear of God. ^16Yea, also I continued in the work of this wall, neither bought we any land: and all my servants were gathered thither unto the work. ^17Moreover there were at my table, of the Jews and the rulers, a hundred and fifty men, besides those that came unto us from among the nations that were round about us. ^18Now that which was prepared for one day was one ox and six choice sheep; also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days store of all sorts of wine: yet for all this I demanded not the bread of the governor, because the bondage was heavy upon this people. ^19Remember unto me, O my God, for good, all that I have done for this people.

Nehemiah 6

6

^1Now it came to pass, when it was reported to Sanballat and Tobiah, and to Geshem the Arabian, and unto the rest of our enemies, that I had builded the wall, and that there was no breach left therein; (though even unto that time I had not set up the doors in the gates;) ^2that Sanballat and Geshem sent unto me, saying, Come, let us meet together in one of the villages in the plain of Ono. But they thought to do me mischief. ^3And I sent messengers unto them, saying, I am doing a great work, so that I cannot come down: why should the work cease, whilst I leave it, and come down to you? ^4And they sent unto me four times after this sort; and I answered them after the same manner. ^5Then sent Sanballat his servant unto me in like manner the fifth time with an open letter in his hand, ^6wherein was written, It is reported among the nations, and Gashmu saith it, that thou and the Jews think to rebel; for which cause thou art building the wall: and thou wouldest be their king, according to these words. ^7And thou hast also appointed prophets to preach of thee at Jerusalem, saying, There is a king in Judah: and now shall it be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together. ^8Then I sent unto him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou feignest them out of thine own heart. ^9For they all would have made us afraid, saying, Their hands shall be weakened from the work, that it be not done. But now, O God, strengthen thou my hands. ^10And I went unto the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabel, who was shut up; and he said, Let us meet together in the house of God, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple: for they will come to slay thee; yea, in the night will they come to slay thee. ^11And I said, Should such a man as I flee? and who is there, that, being such as I, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in. ^12And I discerned, and, lo, God had not sent him; but he pronounced this prophecy against me: and Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him. ^13For this cause was he hired, that I should be afraid, and do so, and sin, and that they might have matter for an evil report, that they might reproach me. ^14Remember, O my God, Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and also the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear. ^15So the wall was finished in the twenty and fifth day of the month Elul, in fifty and two days. ^16And it came to pass, when all our enemies heard thereof, that all the nations that were about us feared, and were much cast down in their own eyes; for they perceived that this work was wrought of our God. ^17Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters unto Tobiah, and the letters of Tobiah came unto them. ^18For there were many in Judah sworn unto him, because he was the son-in-law of Shecaniah the son of Arah; and his son Jehohanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah to wife. ^19Also they spake of his good deeds before me, and reported my words to him. And Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.

Nehemiah 7

7

^1Now it came to pass, when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed, ^2that I gave my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the governor of the castle, charge over Jerusalem; for he was a faithful man, and feared God above many. ^3And I said unto them, Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun be hot; and while they stand on guard, let them shut the doors, and bar ye them: and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every one in his watch, and every one to be over against his house. ^4Now the city was wide and large; but the people were few therein, and the houses were not builded. ^5And my God put into my heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogy. And I found the book of the genealogy of them that came up at the first, and I found written therein: ^6These are the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and that returned unto Jerusalem and to Judah, every one unto his city; ^7who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel: ^8The children of Parosh, two thousand a hundred and seventy and two. ^9The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two. ^10The children of Arah, six hundred fifty and two. ^11The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand and eight hundred and eighteen. ^12The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. ^13The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty and five. ^14The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore. ^15The children of Binnui, six hundred forty and eight. ^16The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and eight. ^17The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty and two. ^18The children of Adonikam, six hundred threescore and seven. ^19The children of Bigvai, two thousand threescore and seven. ^20The children of Adin, six hundred fifty and five. ^21The children of Ater, of Hezekiah, ninety and eight. ^22The children of Hashum, three hundred twenty and eight. ^23The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and four. ^24The children of Hariph, a hundred and twelve. ^25The children of Gibeon, ninety and five. ^26The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, a hundred fourscore and eight. ^27The men of Anathoth, a hundred twenty and eight. ^28The men of Beth-azmaveth, forty and two. ^29The men of Kiriath-jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty and three. ^30The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty and one. ^31The men of Michmas, a hundred and twenty and two. ^32The men of Beth-el and Ai, a hundred twenty and three. ^33The men of the other Nebo, fifty and two. ^34The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. ^35The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty. ^36The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five. ^37The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and one. ^38The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty. ^39The priests: The children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three. ^40The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two. ^41The children of Pashhur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven. ^42The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen. ^43The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, of the children of Hodevah, seventy and four. ^44The singers: the children of Asaph, a hundred forty and eight. ^45The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, a hundred thirty and eight. ^46The Nethinim: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth, ^47the children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon, ^48the children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Salmai, ^49the children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, ^50the children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, ^51the children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Paseah. ^52The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephushesim, ^53the children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur, ^54the children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha, ^55the children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Temah, ^56the children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha. ^57The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida, ^58the children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel, ^59the children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth-hazzebaim, the children of Amon. ^60All the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's servants, were three hundred ninety and two. ^61And these were they that went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer; but they could not show their fathers' houses, nor their seed, whether they were of Israel: ^62The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two. ^63And of the priests: the children of Hobaiah, the children of Hakkoz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name. ^64These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but it was not found: therefore were they deemed polluted and put from the priesthood. ^65And the governor said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and Thummim. ^66The whole assembly together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore, ^67besides their men-servants and their maid-servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred forty and five singing men and singing women. ^68Their horses were seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred forty and five; ^69their camels, four hundred thirty and five; their asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty. ^70And some from among the heads of fathers' houses gave unto the work. The governor gave to the treasury a thousand darics of gold, fifty basins, five hundred and thirty priests' garments. ^71And some of the heads of fathers' houses gave into the treasury of the work twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand and two hundred pounds of silver. ^72And that which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand pounds of silver, and threescore and seven priests' garments. ^73So the priests, and the Levites, and the porters, and the singers, and some of the people, and the Nethinim, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities. And when the seventh month was come, the children of Israel were in their cities.

Nehemiah 8

8

^1And all the people gathered themselves together as one man into the broad place that was before the water gate; and they spake unto Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which Jehovah had commanded to Israel. ^2And Ezra the priest brought the law before the assembly, both men and women, and all that could hear with understanding, upon the first day of the seventh month. ^3And he read therein before the broad place that was before the water gate from early morning until midday, in the presence of the men and the women, and of those that could understand; and the ears of all the people were attentive unto the book of the law. ^4And Ezra the scribe stood upon a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah, and Uriah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchijah, and Hashum, and Hashbaddanah, Zechariah, and Meshullam. ^5And Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people; (for he was above all the people;) and when he opened it, all the people stood up: ^6and Ezra blessed Jehovah, the great God. And all the people answered, Amen, Amen, with the lifting up of their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worshipped Jehovah with their faces to the ground. ^7Also Jeshua, and Bani, and Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodiah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law: and the people stood in their place. ^8And they read in the book, in the law of God, distinctly; and they gave the sense, so that they understood the reading. ^9And Nehemiah, who was the governor, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that taught the people, said unto all the people, This day is holy unto Jehovah your God; mourn not, nor weep. For all the people wept, when they heard the words of the law. ^10Then he said unto them, Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send portions unto him for whom nothing is prepared; for this day is holy unto our Lord: neither be ye grieved; for the joy of Jehovah is your strength. ^11So the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace, for the day is holy; neither be ye grieved. ^12And all the people went their way to eat, and to drink, and to send portions, and to make great mirth, because they had understood the words that were declared unto them. ^13And on the second day were gathered together the heads of fathers' houses of all the people, the priests, and the Levites, unto Ezra the scribe, even to give attention to the words of the law. ^14And they found written in the law, how that Jehovah had commanded by Moses, that the children of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month; ^15and that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, Go forth unto the mount, and fetch olive branches, and branches of wild olive, and myrtle branches, and palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make booths, as it is written. ^16So the people went forth, and brought them, and made themselves booths, every one upon the roof of his house, and in their courts, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the broad place of the water gate, and in the broad place of the gate of Ephraim. ^17And all the assembly of them that were come again out of the captivity made booths, and dwelt in the booths; for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun unto that day had not the children of Israel done so. And there was very great gladness. ^18Also day by day, from the first day unto the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. And they kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day was a solemn assembly, according unto the ordinance.

Nehemiah 9

9

^1Now in the twenty and fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, and with sackcloth, and earth upon them. ^2And the seed of Israel separated themselves from all foreigners, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers. ^3And they stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of Jehovah their God a fourth part of the day; and another fourth part they confessed, and worshipped Jehovah their God. ^4Then stood up upon the stairs of the Levites, Jeshua, and Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, and Chenani, and cried with a loud voice unto Jehovah their God. ^5Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabneiah, Sherebiah, Hodiah, Shebaniah, and Pethahiah, said, Stand up and bless Jehovah your God from everlasting to everlasting; and blessed be thy glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise. ^6Thou art Jehovah, even thou alone; thou hast made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their host, the earth and all things that are thereon, the seas and all that is in them, and thou preservest them all; and the host of heaven worshippeth thee. ^7Thou art Jehovah the God, who didst choose Abram, and broughtest him forth out of Ur of the Chaldees, and gavest him the name of Abraham, ^8and foundest his heart faithful before thee, and madest a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite, and the Girgashite, to give it unto his seed, and hast performed thy words; for thou art righteous. ^9And thou sawest the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heardest their cry by the Red Sea, ^10and showedst signs and wonders upon Pharaoh, and on all his servants, and on all the people of his land; for thou knewest that they dealt proudly against them, and didst get thee a name, as it is this day. ^11And thou didst divide the sea before them, so that they went through the midst of the sea on the dry land; and their pursuers thou didst cast into the depths, as a stone into the mighty waters. ^12Moreover in a pillar of cloud thou leddest them by day; and in a pillar of fire by night, to give them light in the way wherein they should go. ^13Thou camest down also upon mount Sinai, and spakest with them from heaven, and gavest them right ordinances and true laws, good statutes and commandments, ^14and madest known unto them thy holy sabbath, and commandedst them commandments, and statutes, and a law, by Moses thy servant, ^15and gavest them bread from heaven for their hunger, and broughtest forth water for them out of the rock for their thirst, and commandedst them that they should go in to possess the land which thou hadst sworn to give them. ^16But they and our fathers dealt proudly and hardened their neck, and hearkened not to thy commandments, ^17and refused to obey, neither were mindful of thy wonders that thou didst among them, but hardened their neck, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage. But thou art a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in lovingkindness, and forsookest them not. ^18Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and said, This is thy God that brought thee up out of Egypt, and had wrought great provocations; ^19yet thou in thy manifold mercies forsookest them not in the wilderness: the pillar of cloud departed not from over them by day, to lead them in the way; neither the pillar of fire by night, to show them light, and the way wherein they should go. ^20Thou gavest also thy good Spirit to instruct them, and withheldest not thy manna from their mouth, and gavest them water for their thirst. ^21Yea, forty years didst thou sustain them in the wilderness, and they lacked nothing; their clothes waxed not old, and their feet swelled not. ^22Moreover thou gavest them kingdoms and peoples, which thou didst allot after their portions: so they possessed the land of Sihon, even the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan. ^23Their children also multipliedst thou as the stars of heaven, and broughtest them into the land concerning which thou didst say to their fathers, that they should go in to possess it. ^24So the children went in and possessed the land, and thou subduedst before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gavest them into their hands, with their kings, and the peoples of the land, that they might do with them as they would. ^25And they took fortified cities, and a fat land, and possessed houses full of all good things, cisterns hewn out, vineyards, and oliveyards, and fruit-trees in abundance: so they did eat, and were filled, and became fat, and delighted themselves in thy great goodness. ^26Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against thee, and cast thy law behind their back, and slew thy prophets that testified against them to turn them again unto thee, and they wrought great provocations. ^27Therefore thou deliveredst them into the hand of their adversaries, who distressed them: and in the time of their trouble, when they cried unto thee, thou heardest from heaven; and according to thy manifold mercies thou gavest them saviours who saved them out of the hand of their adversaries. ^28But after they had rest, they did evil again before thee; therefore leftest thou them in the hand of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them: yet when they returned, and cried unto thee, thou heardest from heaven; and many times didst thou deliver them according to thy mercies, ^29and testifiedst against them, that thou mightest bring them again unto thy law. Yet they dealt proudly, and hearkened not unto thy commandments, but sinned against thine ordinances, (which if a man do, he shall live in them,) and withdrew the shoulder, and hardened their neck, and would not hear. ^30Yet many years didst thou bear with them, and testifiedst against them by thy Spirit through thy prophets: yet would they not give ear: therefore gavest thou them into the hand of the peoples of the lands. ^31Nevertheless in thy manifold mercies thou didst not make a full end of them, nor forsake them; for thou art a gracious and merciful God. ^32Now therefore, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible God, who keepest covenant and lovingkindness, let not all the travail seem little before thee, that hath come upon us, on our kings, on our princes, and on our priests, and on our prophets, and on our fathers, and on all thy people, since the time of the kings of Assyria unto this day. ^33Howbeit thou art just in all that is come upon us; for thou hast dealt truly, but we have done wickedly; ^34neither have our kings, our princes, our priests, nor our fathers, kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy commandments and thy testimonies wherewith thou didst testify against them. ^35For they have not served thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodness that thou gavest them, and in the large and fat land which thou gavest before them, neither turned they from their wicked works. ^36Behold, we are servants this day, and as for the land that thou gavest unto our fathers to eat the fruit thereof and the good thereof, behold, we are servants in it. ^37And it yieldeth much increase unto the kings whom thou hast set over us because of our sins: also they have power over our bodies, and over our cattle, at their pleasure, and we are in great distress. ^38And yet for all this we make a sure covenant, and write it; and our princes, our Levites, and our priests, seal unto it.

Nehemiah 11

11

^1And the princes of the people dwelt in Jerusalem: the rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts in the other cities. ^2And the people blessed all the men that willingly offered themselves to dwell in Jerusalem. ^3Now these are the chiefs of the province that dwelt in Jerusalem: but in the cities of Judah dwelt every one in his possession in their cities, to wit, Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's servants. ^4And in Jerusalem dwelt certain of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin. Of the children of Judah: Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalalel, of the children of Perez; ^5and Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Colhozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of the Shilonite. ^6All the sons of Perez that dwelt in Jerusalem were four hundred threescore and eight valiant men. ^7And these are the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jeshaiah. ^8And after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight. ^9And Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer; and Judah the son of Hassenuah was second over the city. ^10Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin, ^11Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God, ^12and their brethren that did the work of the house, eight hundred twenty and two; and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah, ^13and his brethren, chiefs of fathers' houses, two hundred forty and two; and Amashsai the son of Azarel, the son of Ahzai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer, ^14and their brethren, mighty men of valor, a hundred twenty and eight; and their overseer was Zabdiel, the son of Haggedolim. ^15And of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni; ^16and Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chiefs of the Levites, who had the oversight of the outward business of the house of God; ^17and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, who was the chief to begin the thanksgiving in prayer, and Bakbukiah, the second among his brethren; and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun. ^18All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred fourscore and four. ^19Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren, that kept watch at the gates, were a hundred seventy and two. ^20And the residue of Israel, of the priests, the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, every one in his inheritance. ^21But the Nethinim dwelt in Ophel: and Ziha and Gishpa were over the Nethinim. ^22The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Mica, of the sons of Asaph, the singers, over the business of the house of God. ^23For there was a commandment from the king concerning them, and a settled provision for the singers, as every day required. ^24And Pethahiah the son of Meshezabel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king's hand in all matters concerning the people. ^25And as for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah dwelt in Kiriath-arba and the towns thereof, and in Dibon and the towns thereof, and in Jekabzeel and the villages thereof, ^26and in Jeshua, and in Moladah, and Beth-pelet, ^27and in Hazar-shual, and in Beer-sheba and the towns thereof, ^28and in Ziklag, and in Meconah and in the towns thereof, ^29and in En-rimmon, and in Zorah, and in Jarmuth, ^30Zanoah, Adullam, and their villages, Lachish and the fields thereof, Azekah and the towns thereof. So they encamped from Beer-sheba unto the valley of Hinnom. ^31The children of Benjamin also dwelt from Geba onward, at Michmash and Aija, and at Beth-el and the towns thereof, ^32at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah, ^33Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim, ^34Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat, ^35Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen. ^36And of the Levites, certain courses in Judah were joined to Benjamin.

Nehemiah 12

12

^1Now these are the priests and the Levites that went up with Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua: Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra, ^2Amariah, Malluch, Hattush, ^3Shecaniah, Rehum, Meremoth, ^4Iddo, Ginnethoi, Abijah, ^5Mijamin, Maadiah, Bilgah, ^6Shemaiah, and Joiarib, Jedaiah. ^7Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah, Jedaiah. These were the chiefs of the priests and of their brethren in the days of Jeshua. ^8Moreover the Levites: Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, and Mattaniah, who was over the thanksgiving, he and his brethren. ^9Also Bakbukiah and Unno, their brethren, were over against them according to their offices. ^10And Jeshua begat Joiakim, and Joiakim begat Eliashib, and Eliashib begat Joiada, ^11and Joiada begat Jonathan, and Jonathan begat Jaddua. ^12And in the days of Joiakim were priests, heads of fathers' houses: of Seraiah, Meraiah; of Jeremiah, Hananiah; ^13of Ezra, Meshullam; of Amariah, Jehohanan; ^14of Malluchi, Jonathan; of Shebaniah, Joseph; ^15of Harim, Adna; of Meraioth, Helkai; ^16of Iddo, Zechariah; of Ginnethon, Meshullam; ^17of Abijah, Zichri; of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai; ^18of Bilgah, Shammua; of Shemaiah, Jehonathan; ^19and of Joiarib, Mattenai; of Jedaiah, Uzzi; ^20of Sallai, Kallai; of Amok, Eber; ^21of Hilkiah, Hashabiah; of Jedaiah, Nethanel. ^22As for the Levites, in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, and Johanan, and Jaddua, there were recorded the heads of fathers' houses; also the priests, in the reign of Darius the Persian. ^23The sons of Levi, heads of fathers' houses, were written in the book of the chronicles, even until the days of Johanan the son of Eliashib. ^24And the chiefs of the Levites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Jeshua the son of Kadmiel, with their brethren over against them, to praise and give thanks, according to the commandment of David the man of God, watch next to watch. ^25Mattaniah, and Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, were porters keeping the watch at the store-houses of the gates. ^26These were in the days of Joiakim the son of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor, and of Ezra the priest the scribe. ^27And at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem they sought the Levites out of all their places, to bring them to Jerusalem, to keep the dedication with gladness, both with thanksgivings, and with singing, with cymbals, psalteries, and with harps. ^28And the sons of the singers gathered themselves together, both out of the plain round about Jerusalem, and from the villages of the Netophathites; ^29also from Beth-gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba and Azmaveth: for the singers had builded them villages round about Jerusalem. ^30And the priests and the Levites purified themselves; and they purified the people, and the gates, and the wall. ^31Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall, and appointed two great companies that gave thanks and went in procession; whereof one went on the right hand upon the wall toward the dung gate: ^32and after them went Hoshaiah, and half of the princes of Judah, ^33and Azariah, Ezra, and Meshullam, ^34Judah, and Benjamin, and Shemaiah, and Jeremiah, ^35and certain of the priests' sons with trumpets: Zechariah the son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micaiah, the son of Zaccur, the son of Asaph; ^36and his brethren, Shemaiah, and Azarel, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethanel, and Judah, Hanani, with the musical instruments of David the man of God; and Ezra the scribe was before them. ^37And by the fountain gate, and straight before them, they went up by the stairs of the city of David, at the ascent of the wall, above the house of David, even unto the water gate eastward. ^38And the other company of them that gave thanks went to meet them, and I after them, with the half of the people, upon the wall, above the tower of the furnaces, even unto the broad wall, ^39and above the gate of Ephraim, and by the old gate, and by the fish gate, and the tower of Hananel, and the tower of Hammeah, even unto the sheep gate: and they stood still in the gate of the guard. ^40So stood the two companies of them that gave thanks in the house of God, and I, and the half of the rulers with me; ^41and the priests, Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Micaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah, and Hananiah, with trumpets; ^42and Maaseiah, and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Jehohanan, and Malchijah, and Elam, and Ezer. And the singers sang loud, with Jezrahiah their overseer. ^43And they offered great sacrifices that day, and rejoiced; for God had made them rejoice with great joy; and the women also and the children rejoiced: so that the joy of Jerusalem was heard even afar off. ^44And on that day were men appointed over the chambers for the treasures, for the heave-offerings, for the first-fruits, and for the tithes, to gather into them, according to the fields of the cities, the portions appointed by the law for the priests and Levites: for Judah rejoiced for the priests and for the Levites that waited. ^45And they kept the charge of their God, and the charge of the purification, and so did the singers and the porters, according to the commandment of David, and of Solomon his son. ^46For in the days of David and Asaph of old there was a chief of the singers, and songs of praise and thanksgiving unto God. ^47And all Israel in the days of Zerubbabel, and in the days of Nehemiah, gave the portions of the singers and the porters, as every day required: and they set apart that which was for the Levites; and the Levites set apart that which was for the sons of Aaron.

Nehemiah 13

13

^1On that day they read in the book of Moses in the audience of the people; and therein was found written, that an Ammonite and a Moabite should not enter into the assembly of God for ever, ^2because they met not the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, to curse them: howbeit our God turned the curse into a blessing. ^3And it came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude. ^4Now before this, Eliashib the priest, who was appointed over the chambers of the house of our God, being allied unto Tobiah, ^5had prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the meal-offerings, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithes of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, which were given by commandment to the Levites, and the singers, and the porters; and the heave-offerings for the priests. ^6But in all this time I was not at Jerusalem; for in the two and thirtieth year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon I went unto the king: and after certain days asked I leave of the king, ^7and I came to Jerusalem, and understood the evil that Eliashib had done for Tobiah, in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of God. ^8And it grieved me sore: therefore I cast forth all the household stuff of Tobiah out of the chamber. ^9Then I commanded, and they cleansed the chambers: and thither brought I again the vessels of the house of God, with the meal-offerings and the frankincense. ^10And I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given them; so that the Levites and the singers, that did the work, were fled every one to his field. ^11Then contended I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And I gathered them together, and set them in their place. ^12Then brought all Judah the tithe of the grain and the new wine and the oil unto the treasuries. ^13And I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah; for they were counted faithful, and their business was to distribute unto their brethren. ^14Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for the observances thereof. ^15In those days saw I in Judah some men treading wine-presses on the sabbath, and bringing in sheaves, and lading asses therewith; as also wine, grapes, and figs, and all manner of burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the sabbath day: and I testified against them in the day wherein they sold victuals. ^16There dwelt men of Tyre also therein, who brought in fish, and all manner of wares, and sold on the sabbath unto the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem. ^17Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said unto them, What evil thing is this that ye do, and profane the sabbath day? ^18Did not your fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, and upon this city? yet ye bring more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath. ^19And it came to pass that, when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the sabbath, I commanded that the doors should be shut, and commanded that they should not be opened till after the sabbath: and some of my servants set I over the gates, that there should no burden be brought in on the sabbath day. ^20So the merchants and sellers of all kind of wares lodged without Jerusalem once or twice. ^21Then I testified against them, and said unto them, Why lodge ye about the wall? if ye do so again, I will lay hands on you. From that time forth came they no more on the sabbath. ^22And I commanded the Levites that they should purify themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to sanctify the sabbath day. Remember unto me, O my God, this also, and spare me according to the greatness of thy lovingkindness. ^23In those days also saw I the Jews that had married women of Ashdod, of Ammon, and of Moab: ^24and their children spake half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jews' language, but according to the language of each people. ^25And I contended with them, and cursed them, and smote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, saying, Ye shall not give your daughters unto their sons, nor take their daughters for your sons, or for yourselves. ^26Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? yet among many nations was there no king like him, and he was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel: nevertheless even him did foreign women cause to sin. ^27Shall we then hearken unto you to do all this great evil, to trespass against our God in marrying foreign women? ^28And one of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, was son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite: therefore I chased him from me. ^29Remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites. ^30Thus cleansed I them from all foreigners, and appointed charges for the priests and for the Levites, every one in his work; ^31and for the wood-offering, at times appointed, and for the first-fruits. Remember me, O my God, for good.

Numbers 2

2

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^2The children of Israel shall encamp every man by his own standard, with the ensigns of their fathers' houses: over against the tent of meeting shall they encamp round about. ^3And those that encamp on the east side toward the sunrising shall be they of the standard of the camp of Judah, according to their hosts: and the prince of the children of Judah shall be Nahshon the son of Amminadab. ^4And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were threescore and fourteen thousand and six hundred. ^5And those that encamp next unto him shall be the tribe of Issachar: and the prince of the children of Issachar shall be Nethanel the son of Zuar. ^6And his host, and those that were numbered thereof, were fifty and four thousand and four hundred. ^7And the tribe of Zebulun: and the prince of the children of Zebulun shall be Eliab the son of Helon. ^8And his host, and those that were numbered thereof, were fifty and seven thousand and four hundred. ^9All that were numbered of the camp of Judah were a hundred thousand and fourscore thousand and six thousand and four hundred, according to their hosts. They shall set forth first.

^10On the south side shall be the standard of the camp of Reuben according to their hosts: and the prince of the children of Reuben shall be Elizur the son of Shedeur. ^11And his host, and those that were numbered thereof, were forty and six thousand and five hundred. ^12And those that encamp next unto him shall be the tribe of Simeon: and the prince of the children of Simeon shall be Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai. ^13And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were fifty and nine thousand and three hundred. ^14And the tribe of Gad: and the prince of the children of Gad shall be Eliasaph the son of Reuel. ^15And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were forty and five thousand and six hundred and fifty. ^16All that were numbered of the camp of Reuben were a hundred thousand and fifty and one thousand and four hundred and fifty, according to their hosts. And they shall set forth second.

^17Then the tent of meeting shall set forward, with the camp of the Levites in the midst of the camps: as they encamp, so shall they set forward, every man in his place, by their standards.

^18On the west side shall be the standard of the camp of Ephraim according to their hosts: and the prince of the children of Ephraim shall be Elishama the son of Ammihud. ^19And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were forty thousand and five hundred. ^20And next unto him shall be the tribe of Manasseh: and the prince of the children of Manasseh shall be Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur. ^21And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were thirty and two thousand and two hundred. ^22And the tribe of Benjamin: and the prince of the children of Benjamin shall be Abidan the son of Gideoni. ^23And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were thirty and five thousand and four hundred. ^24All that were numbered of the camp of Ephraim were a hundred thousand and eight thousand and a hundred, according to their hosts. And they shall set forth third.

^25On the north side shall be the standard of the camp of Dan according to their hosts: and the prince of the children of Dan shall be Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai. ^26And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were threescore and two thousand and seven hundred. ^27And those that encamp next unto him shall be the tribe of Asher: and the prince of the children of Asher shall be Pagiel the son of Ochran. ^28And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were forty and one thousand and five hundred. ^29And the tribe of Naphtali: and the prince of the children of Naphtali shall be Ahira the son of Enan. ^30And his host, and those that were numbered of them, were fifty and three thousand and four hundred. ^31All that were numbered of the camp of Dan were a hundred thousand and fifty and seven thousand and six hundred. They shall set forth hindmost by their standards.

^32These are they that were numbered of the children of Israel by their fathers' houses: all that were numbered of the camps according to their hosts were six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty. ^33But the Levites were not numbered among the children of Israel; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^34Thus did the children of Israel; according to all that Jehovah commanded Moses, so they encamped by their standards, and so they set forward, every one by their families, according to their fathers' houses.

Numbers 3

3

^1Now these are the generations of Aaron and Moses in the day that Jehovah spake with Moses in mount Sinai. ^2And these are the names of the sons of Aaron: Nadab the first-born, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. ^3These are the names of the sons of Aaron, the priests that were anointed, whom he consecrated to minister in the priest's office. ^4And Nadab and Abihu died before Jehovah, when they offered strange fire before Jehovah, in the wilderness of Sinai, and they had no children; and Eleazar and Ithamar ministered in the priest's office in the presence of Aaron their father.

^5And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^6Bring the tribe of Levi near, and set them before Aaron the priest, that they may minister unto him. ^7And they shall keep his charge, and the charge of the whole congregation before the tent of meeting, to do the service of the tabernacle. ^8And they shall keep all the furniture of the tent of meeting, and the charge of the children of Israel, to do the service of the tabernacle. ^9And thou shalt give the Levites unto Aaron and to his sons: they are wholly given unto him on the behalf of the children of Israel. ^10And thou shalt appoint Aaron and his sons, and they shall keep their priesthood: and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death.

^11And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^12And I, behold, I have taken the Levites from among the children of Israel instead of all the first-born that openeth the womb among the children of Israel; and the Levites shall be mine: ^13for all the first-born are mine; on the day that I smote all the first-born in the land of Egypt I hallowed unto me all the first-born in Israel, both man and beast; mine they shall be: I am Jehovah.

^14And Jehovah spake unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, saying, ^15Number the children of Levi by their fathers' houses, by their families: every male from a month old and upward shalt thou number them. ^16And Moses numbered them according to the word of Jehovah, as he was commanded. ^17And these were the sons of Levi by their names: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari. ^18And these are the names of the sons of Gershon by their families: Libni and Shimei. ^19And the sons of Kohath by their families: Amram, and Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel. ^20And the sons of Merari by their families: Mahli and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to their fathers' houses.

^21Of Gershon was the family of the Libnites, and the family of the Shimeites: these are the families of the Gershonites. ^22Those that were numbered of them, according to the number of all the males, from a month old and upward, even those that were numbered of them were seven thousand and five hundred. ^23The families of the Gershonites shall encamp behind the tabernacle westward. ^24And the prince of the fathers' house of the Gershonites shall be Eliasaph the son of Lael. ^25And the charge of the sons of Gershon in the tent of meeting shall be the tabernacle, and the Tent, the covering thereof, and the screen for the door of the tent of meeting, ^26and the hangings of the court, and the screen for the door of the court, which is by the tabernacle, and by the altar round about, and the cords of it for all the service thereof.

^27And of Kohath was the family of the Amramites, and the family of the Izharites, and the family of the Hebronites, and the family of the Uzzielites: these are the families of the Kohathites. ^28According to the number of all the males, from a month old and upward, there were eight thousand and six hundred, keeping the charge of the sanctuary. ^29The families of the sons of Kohath shall encamp on the side of the tabernacle southward. ^30And the prince of the fathers' house of the families of the Kohathites shall be Elizaphan the son of Uzziel. ^31And their charge shall be the ark, and the table, and the candlestick, and the altars, and the vessels of the sanctuary wherewith they minister, and the screen, and all the service thereof. ^32And Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest shall be prince of the princes of the Levites, and have the oversight of them that keep the charge of the sanctuary.

^33Of Merari was the family of the Mahlites, and the family of the Mushites: these are the families of Merari. ^34And those that were numbered of them, according to the number of all the males, from a month old and upward, were six thousand and two hundred. ^35And the prince of the fathers' house of the families of Merari was Zuriel the son of Abihail: they shall encamp on the side of the tabernacle northward. ^36And the appointed charge of the sons of Merari shall be the boards of the tabernacle, and the bars thereof, and the pillars thereof, and the sockets thereof, and all the instruments thereof, and all the service thereof, ^37and the pillars of the court round about, and their sockets, and their pins, and their cords.

^38And those that encamp before the tabernacle eastward, before the tent of meeting toward the sunrising, shall be Moses, and Aaron and his sons, keeping the charge of the sanctuary for the charge of the children of Israel; and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death. ^39All that were numbered of the Levites, whom Moses and Aaron numbered at the commandment of Jehovah, by their families, all the males from a month old and upward, were twenty and two thousand.

^40And Jehovah said unto Moses, Number all the first-born males of the children of Israel from a month old and upward, and take the number of their names. ^41And thou shalt take the Levites for me (I am Jehovah) instead of all the first-born among the children of Israel; and the cattle of the Levites instead of all the firstlings among the cattle of the children of Israel: ^42and Moses numbered, as Jehovah commanded him, all the first-born among the children of Israel. ^43And all the first-born males according to the number of names, from a month old and upward, of those that were numbered of them, were twenty and two thousand two hundred and threescore and thirteen.

^44And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^45Take the Levites instead of all the first-born among the children of Israel, and the cattle of the Levites instead of their cattle; and the Levites shall be mine: I am Jehovah. ^46And for the redemption of the two hundred and threescore and thirteen of the first-born of the children of Israel, that are over and above the number of the Levites, ^47thou shalt take five shekels apiece by the poll; after the shekel of the sanctuary shalt thou take them (the shekel is twenty gerahs): ^48and thou shalt give the money, wherewith the odd number of them is redeemed, unto Aaron and to his sons. ^49And Moses took the redemption-money from them that were over and above them that were redeemed by the Levites; ^50from the first-born of the children of Israel took he the money, a thousand three hundred and threescore and five shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary: ^51and Moses gave the redemption-money unto Aaron and to his sons, according to the word of Jehovah, as Jehovah commanded Moses.

Numbers 4

4

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^2Take the sum of the sons of Kohath from among the sons of Levi, by their families, by their fathers' houses, ^3from thirty years old and upward even until fifty years old, all that enter upon the service, to do the work in the tent of meeting. ^4This is the service of the sons of Kohath in the tent of meeting, about the most holy things: ^5when the camp setteth forward, Aaron shall go in, and his sons, and they shall take down the veil of the screen, and cover the ark of the testimony with it, ^6and shall put thereon a covering of sealskin, and shall spread over it a cloth all of blue, and shall put in the staves thereof. ^7And upon the table of showbread they shall spread a cloth of blue, and put thereon the dishes, and the spoons, and the bowls and the cups wherewith to pour out; and the continual bread shall be thereon: ^8and they shall spread upon them a cloth of scarlet, and cover the same with a covering of sealskin, and shall put in the staves thereof. ^9And they shall take a cloth of blue, and cover the candlestick of the light, and its lamps, and its snuffers, and its snuffdishes, and all the oil vessels thereof, wherewith they minister unto it: ^10and they shall put it and all the vessels thereof within a covering of sealskin, and shall put it upon the frame. ^11And upon the golden altar they shall spread a cloth of blue, and cover it with a covering of sealskin, and shall put in the staves thereof: ^12and they shall take all the vessels of ministry, wherewith they minister in the sanctuary, and put them in a cloth of blue, and cover them with a covering of sealskin, and shall put them on the frame. ^13And they shall take away the ashes from the altar, and spread a purple cloth thereon: ^14and they shall put upon it all the vessels thereof, wherewith they minister about it, the firepans, the flesh-hooks, and the shovels, and the basins, all the vessels of the altar; and they shall spread upon it a covering of sealskin, and put in the staves thereof. ^15And when Aaron and his sons have made an end of covering the sanctuary, and all the furniture of the sanctuary, as the camp is set forward; after that, the sons of Kohath shall come to bear it: but they shall not touch the sanctuary, lest they die. These things are the burden of the sons of Kohath in the tent of meeting. ^16And the charge of Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest shall be the oil for the light, and the sweet incense, and the continual meal-offering, and the anointing oil, the charge of all the tabernacle, and of all that therein is, the sanctuary, and the furniture thereof.

^17And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^18Cut ye not off the tribe of the families of the Kohathites from among the Levites; ^19but thus do unto them, that they may live, and not die, when they approach unto the most holy things: Aaron and his sons shall go in, and appoint them every one to his service and to his burden; ^20but they shall not go in to see the sanctuary even for a moment, lest they die.

^21And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^22Take the sum of the sons of Gershon also, by their fathers' houses, by their families; ^23from thirty years old and upward until fifty years old shalt thou number them; all that enter in to wait upon the service, to do the work in the tent of meeting. ^24This is the service of the families of the Gershonites, in serving and in bearing burdens: ^25they shall bear the curtains of the tabernacle, and the tent of meeting, its covering, and the covering of sealskin that is above upon it, and the screen for the door of the tent of meeting, ^26and the hangings of the court, and the screen for the door of the gate of the court, which is by the tabernacle and by the altar round about, and their cords, and all the instruments of their service, and whatsoever shall be done with them: therein shall they serve. ^27At the commandment of Aaron and his sons shall be all the service of the sons of the Gershonites, in all their burden, and in all their service; and ye shall appoint unto them in charge all their burden. ^28This is the service of the families of the sons of the Gershonites in the tent of meeting: and their charge shall be under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.

^29As for the sons of Merari, thou shalt number them by their families, by their fathers' houses; ^30from thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old shalt thou number them, every one that entereth upon the service, to do the work of the tent of meeting. ^31And this is the charge of their burden, according to all their service in the tent of meeting: the boards of the tabernacle, and the bars thereof, and the pillars thereof, and the sockets thereof, ^32and the pillars of the court round about, and their sockets, and their pins, and their cords, with all their instruments, and with all their service: and by name ye shall appoint the instruments of the charge of their burden. ^33This is the service of the families of the sons of Merari, according to all their service, in the tent of meeting, under the hand of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.

^34And Moses and Aaron and the princes of the congregation numbered the sons of the Kohathites by their families, and by their fathers' houses, ^35from thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entered upon the service, for work in the tent of meeting: ^36and those that were numbered of them by their families were two thousand seven hundred and fifty. ^37These are they that were numbered of the families of the Kohathites, all that did serve in the tent of meeting, whom Moses and Aaron numbered according to the commandment of Jehovah by Moses. ^38And those that were numbered of the sons of Gershon, their families, and by their fathers' houses, ^39from thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entered upon the service, for work in the tent of meeting, ^40even those that were numbered of them, by their families, by their fathers' houses, were two thousand and six hundred and thirty. ^41These are they that were numbered of the families of the sons of Gershon, all that did serve in the tent of meeting, whom Moses and Aaron numbered according to the commandment of Jehovah.

^42And those that were numbered of the families of the sons of Merari, by their families, by their fathers' houses, ^43from thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entered upon the service, for work in the tent of meeting, ^44even those that were numbered of them by their families, were three thousand and two hundred. ^45These are they that were numbered of the families of the sons of Merari, whom Moses and Aaron numbered according to the commandment of Jehovah by Moses.

^46All those that were numbered of the Levites, whom Moses and Aaron and the princes of Israel numbered, by their families, and by their fathers' houses, ^47from thirty years old and upward even unto fifty years old, every one that entered in to do the work of service, and the work of bearing burdens in the tent of meeting, ^48even those that were numbered of them, were eight thousand and five hundred and fourscore. ^49According to the commandment of Jehovah they were numbered by Moses, every one according to his service, and according to his burden: thus were they numbered of him, as Jehovah commanded Moses.

Numbers 5

5

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Command the children of Israel, that they put out of the camp every leper, and every one that hath an issue, and whosoever is unclean by the dead: ^3both male and female shall ye put out, without the camp shall ye put them; that they defile not their camp, in the midst whereof I dwell. ^4And the children of Israel did so, and put them out without the camp; as Jehovah spake unto Moses, so did the children of Israel.

^5And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^6Speak unto the children of Israel, When a man or woman shall commit any sin that men commit, so as to trespass against Jehovah, and that soul shall be guilty; ^7then he shall confess his sin which he hath done: and he shall make restitution for his guilt in full, and add unto it the fifth part thereof, and give it unto him in respect of whom he hath been guilty. ^8But if the man have no kinsman to whom restitution may be made for the guilt, the restitution for guilt which is made unto Jehovah shall be the priest's; besides the ram of the atonement, whereby atonement shall be made for him. ^9And every heave-offering of all the holy things of the children of Israel, which they present unto the priest, shall be his. ^10And every man's hallowed things shall be his: whatsoever any man giveth the priest, it shall be his.

^11And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^12Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, If any man's wife go aside, and commit a trespass against him, ^13and a man lie with her carnally, and it be hid from the eyes of her husband, and be kept close, and she be defiled, and there be no witness against her, and she be not taken in the act; ^14and the spirit of jealousy come upon him, and he be jealous of his wife, and she be defiled: or if the spirit of jealousy come upon him, and he be jealous of his wife, and she be not defiled: ^15then shall the man bring his wife unto the priest, and shall bring her oblation for her, the tenth part of an ephah of barley meal; he shall pour no oil upon it, nor put frankincense thereon; for it is a meal-offering of jealousy, a meal-offering of memorial, bringing iniquity to remembrance.

^16And the priest shall bring her near, and set her before Jehovah: ^17and the priest shall take holy water in an earthen vessel; and of the dust that is on the floor of the tabernacle the priest shall take, and put it into the water. ^18And the priest shall set the woman before Jehovah, and let the hair of the woman's head go loose, and put the meal-offering of memorial in her hands, which is the meal-offering of jealousy: and the priest shall have in his hand the water of bitterness that causeth the curse. ^19And the priest shall cause her to swear, and shall say unto the woman, If no man have lain with thee, and if thou have not gone aside to uncleanness, being under thy husband, be thou free from this water of bitterness that causeth the curse. ^20But if thou have gone aside, being under thy husband, and if thou be defiled, and some man have lain with thee besides thy husband: ^21then the priest shall cause the woman to swear with the oath of cursing, and the priest shall say unto the woman, Jehovah make thee a curse and an oath among thy people, when Jehovah doth make thy thigh to fall away, and thy body to swell; ^22and this water that causeth the curse shall go into thy bowels, and make thy body to swell, and thy thigh to fall away. And the woman shall say, Amen, Amen.

^23And the priest shall write these curses in a book, and he shall blot them out into the water of bitterness: ^24and he shall make the woman drink the water of bitterness that causeth the curse; and the water that causeth the curse shall enter into her and become bitter. ^25And the priest shall take the meal-offering of jealousy out of the woman's hand, and shall wave the meal-offering before Jehovah, and bring it unto the altar: ^26and the priest shall take a handful of the meal-offering, as the memorial thereof, and burn it upon the altar, and afterward shall make the woman drink the water. ^27And when he hath made her drink the water, then it shall come to pass, if she be defiled, and have committed a trespass against her husband, that the water that causeth the curse shall enter into her and become bitter, and her body shall swell, and her thigh shall fall away: and the woman shall be a curse among her people. ^28And if the woman be not defiled, but be clean; then she shall be free, and shall conceive seed.

^29This is the law of jealousy, when a wife, being under her husband, goeth aside, and is defiled; ^30or when the spirit of jealousy cometh upon a man, and he is jealous of his wife; then shall he set the woman before Jehovah, and the priest shall execute upon her all this law. ^31And the man shall be free from iniquity, and that woman shall bear her iniquity.

Numbers 6

6

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When either man or woman shall make a special vow, the vow of a Nazirite, to separate himself unto Jehovah, ^3he shall separate himself from wine and strong drink; he shall drink no vinegar of wine, or vinegar of strong drink, neither shall he drink any juice of grapes, nor eat fresh grapes or dried. ^4All the days of his separation shall he eat nothing that is made of the grape-vine, from the kernels even to the husk.

^5All the days of his vow of separation there shall no razor come upon his head: until the days be fulfilled, in which he separateth himself unto Jehovah, he shall be holy; he shall let the locks of the hair of his head grow long.

^6All the days that he separateth himself unto Jehovah he shall not come near to a dead body. ^7He shall not make himself unclean for his father, or for his mother, for his brother, or for his sister, when they die; because his separation unto God is upon his head. ^8All the days of his separation he is holy unto Jehovah.

^9And if any man die very suddenly beside him, and he defile the head of his separation; then he shall shave his head in the day of his cleansing, on the seventh day shall he shave it. ^10And on the eighth day he shall bring two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, to the priest, to the door of the tent of meeting: ^11and the priest shall offer one for a sin-offering, and the other for a burnt-offering, and make atonement for him, for that he sinned by reason of the dead, and shall hallow his head that same day. ^12And he shall separate unto Jehovah the days of his separation, and shall bring a he-lamb a year old for a trespass-offering; but the former days shall be void, because his separation was defiled.

^13And this is the law of the Nazirite, when the days of his separation are fulfilled: he shall be brought unto the door of the tent of meeting: ^14and he shall offer his oblation unto Jehovah, one he-lamb a year old without blemish for a burnt-offering, and one ewe-lamb a year old without blemish for a sin-offering, and one ram without blemish for peace-offerings, ^15and a basket of unleavened bread, cakes of fine flour mingled with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and their meal-offering, and their drink-offerings. ^16And the priest shall present them before Jehovah, and shall offer his sin-offering, and his burnt-offering: ^17and he shall offer the ram for a sacrifice of peace-offerings unto Jehovah, with the basket of unleavened bread: the priest shall offer also the meal-offering thereof, and the drink-offering thereof. ^18And the Nazirite shall shave the head of his separation at the door of the tent of meeting, and shall take the hair of the head of his separation, and put it on the fire which is under the sacrifice of peace-offerings. ^19And the priest shall take the boiled shoulder of the ram, and one unleavened cake out of the basket, and one unleavened wafer, and shall put them upon the hands of the Nazirite, after he hath shaven the head of his separation; ^20and the priest shall wave them for a wave-offering before Jehovah; this is holy for the priest, together with the wave-breast and heave-thigh: and after that the Nazirite may drink wine.

^21This is the law of the Nazirite who voweth, and of his oblation unto Jehovah for his separation, besides that which he is able to get: according to his vow which he voweth, so he must do after the law of his separation.

^22And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^23Speak unto Aaron and unto his sons, saying, On this wise ye shall bless the children of Israel: ye shall say unto them,

^24Jehovah bless thee, and keep thee:

^25Jehovah make his face to shine upon thee, and be gracious unto thee:

^26Jehovah lift up his countenance upon thee, and give thee peace.

^27So shall they put my name upon the children of Israel; and I will bless them.

Numbers 8

8

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto Aaron, and say unto him, When thou lightest the lamps, the seven lamps shall give light in front of the candlestick. ^3And Aaron did so; he lighted the lamps thereof so as to give light in front of the candlestick, as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^4And this was the work of the candlestick, beaten work of gold; unto the base thereof, and unto the flowers thereof, it was beaten work: according unto the pattern which Jehovah had showed Moses, so he made the candlestick.

^5And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^6Take the Levites from among the children of Israel, and cleanse them. ^7And thus shalt thou do unto them, to cleanse them: sprinkle the water of expiation upon them, and let them cause a razor to pass over all their flesh, and let them wash their clothes, and cleanse themselves. ^8Then let them take a young bullock, and its meal-offering, fine flour mingled with oil; and another young bullock shalt thou take for a sin-offering. ^9And thou shalt present the Levites before the tent of meeting: and thou shalt assemble the whole congregation of the children of Israel: ^10and thou shalt present the Levites before Jehovah. And the children of Israel shall lay their hands upon the Levites: ^11and Aaron shall offer the Levites before Jehovah for a wave-offering, on the behalf of the children of Israel, that it may be theirs to do the service of Jehovah. ^12And the Levites shall lay their hands upon the heads of the bullocks: and offer thou the one for a sin-offering, and the other for a burnt-offering, unto Jehovah, to make atonement for the Levites. ^13And thou shalt set the Levites before Aaron, and before his sons, and offer them for a wave-offering unto Jehovah.

^14Thus shalt thou separate the Levites from among the children of Israel; and the Levites shall be mine. ^15And after that shall the Levites go in to do the service of the tent of meeting: and thou shalt cleanse them, and offer them for a wave-offering. ^16For they are wholly given unto me from among the children of Israel; instead of all that openeth the womb, even the first-born of all the children of Israel, have I taken them unto me. ^17For all the first-born among the children of Israel are mine, both man and beast: on the day that I smote all the first-born in the land of Egypt I sanctified them for myself. ^18And I have taken the Levites instead of all the first-born among the children of Israel. ^19And I have given the Levites as a gift to Aaron and to his sons from among the children of Israel, to do the service of the children of Israel in the tent of meeting, and to make atonement for the children of Israel; that there be no plague among the children of Israel, when the children of Israel come nigh unto the sanctuary.

^20Thus did Moses, and Aaron, and all the congregation of the children of Israel, unto the Levites: according unto all that Jehovah commanded Moses touching the Levites, so did the children of Israel unto them. ^21And the Levites purified themselves from sin, and they washed their clothes: and Aaron offered them for a wave-offering before Jehovah; and Aaron made atonement for them to cleanse them. ^22And after that went the Levites in to do their service in the tent of meeting before Aaron, and before his sons: as Jehovah had commanded Moses concerning the Levites, so did they unto them.

^23And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^24This is that which belongeth unto the Levites: from twenty and five years old and upward they shall go in to wait upon the service in the work of the tent of meeting: ^25and from the age of fifty years they shall cease waiting upon the work, and shall serve no more, ^26but shall minister with their brethren in the tent of meeting, to keep the charge, and shall do no service. Thus shalt thou do unto the Levites touching their charges.

Numbers 9

9

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the first month of the second year after they were come out of the land of Egypt, saying, ^2Moreover let the children of Israel keep the passover in its appointed season. ^3In the fourteenth day of this month, at even, ye shall keep it in its appointed season: according to all the statutes of it, and according to all the ordinances thereof, shall ye keep it. ^4And Moses spake unto the children of Israel, that they should keep the passover. ^5And they kept the passover in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, at even, in the wilderness of Sinai: according to all that Jehovah commanded Moses, so did the children of Israel. ^6And there were certain men, who were unclean by reason of the dead body of a man, so that they could not keep the passover on that day: and they came before Moses and before Aaron on that day: ^7and those men said unto him, We are unclean by reason of the dead body of a man: wherefore are we kept back, that we may not offer the oblation of Jehovah in its appointed season among the children of Israel? ^8And Moses said unto them, Stay ye, that I may hear what Jehovah will command concerning you.

^9And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^10Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If any man of you or of your generations shall be unclean by reason of a dead body, or be on a journey afar off, yet he shall keep the passover unto Jehovah. ^11In the second month on the fourteenth day at even they shall keep it; they shall eat it with unleavened bread and bitter herbs: ^12they shall leave none of it unto the morning, nor break a bone thereof: according to all the statute of the passover they shall keep it. ^13But the man that is clean, and is not on a journey, and forbeareth to keep the passover, that soul shall be cut off from his people; because he offered not the oblation of Jehovah in its appointed season, that man shall bear his sin. ^14And if a stranger shall sojourn among you, and will keep the passover unto Jehovah; according to the statute of the passover, and according to the ordinance thereof, so shall he do: ye shall have one statute, both for the sojourner, and for him that is born in the land.

^15And on the day that the tabernacle was reared up the cloud covered the tabernacle, even the tent of the testimony: and at even it was upon the tabernacle as it were the appearance of fire, until morning. ^16So it was alway: the cloud covered it, and the appearance of fire by night. ^17And whenever the cloud was taken up from over the Tent, then after that the children of Israel journeyed: and in the place where the cloud abode, there the children of Israel encamped. ^18At the commandment of Jehovah the children of Israel journeyed, and at the commandment of Jehovah they encamped: as long as the cloud abode upon the tabernacle they remained encamped. ^19And when the cloud tarried upon the tabernacle many days, then the children of Israel kept the charge of Jehovah, and journeyed not. ^20And sometimes the cloud was a few days upon the tabernacle; then according to the commandment of Jehovah they remained encamped, and according to the commandment of Jehovah they journeyed. ^21And sometimes the cloud was from evening until morning; and when the cloud was taken up in the morning, they journeyed: or if it continued by day and by night, when the cloud was taken up, they journeyed. ^22Whether it were two days, or a month, or a year, that the cloud tarried upon the tabernacle, abiding thereon, the children of Israel remained encamped, and journeyed not; but when it was taken up, they journeyed. ^23At the commandment of Jehovah they encamped, and at the commandment of Jehovah they journeyed: they kept the charge of Jehovah, at the commandment of Jehovah by Moses.

Numbers 10

10

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Make thee two trumpets of silver; of beaten work shalt thou make them: and thou shalt use them for the calling of the congregation, and for the journeying of the camps. ^3And when they shall blow them, all the congregation shall gather themselves unto thee at the door of the tent of meeting. ^4And if they blow but one, then the princes, the heads of the thousands of Israel, shall gather themselves unto thee. ^5And when ye blow an alarm, the camps that lie on the east side shall take their journey. ^6And when ye blow an alarm the second time, the camps that lie on the south side shall take their journey: they shall blow an alarm for their journeys. ^7But when the assembly is to be gathered together, ye shall blow, but ye shall not sound an alarm. ^8And the sons of Aaron, the priests, shall blow the trumpets; and they shall be to you for a statute for ever throughout your generations. ^9And when ye go to war in your land against the adversary that oppresseth you, then ye shall sound an alarm with the trumpets; and ye shall be remembered before Jehovah your God, and ye shall be saved from your enemies. ^10Also in the day of your gladness, and in your set feasts, and in the beginnings of your months, ye shall blow the trumpets over your burnt-offerings, and over the sacrifices of your peace-offerings; and they shall be to you for a memorial before your God: I am Jehovah your God.

^11And it came to pass in the second year, in the second month, on the twentieth day of the month, that the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle of the testimony. ^12And the children of Israel set forward according to their journeys out of the wilderness of Sinai; and the cloud abode in the wilderness of Paran. ^13And they first took their journey according to the commandment of Jehovah by Moses. ^14And in the first place the standard of the camp of the children of Judah set forward according to their hosts: and over his host was Nahshon the son of Amminadab. ^15And over the host of the tribe of the children of Issachar was Nethanel the son of Zuar. ^16And over the host of the tribe of the children of Zebulun was Eliab the son of Helon. ^17And the tabernacle was taken down; and the sons of Gershon and the sons of Merari, who bare the tabernacle, set forward. ^18And the standard of the camp of Reuben set forward according to their hosts: and over his host was Elizur the son of Shedeur. ^19And over the host of the tribe of the children of Simeon was Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai. ^20And over the host of the tribe of the children of Gad was Eliasaph the son of Deuel.

^21And the Kohathites set forward, bearing the sanctuary: and the others did set up the tabernacle against their coming. ^22And the standard of the camp of the children of Ephraim set forward according to their hosts: and over his host was Elishama the son of Ammihud. ^23And over the host of the tribe of the children of Manasseh was Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur. ^24And over the host of the tribe of the children of Benjamin was Abidan the son of Gideoni.

^25And the standard of the camp of the children of Dan, which was the rearward of all the camps, set forward according to their hosts: and over his host was Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai. ^26And over the host of the tribe of the children of Asher was Pagiel the son of Ochran. ^27And over the host of the tribe of the children of Naphtali was Ahira the son of Enan. ^28Thus were the journeyings of the children of Israel according to their hosts; and they set forward.

^29And Moses said unto Hobab, the son of Reuel the Midianite, Moses' father-in-law, We are journeying unto the place of which Jehovah said, I will give it you: come thou with us, and we will do thee good; for Jehovah hath spoken good concerning Israel. ^30And he said unto him, I will not go; but I will depart to mine own land, and to my kindred. ^31And he said, Leave us not, I pray thee; forasmuch as thou knowest how we are to encamp in the wilderness, and thou shalt be to us instead of eyes. ^32And it shall be, if thou go with us, yea, it shall be, that what good soever Jehovah shall do unto us, the same will we do unto thee.

^33And they set forward from the mount of Jehovah three days' journey; and the ark of the covenant of Jehovah went before them three days' journey, to seek out a resting-place for them. ^34And the cloud of Jehovah was over them by day, when they set forward from the camp. ^35And it came to pass, when the ark set forward, that Moses said, Rise up, O Jehovah, and let thine enemies be scattered; and let them that hate thee flee before thee. ^36And when it rested, he said, Return, O Jehovah, unto the ten thousands of the thousands of Israel.

Numbers 11

11

^1And the people were as murmurers, speaking evil in the ears of Jehovah: and when Jehovah heard it, his anger was kindled; and the fire of Jehovah burnt among them, and devoured in the uttermost part of the camp. ^2And the people cried unto Moses; and Moses prayed unto Jehovah, and the fire abated. ^3And the name of that place was called Taberah, because the fire of Jehovah burnt among them.

^4And the mixed multitude that was among them lusted exceedingly: and the children of Israel also wept again, and said, Who shall give us flesh to eat? ^5We remember the fish, which we did eat in Egypt for nought; the cucumbers, and the melons, and the leeks, and the onions, and the garlic: ^6but now our soul is dried away; there is nothing at all save this manna to look upon. ^7And the manna was like coriander seed, and the appearance thereof as the appearance of bdellium. ^8The people went about, and gathered it, and ground it in mills, or beat it in mortars, and boiled it in pots, and made cakes of it: and the taste of it was as the taste of fresh oil. ^9And when the dew fell upon the camp in the night, the manna fell upon it. ^10And Moses heard the people weeping throughout their families, every man at the door of his tent: and the anger of Jehovah was kindled greatly; and Moses was displeased. ^11And Moses said unto Jehovah, Wherefore hast thou dealt ill with thy servant? and wherefore have I not found favor in thy sight, that thou layest the burden of all this people upon me? ^12Have I conceived all this people? have I brought them forth, that thou shouldest say unto me, Carry them in thy bosom, as a nursing-father carrieth the sucking child, unto the land which thou swarest unto their fathers? ^13Whence should I have flesh to give unto all this people? for they weep unto me, saying, Give us flesh, that we may eat. ^14I am not able to bear all this people alone, because it is too heavy for me. ^15And if thou deal thus with me, kill me, I pray thee, out of hand, if I have found favor in thy sight; and let me not see my wretchedness.

^16And Jehovah said unto Moses, Gather unto me seventy men of the elders of Israel, whom thou knowest to be the elders of the people, and officers over them; and bring them unto the tent of meeting, that they may stand there with thee. ^17And I will come down and talk with thee there: and I will take of the Spirit which is upon thee, and will put it upon them; and they shall bear the burden of the people with thee, that thou bear it not thyself alone. ^18And say thou unto the people, Sanctify yourselves against to-morrow, and ye shall eat flesh; for ye have wept in the ears of Jehovah, saying, Who shall give us flesh to eat? for it was well with us in Egypt: therefore Jehovah will give you flesh, and ye shall eat. ^19Ye shall not eat one day, nor two days, nor five days, neither ten days, nor twenty days, ^20but a whole month, until it come out at your nostrils, and it be loathsome unto you; because that ye have rejected Jehovah who is among you, and have wept before him, saying, Why came we forth out of Egypt? ^21And Moses said, The people, among whom I am, are six hundred thousand footmen; and thou hast said, I will give them flesh, that they may eat a whole month. ^22Shall flocks and herds be slain for them, to suffice them? or shall all the fish of the sea be gathered together for them, to suffice them? ^23And Jehovah said unto Moses, Is Jehovah's hand waxed short? now shalt thou see whether my word shall come to pass unto thee or not.

^24And Moses went out, and told the people the words of Jehovah: and he gathered seventy men of the elders of the people, and set them round about the Tent. ^25And Jehovah came down in the cloud, and spake unto him, and took of the Spirit that was upon him, and put it upon the seventy elders: and it came to pass, that, when the Spirit rested upon them, they prophesied, but they did so no more.

^26But there remained two men in the camp, the name of the one was Eldad, and the name of the other Medad: and the Spirit rested upon them; and they were of them that were written, but had not gone out unto the Tent; and they prophesied in the camp. ^27And there ran a young man, and told Moses, and said, Eldad and Medad do prophesy in the camp. ^28And Joshua the son of Nun, the minister of Moses, one of his chosen men, answered and said, My lord Moses, forbid them. ^29And Moses said unto him, Art thou jealous for my sake? would that all Jehovah's people were prophets, that Jehovah would put his Spirit upon them! ^30And Moses gat him into the camp, he and the elders of Israel.

^31And there went forth a wind from Jehovah, and brought quails from the sea, and let them fall by the camp, about a day's journey on this side, and a day's journey on the other side, round about the camp, and about two cubits above the face of the earth. ^32And the people rose up all that day, and all the night, and all the next day, and gathered the quails: he that gathered least gathered ten homers: and they spread them all abroad for themselves round about the camp. ^33While the flesh was yet between their teeth, ere it was chewed, the anger of Jehovah was kindled against the people, and Jehovah smote the people with a very great plague. ^34And the name of that place was called Kibrothhattaavah, because there they buried the people that lusted. ^35From Kibrothhattaavah the people journeyed unto Hazeroth; and they abode at Hazeroth.

Numbers 12

12

^1And Miriam and Aaron spake against Moses because of the Cushite woman whom he had married; for he had married a Cushite woman. ^2And they said, Hath Jehovah indeed spoken only with Moses? hath he not spoken also with us? And Jehovah heard it. ^3Now the man Moses was very meek, above all the men that were upon the face of the earth.

^4And Jehovah spake suddenly unto Moses, and unto Aaron, and unto Miriam, Come out ye three unto the tent of meeting. And they three came out. ^5And Jehovah came down in a pillar of cloud, and stood at the door of the Tent, and called Aaron and Miriam; and they both came forth. ^6And he said, Hear now my words: if there be a prophet among you, I Jehovah will make myself known unto him in a vision, I will speak with him in a dream. ^7My servant Moses is not so; he is faithful in all my house: ^8with him will I speak mouth to mouth, even manifestly, and not in dark speeches; and the form of Jehovah shall he behold: wherefore then were ye not afraid to speak against my servant, against Moses?

^9And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against them; and he departed. ^10And the cloud removed from over the Tent; and, behold, Miriam was leprous, as white as snow: and Aaron looked upon Miriam, and, behold, she was leprous. ^11And Aaron said unto Moses, Oh, my lord, lay not, I pray thee, sin upon us, for that we have done foolishly, and for that we have sinned. ^12Let her not, I pray, be as one dead, of whom the flesh is half consumed when he cometh out of his mother's womb. ^13And Moses cried unto Jehovah, saying, Heal her, O God, I beseech thee. ^14And Jehovah said unto Moses, If her father had but spit in her face, should she not be ashamed seven days? let her be shut up without the camp seven days, and after that she shall be brought in again. ^15And Miriam was shut up without the camp seven days: and the people journeyed not till Miriam was brought in again.

^16And afterward the people journeyed from Hazeroth, and encamped in the wilderness of Paran.

Numbers 13

13

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Send thou men, that they may spy out the land of Canaan, which I give unto the children of Israel: of every tribe of their fathers shall ye send a man, every one a prince among them. ^3And Moses sent them from the wilderness of Paran according to the commandment of Jehovah: all of them men who were heads of the children of Israel. ^4And these were their names: Of the tribe of Reuben, Shammua the son of Zaccur. ^5Of the tribe of Simeon, Shaphat the son of Hori. ^6Of the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh. ^7Of the tribe of Issachar, Igal the son of Joseph. ^8Of the tribe of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Nun. ^9Of the tribe of Benjamin, Palti the son of Raphu. ^10Of the tribe of Zebulun, Gaddiel the son of Sodi. ^11Of the tribe of Joseph, namely, of the tribe of Manasseh, Gaddi the son of Susi. ^12Of the tribe of Dan, Ammiel the son of Gemalli. ^13Of the tribe of Asher, Sethur the son of Michael. ^14Of the tribe of Naphtali, Nahbi the son of Vophsi. ^15Of the tribe of Gad, Geuel the son of Machi. ^16These are the names of the men that Moses sent to spy out the land. And Moses called Hoshea the son of Nun Joshua.

^17And Moses sent them to spy out the land of Canaan, and said unto them, Get you up this way by the South, and go up into the hill-country: ^18and see the land, what it is; and the people that dwell therein, whether they are strong or weak, whether they are few or many; ^19and what the land is that they dwell in, whether it is good or bad; and what cities they are that they dwell in, whether in camps, or in strongholds; ^20and what the land is, whether it is fat or lean, whether there is wood therein, or not. And be ye of good courage, and bring of the fruit of the land. Now the time was the time of the first-ripe grapes.

^21So they went up, and spied out the land from the wilderness of Zin unto Rehob, to the entrance of Hamath. ^22And they went up by the South, and came unto Hebron; and Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai, the children of Anak, were there. (Now Hebron was built seven years before Zoan in Egypt.) ^23And they came unto the valley of Eshcol, and cut down from thence a branch with one cluster of grapes, and they bare it upon a staff between two; they brought also of the pomegranates, and of the figs. ^24That place was called the valley of Eshcol, because of the cluster which the children of Israel cut down from thence.

^25And they returned from spying out the land at the end of forty days. ^26And they went and came to Moses, and to Aaron, and to all the congregation of the children of Israel, unto the wilderness of Paran, to Kadesh; and brought back word unto them, and unto all the congregation, and showed them the fruit of the land. ^27And they told him, and said, We came unto the land whither thou sentest us; and surely it floweth with milk and honey; and this is the fruit of it. ^28Howbeit the people that dwell in the land are strong, and the cities are fortified, and very great: and moreover we saw the children of Anak there. ^29Amalek dwelleth in the land of the South: and the Hittite, and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, dwell in the hill-country; and the Canaanite dwelleth by the sea, and along by the side of the Jordan.

^30And Caleb stilled the people before Moses, and said, Let us go up at once, and possess it; for we are well able to overcome it. ^31But the men that went up with him said, We are not able to go up against the people; for they are stronger than we. ^32And they brought up an evil report of the land which they had spied out unto the children of Israel, saying, The land, through which we have gone to spy it out, is a land that eateth up the inhabitants thereof; and all the people that we saw in it are men of great stature. ^33And there we saw the Nephilim, the sons of Anak, who come of the Nephilim: and we were in our own sight as grasshoppers, and so we were in their sight.

Numbers 14

14

^1And all the congregation lifted up their voice, and cried; and the people wept that night. ^2And all the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron: and the whole congregation said unto them, Would that we had died in the land of Egypt! or would that we had died in this wilderness! ^3And wherefore doth Jehovah bring us unto this land, to fall by the sword? Our wives and our little ones will be a prey: were it not better for us to return into Egypt?

^4And they said one to another, Let us make a captain, and let us return into Egypt. ^5Then Moses and Aaron fell on their faces before all the assembly of the congregation of the children of Israel. ^6And Joshua the son of Nun and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, who were of them that spied out the land, rent their clothes: ^7and they spake unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, The land, which we passed through to spy it out, is an exceeding good land. ^8If Jehovah delight in us, then he will bring us into this land, and give it unto us; a land which floweth with milk and honey. ^9Only rebel not against Jehovah, neither fear ye the people of the land; for they are bread for us: their defence is removed from over them, and Jehovah is with us: fear them not. ^10But all the congregation bade stone them with stones. And the glory of Jehovah appeared in the tent of meeting unto all the children of Israel.

^11And Jehovah said unto Moses, How long will this people despise me? and how long will they not believe in me, for all the signs which I have wrought among them? ^12I will smite them with the pestilence, and disinherit them, and will make of thee a nation greater and mightier than they.

^13And Moses said unto Jehovah, Then the Egyptians will hear it; for thou broughtest up this people in thy might from among them; ^14and they will tell it to the inhabitants of this land. They have heard that thou Jehovah art in the midst of this people; for thou Jehovah art seen face to face, and thy cloud standeth over them, and thou goest before them, in a pillar of cloud by day, and in a pillar of fire by night. ^15Now if thou shalt kill this people as one man, then the nations which have heard the fame of thee will speak, saying, ^16Because Jehovah was not able to bring this people into the land which he sware unto them, therefore he hath slain them in the wilderness. ^17And now, I pray thee, let the power of the Lord be great, according as thou hast spoken, saying, ^18Jehovah is slow to anger, and abundant in lovingkindness, forgiving iniquity and transgression; and that will by no means clear the guilty, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, upon the third and upon the fourth generation. ^19Pardon, I pray thee, the iniquity of this people according unto the greatness of thy lovingkindness, and according as thou hast forgiven this people, from Egypt even until now.

^20And Jehovah said, I have pardoned according to thy word: ^21but in very deed, as I live, and as all the earth shall be filled with the glory of Jehovah; ^22because all those men that have seen my glory, and my signs, which I wrought in Egypt and in the wilderness, yet have tempted me these ten times, and have not hearkened to my voice; ^23surely they shall not see the land which I sware unto their fathers, neither shall any of them that despised me see it: ^24but my servant Caleb, because he had another spirit with him, and hath followed me fully, him will I bring into the land whereinto he went; and his seed shall possess it. ^25Now the Amalekite and the Canaanite dwell in the valley: to-morrow turn ye, and get you into the wilderness by the way to the Red Sea.

^26And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^27How long shall I bear with this evil congregation, that murmur against me? I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel, which they murmur against me. ^28Say unto them, As I live, saith Jehovah, surely as ye have spoken in mine ears, so will I do to you: ^29your dead bodies shall fall in this wilderness; and all that were numbered of you, according to your whole number, from twenty years old and upward, that have murmured against me, ^30surely ye shall not come into the land, concerning which I sware that I would make you dwell therein, save Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun. ^31But your little ones, that ye said should be a prey, them will I bring in, and they shall know the land which ye have rejected. ^32But as for you, your dead bodies shall fall in this wilderness. ^33And your children shall be wanderers in the wilderness forty years, and shall bear your whoredoms, until your dead bodies be consumed in the wilderness. ^34After the number of the days in which ye spied out the land, even forty days, for every day a year, shall ye bear your iniquities, even forty years, and ye shall know my alienation. ^35I, Jehovah, have spoken, surely this will I do unto all this evil congregation, that are gathered together against me: in this wilderness they shall be consumed, and there they shall die.

^36And the men, whom Moses sent to spy out the land, who returned, and made all the congregation to murmur against him, by bringing up an evil report against the land, ^37even those men that did bring up an evil report of the land, died by the plague before Jehovah. ^38But Joshua the son of Nun, and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, remained alive of those men that went to spy out the land.

^39And Moses told these words unto all the children of Israel: and the people mourned greatly. ^40And they rose up early in the morning, and gat them up to the top of the mountain, saying, Lo, we are here, and will go up unto the place which Jehovah hath promised: for we have sinned. ^41And Moses said, Wherefore now do ye transgress the commandment of Jehovah, seeing it shall not prosper? ^42Go not up, for Jehovah is not among you; that ye be not smitten down before your enemies. ^43For there the Amalekite and the Canaanite are before you, and ye shall fall by the sword: because ye are turned back from following Jehovah, therefore Jehovah will not be with you. ^44But they presumed to go up to the top of the mountain: nevertheless the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and Moses, departed not out of the camp. ^45Then the Amalekite came down, and the Canaanite who dwelt in that mountain, and smote them and beat them down, even unto Hormah.

Numbers 15

15

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye are come into the land of your habitations, which I give unto you, ^3and will make an offering by fire unto Jehovah, a burnt-offering, or a sacrifice, to accomplish a vow, or as a freewill-offering, or in your set feasts, to make a sweet savor unto Jehovah, of the herd, or of the flock; ^4then shall he that offereth his oblation offer unto Jehovah a meal-offering of a tenth part of an ephah of fine flour mingled with the fourth part of a hin of oil: ^5and wine for the drink-offering, the fourth part of a hin, shalt thou prepare with the burnt-offering, or for the sacrifice, for each lamb. ^6Or for a ram, thou shalt prepare for a meal-offering two tenth parts of an ephah of fine flour mingled with the third part of a hin of oil: ^7and for the drink-offering thou shalt offer the third part of a hin of wine, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^8And when thou preparest a bullock for a burnt-offering, or for a sacrifice, to accomplish a vow, or for peace-offerings unto Jehovah; ^9then shall he offer with the bullock a meal-offering of three tenth parts of an ephah of fine flour mingled with half a hin of oil: ^10and thou shalt offer for the drink-offering half a hin of wine, for an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah.

^11Thus shall it be done for each bullock, or for each ram, or for each of the he-lambs, or of the kids. ^12According to the number that ye shall prepare, so shall ye do to every one according to their number. ^13All that are home-born shall do these things after this manner, in offering an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^14And if a stranger sojourn with you, or whosoever may be among you throughout your generations, and will offer an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah; as ye do, so he shall do. ^15For the assembly, there shall be one statute for you, and for the stranger that sojourneth with you, a statute for ever throughout your generations: as ye are, so shall the sojourner be before Jehovah. ^16One law and one ordinance shall be for you, and for the stranger that sojourneth with you.

^17And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^18Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land whither I bring you, ^19then it shall be, that, when ye eat of the bread of the land, ye shall offer up a heave-offering unto Jehovah. ^20Of the first of your dough ye shall offer up a cake for a heave-offering: as the heave-offering of the threshing-floor, so shall ye heave it. ^21Of the first of your dough ye shall give unto Jehovah a heave-offering throughout your generations.

^22And when ye shall err, and not observe all these commandments, which Jehovah hath spoken unto Moses, ^23even all that Jehovah hath commanded you by Moses, from the day that Jehovah gave commandment, and onward throughout your generations; ^24then it shall be, if it be done unwittingly, without the knowledge of the congregation, that all the congregation shall offer one young bullock for a burnt-offering, for a sweet savor unto Jehovah, with the meal-offering thereof, and the drink-offering thereof, according to the ordinance, and one he-goat for a sin-offering. ^25And the priest shall make atonement for all the congregation of the children of Israel, and they shall be forgiven; for it was an error, and they have brought their oblation, an offering made by fire unto Jehovah, and their sin-offering before Jehovah, for their error: ^26and all the congregation of the children of Israel shall be forgiven, and the stranger that sojourneth among them; for in respect of all the people it was done unwittingly.

^27And if one person sin unwittingly, then he shall offer a she-goat a year old for a sin-offering. ^28And the priest shall make atonement for the soul that erreth, when he sinneth unwittingly, before Jehovah, to make atonement for him; and he shall be forgiven. ^29Ye shall have one law for him that doeth aught unwittingly, for him that is home-born among the children of Israel, and for the stranger that sojourneth among them. ^30But the soul that doeth aught with a high hand, whether he be home-born or a sojourner, the same blasphemeth Jehovah; and that soul shall be cut off from among his people. ^31Because he hath despised the word of Jehovah, and hath broken his commandment, that soul shall utterly be cut off; his iniquity shall be upon him.

^32And while the children of Israel were in the wilderness, they found a man gathering sticks upon the sabbath day. ^33And they that found him gathering sticks brought him unto Moses and Aaron, and unto all the congregation. ^34And they put him in ward, because it had not been declared what should be done to him. ^35And Jehovah said unto Moses, The man shall surely be put to death: all the congregation shall stone him with stones without the camp. ^36And all the congregation brought him without the camp, and stoned him to death with stones; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^37And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^38Speak unto the children of Israel, and bid them that they make them fringes in the borders of their garments throughout their generations, and that they put upon the fringe of each border a cord of blue: ^39and it shall be unto you for a fringe, that ye may look upon it, and remember all the commandments of Jehovah, and do them; and that ye follow not after your own heart and your own eyes, after which ye use to play the harlot; ^40that ye may remember and do all my commandments, and be holy unto your God. ^41I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am Jehovah your God.

Numbers 16

16

^1Now Korah, the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, with Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, and On, the son of Peleth, sons of Reuben, took men: ^2and they rose up before Moses, with certain of the children of Israel, two hundred and fifty princes of the congregation, called to the assembly, men of renown; ^3and they assembled themselves together against Moses and against Aaron, and said unto them, Ye take too much upon you, seeing all the congregation are holy, every one of them, and Jehovah is among them: wherefore then lift ye up yourselves above the assembly of Jehovah?

^4And when Moses heard it, he fell upon his face: ^5and he spake unto Korah and unto all his company, saying, In the morning Jehovah will show who are his, and who is holy, and will cause him to come near unto him: even him whom he shall choose will he cause to come near unto him. ^6This do: take you censers, Korah, and all his company; ^7and put fire in them, and put incense upon them before Jehovah to-morrow: and it shall be that the man whom Jehovah doth choose, he shall be holy: ye take too much upon you, ye sons of Levi. ^8And Moses said unto Korah, Hear now, ye sons of Levi: ^9seemeth it but a small thing unto you, that the God of Israel hath separated you from the congregation of Israel, to bring you near to himself, to do the service of the tabernacle of Jehovah, and to stand before the congregation to minister unto them; ^10and that he hath brought thee near, and all thy brethren the sons of Levi with thee? and seek ye the priesthood also? ^11Therefore thou and all thy company are gathered together against Jehovah: and Aaron, what is he that ye murmur against him?

^12And Moses sent to call Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab; and they said, We will not come up: ^13is it a small thing that thou hast brought us up out of a land flowing with milk and honey, to kill us in the wilderness, but thou must needs make thyself also a prince over us? ^14Moreover thou hast not brought us into a land flowing with milk and honey, nor given us inheritance of fields and vineyards: wilt thou put out the eyes of these men? we will not come up.

^15And Moses was very wroth, and said unto Jehovah, Respect not thou their offering: I have not taken one ass from them, neither have I hurt one of them. ^16And Moses said unto Korah, Be thou and all thy company before Jehovah, thou, and they, and Aaron, to-morrow: ^17and take ye every man his censer, and put incense upon them, and bring ye before Jehovah every man his censer, two hundred and fifty censers; thou also, and Aaron, each his censer. ^18And they took every man his censer, and put fire in them, and laid incense thereon, and stood at the door of the tent of meeting with Moses and Aaron. ^19And Korah assembled all the congregation against them unto the door of the tent of meeting: and the glory of Jehovah appeared unto all the congregation.

^20And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^21Separate yourselves from among this congregation, that I may consume them in a moment. ^22And they fell upon their faces, and said, O God, the God of the spirits of all flesh, shall one man sin, and wilt thou be wroth with all the congregation? ^23And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^24Speak unto the congregation, saying, Get you up from about the tabernacle of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram.

^25And Moses rose up and went unto Dathan and Abiram; and the elders of Israel followed him. ^26And he spake unto the congregation, saying, Depart, I pray you, from the tents of these wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, lest ye be consumed in all their sins. ^27So they gat them up from the tabernacle of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, on every side: and Dathan and Abiram came out, and stood at the door of their tents, and their wives, and their sons, and their little ones. ^28And Moses said, Hereby ye shall know that Jehovah hath sent me to do all these works; for I have not done them of mine own mind. ^29If these men die the common death of all men, or if they be visited after the visitation of all men; then Jehovah hath not sent me. ^30But if Jehovah make a new thing, and the ground open its mouth, and swallow them up, with all that appertain unto them, and they go down alive into Sheol; then ye shall understand that these men have despised Jehovah.

^31And it came to pass, as he made an end of speaking all these words, that the ground clave asunder that was under them; ^32and the earth opened its mouth, and swallowed them up, and their households, and all the men that appertained unto Korah, and all their goods. ^33So they, and all that appertained to them, went down alive into Sheol: and the earth closed upon them, and they perished from among the assembly. ^34And all Israel that were round about them fled at the cry of them; for they said, Lest the earth swallow us up. ^35And fire came forth from Jehovah, and devoured the two hundred and fifty men that offered the incense.

^36And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^37Speak unto Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, that he take up the censers out of the burning, and scatter thou the fire yonder; for they are holy, ^38even the censers of these sinners against their own lives; and let them be made beaten plates for a covering of the altar: for they offered them before Jehovah; therefore they are holy; and they shall be a sign unto the children of Israel. ^39And Eleazar the priest took the brazen censers, which they that were burnt had offered; and they beat them out for a covering of the altar, ^40to be a memorial unto the children of Israel, to the end that no stranger, that is not of the seed of Aaron, come near to burn incense before Jehovah; that he be not as Korah, and as his company: as Jehovah spake unto him by Moses.

^41But on the morrow all the congregation of the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron, saying, Ye have killed the people of Jehovah. ^42And it came to pass, when the congregation was assembled against Moses and against Aaron, that they looked toward the tent of meeting: and, behold, the cloud covered it, and the glory of Jehovah appeared. ^43And Moses and Aaron came to the front of the tent of meeting. ^44And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^45Get you up from among this congregation, that I may consume them in a moment. And they fell upon their faces. ^46And Moses said unto Aaron, Take they censer, and put fire therein from off the altar, and lay incense thereon, and carry it quickly unto the congregation, and make atonement for them: for there is wrath gone out from Jehovah; the plague is begun. ^47And Aaron took as Moses spake, and ran into the midst of the assembly; and, behold, the plague was begun among the people: and he put on the incense, and made atonement for the people. ^48And he stood between the dead and the living; and the plague was stayed. ^49Now they that died by the plague were fourteen thousand and seven hundred, besides them that died about the matter of Korah. ^50And Aaron returned unto Moses unto the door of the tent of meeting: and the plague was stayed.

Numbers 17

17

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, and take of them rods, one for each fathers' house, of all their princes according to their fathers' houses, twelve rods: write thou every man's name upon his rod. ^3And thou shalt write Aaron's name upon the rod of Levi; for there shall be one rod for each head of their fathers' houses. ^4And thou shalt lay them up in the tent of meeting before the testimony, where I meet with you. ^5And it shall come to pass, that the rod of the man whom I shall choose shall bud: and I will make to cease from me the murmurings of the children of Israel, which they murmur against you. ^6And Moses spake unto the children of Israel; and all their princes gave him rods, for each prince one, according to their fathers' houses, even twelve rods: and the rod of Aaron was among their rods. ^7And Moses laid up the rods before Jehovah in the tent of the testimony.

^8And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses went into the tent of the testimony; and, behold, the rod of Aaron for the house of Levi was budded, and put forth buds, and produced blossoms, and bare ripe almonds. ^9And Moses brought out all the rods from before Jehovah unto all the children of Israel: and they looked, and took every man his rod. ^10And Jehovah said unto Moses, Put back the rod of Aaron before the testimony, to be kept for a token against the children of rebellion; that thou mayest make an end of their murmurings against me, that they die not. ^11Thus did Moses: as Jehovah commanded him, so did he.

^12And the children of Israel spake unto Moses, saying, Behold, we perish, we are undone, we are all undone. ^13Every one that cometh near, that cometh near unto the tabernacle of Jehovah, dieth: shall we perish all of us?

Numbers 18

18

^1And Jehovah said unto Aaron, Thou and thy sons and thy fathers' house with thee shall bear the iniquity of the sanctuary; and thou and thy sons with thee shall bear the iniquity of your priesthood. ^2And thy brethren also, the tribe of Levi, the tribe of thy father, bring thou near with thee, that they may be joined unto thee, and minister unto thee: but thou and thy sons with thee shall be before the tent of the testimony. ^3And they shall keep thy charge, and the charge of all the Tent: only they shall not come nigh unto the vessels of the sanctuary and unto the altar, that they die not, neither they, nor ye. ^4And they shall be joined unto thee, and keep the charge of the tent of meeting, for all the service of the Tent: and a stranger shall not come nigh unto you. ^5And ye shall keep the charge of the sanctuary, and the charge of the altar; that there be wrath no more upon the children of Israel. ^6And I, behold, I have taken your brethren the Levites from among the children of Israel: to you they are a gift, given unto Jehovah, to do the service of the tent of meeting. ^7And thou and thy sons with thee shall keep your priesthood for everything of the altar, and for that within the veil; and ye shall serve: I give you the priesthood as a service of gift: and the stranger that cometh nigh shall be put to death.

^8And Jehovah spake unto Aaron, And I, behold, I have given thee the charge of my heave-offerings, even all the hallowed things of the children of Israel; unto thee have I given them by reason of the anointing, and to thy sons, as a portion for ever. ^9This shall be thine of the most holy things, reserved from the fire: every oblation of theirs, even every meal-offering of theirs, and every sin-offering of theirs, and every trespass-offering of theirs, which they shall render unto me, shall be most holy for thee and for thy sons. ^10As the most holy things shalt thou eat thereof; every male shall eat thereof: it shall be holy unto thee. ^11And this is thine: the heave-offering of their gift, even all the wave-offerings of the children of Israel; I have given them unto thee, and to thy sons and to thy daughters with thee, as a portion for ever; every one that is clean in thy house shall eat thereof. ^12All the best of the oil, and all the best of the vintage, and of the grain, the first-fruits of them which they give unto Jehovah, to thee have I given them. ^13The first-ripe fruits of all that is in their land, which they bring unto Jehovah, shall be thine; every one that is clean in thy house shall eat thereof. ^14Everything devoted in Israel shall be thine. ^15Everything that openeth the womb, of all flesh which they offer unto Jehovah, both of man and beast shall be thine: nevertheless the first-born of man shalt thou surely redeem, and the firstling of unclean beasts shalt thou redeem. ^16And those that are to be redeemed of them from a month old shalt thou redeem, according to thine estimation, for the money of five shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary (the same is twenty gerahs). ^17But the firstling of a cow, or the firstling of a sheep, or the firstling of a goat, thou shalt not redeem; they are holy: thou shalt sprinkle their blood upon the altar, and shalt burn their fat for an offering made by fire, for a sweet savor unto Jehovah. ^18And the flesh of them shall be thine, as the wave-breast and as the right thigh, it shall be thine. ^19All the heave-offerings of the holy things, which the children of Israel offer unto Jehovah, have I given thee, and thy sons and thy daughters with thee, as a portion for ever: it is a covenant of salt for ever before Jehovah unto thee and to thy seed with thee. ^20And Jehovah said unto Aaron, Thou shalt have no inheritance in their land, neither shalt thou have any portion among them: I am thy portion and thine inheritance among the children of Israel.

^21And unto the children of Levi, behold, I have given all the tithe in Israel for an inheritance, in return for their service which they serve, even the service of the tent of meeting. ^22And henceforth the children of Israel shall not come nigh the tent of meeting, lest they bear sin, and die. ^23But the Levites shall do the service of the tent of meeting, and they shall bear their iniquity: it shall be a statute for ever throughout your generations; and among the children of Israel they shall have no inheritance. ^24For the tithe of the children of Israel, which they offer as a heave-offering unto Jehovah, I have given to the Levites for an inheritance: therefore I have said unto them, Among the children of Israel they shall have no inheritance.

^25And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^26Moreover thou shalt speak unto the Levites, and say unto them, When ye take of the children of Israel the tithe which I have given you from them for your inheritance, then ye shall offer up a heave-offering of it for Jehovah, a tithe of the tithe. ^27And your heave-offering shall be reckoned unto you, as though it were the grain of the threshing-floor, and as the fulness of the winepress. ^28Thus ye also shall offer a heave-offering unto Jehovah of all your tithes, which ye receive of the children of Israel; and thereof ye shall give Jehovah's heave-offering to Aaron the priest. ^29Out of all your gifts ye shall offer every heave-offering of Jehovah, of all the best thereof, even the hallowed part thereof out of it. ^30Therefore thou shalt say unto them, When ye heave the best thereof from it, then it shall be reckoned unto the Levites as the increase of the threshing-floor, and as the increase of the wine-press. ^31And ye shall eat it in every place, ye and your households: for it is your reward in return for your service in the tent of meeting. ^32And ye shall bear no sin by reason of it, when ye have heaved from it the best thereof: and ye shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, that ye die not.

Numbers 19

19

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^2This is the statute of the law which Jehovah hath commanded, saying, Speak unto the children of Israel, that they bring thee a red heifer without spot, wherein is no blemish, and upon which never came yoke. ^3And ye shall give her unto Eleazar the priest, and he shall bring her forth without the camp, and one shall slay her before his face: ^4and Eleazar the priest shall take of her blood with his finger, and sprinkle her blood toward the front of the tent of meeting seven times. ^5And one shall burn the heifer in his sight; her skin, and her flesh, and her blood, with her dung, shall he burn: ^6and the priest shall take cedar-wood, and hyssop, and scarlet, and cast it into the midst of the burning of the heifer. ^7Then the priest shall wash his clothes, and he shall bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp, and the priest shall be unclean until the even. ^8And he that burneth her shall wash his clothes in water, and bathe his flesh in water, and shall be unclean until the even. ^9And a man that is clean shall gather up the ashes of the heifer, and lay them up without the camp in a clean place; and it shall be kept for the congregation of the children of Israel for a water for impurity: it is a sin-offering. ^10And he that gathereth the ashes of the heifer shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: and it shall be unto the children of Israel, and unto the stranger that sojourneth among them, for a statute for ever.

^11He that toucheth the dead body of any man shall be unclean seven days: ^12the same shall purify himself therewith on the third day, and on the seventh day he shall be clean: but if he purify not himself the third day, then the seventh day he shall not be clean. ^13Whosoever toucheth a dead person, the body of a man that hath died, and purifieth not himself, defileth the tabernacle of Jehovah; and that soul shall be cut off from Israel: because the water for impurity was not sprinkled upon him, he shall be unclean; his uncleanness is yet upon him.

^14This is the law when a man dieth in a tent: every one that cometh into the tent, and every one that is in the tent, shall be unclean seven days. ^15And every open vessel, which hath no covering bound upon it, is unclean. ^16And whosoever in the open field toucheth one that is slain with a sword, or a dead body, or a bone of a man, or a grave, shall be unclean seven days. ^17And for the unclean they shall take of the ashes of the burning of the sin-offering; and running water shall be put thereto in a vessel: ^18and a clean person shall take hyssop, and dip it in the water, and sprinkle it upon the tent, and upon all the vessels, and upon the persons that were there, and upon him that touched the bone, or the slain, or the dead, or the grave: ^19and the clean person shall sprinkle upon the unclean on the third day, and on the seventh day: and on the seventh day he shall purify him; and he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and shall be clean at even.

^20But the man that shall be unclean, and shall not purify himself, that soul shall be cut off from the midst of the assembly, because he hath defiled the sanctuary of Jehovah: the water for impurity hath not been sprinkled upon him; he is unclean. ^21And it shall be a perpetual statute unto them: and he that sprinkleth the water for impurity shall wash his clothes, and he that toucheth the water for impurity shall be unclean until even. ^22And whatsoever the unclean person toucheth shall be unclean; and the soul that toucheth it shall be unclean until even.

Numbers 20

20

^1And the children of Israel, even the whole congregation, came into the wilderness of Zin in the first month: and the people abode in Kadesh; and Miriam died there, and was buried there. ^2And there was no water for the congregation: and they assembled themselves together against Moses and against Aaron. ^3And the people strove with Moses, and spake, saying, Would that we had died when our brethren died before Jehovah! ^4And why have ye brought the assembly of Jehovah into this wilderness, that we should die there, we and our beasts? ^5And wherefore have ye made us to come up out of Egypt, to bring us in unto this evil place? it is no place of seed, or of figs, or of vines, or of pomegranates; neither is there any water to drink. ^6And Moses and Aaron went from the presence of the assembly unto the door of the tent of meeting, and fell upon their faces: and the glory of Jehovah appeared unto them. ^7And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^8Take the rod, and assemble the congregation, thou, and Aaron thy brother, and speak ye unto the rock before their eyes, that it give forth its water; and thou shalt bring forth to them water out of the rock; so thou shalt give the congregation and their cattle drink. ^9And Moses took the rod from before Jehovah, as he commanded him.

^10And Moses and Aaron gathered the assembly together before the rock, and he said unto them, Hear now, ye rebels; shall we bring you forth water out of this rock? ^11And Moses lifted up his hand, and smote the rock with his rod twice: and water came forth abundantly, and the congregation drank, and their cattle. ^12And Jehovah said unto Moses and Aaron, Because ye believed not in me, to sanctify me in the eyes of the children of Israel, therefore ye shall not bring this assembly into the land which I have given them. ^13These are the waters of Meribah; because the children of Israel strove with Jehovah, and he was sanctified in them.

^14And Moses sent messengers from Kadesh unto the king of Edom, Thus saith thy brother Israel, Thou knowest all the travail that hath befallen us: ^15how our fathers went down into Egypt, and we dwelt in Egypt a long time; and the Egyptians dealt ill with us, and our fathers: ^16and when we cried unto Jehovah, he heard our voice, and sent an angel, and brought us forth out of Egypt: and, behold, we are in Kadesh, a city in the uttermost of thy border. ^17Let us pass, I pray thee, through thy land: we will not pass through field or through vineyard, neither will we drink of the water of the wells: we will go along the king's highway; we will not turn aside to the right hand nor to the left, until we have passed thy border. ^18And Edom said unto him, Thou shalt not pass through me, lest I come out with the sword against thee. ^19And the children of Israel said unto him, We will go up by the highway; and if we drink of thy water, I and my cattle, then will I give the price thereof: let me only, without doing anything else, pass through on my feet. ^20And he said, Thou shalt not pass through. And Edom came out against him with much people, and with a strong hand. ^21Thus Edom refused to give Israel passage through his border: wherefore Israel turned away from him.

^22And they journeyed from Kadesh: and the children of Israel, even the whole congregation, came unto mount Hor. ^23And Jehovah spake unto Moses and Aaron in mount Hor, by the border of the land of Edom, saying, ^24Aaron shall be gathered unto his people; for he shall not enter into the land which I have given unto the children of Israel, because ye rebelled against my word at the waters of Meribah. ^25Take Aaron and Eleazar his son, and bring them up unto mount Hor; ^26and strip Aaron of his garments, and put them upon Eleazar his son: and Aaron shall be gathered unto his people, and shall die there. ^27And Moses did as Jehovah commanded: and they went up into mount Hor in the sight of all the congregation. ^28And Moses stripped Aaron of his garments, and put them upon Eleazar his son; and Aaron died there on the top of the mount: and Moses and Eleazar came down from the mount. ^29And when all the congregation saw that Aaron was dead, they wept for Aaron thirty days, even all the house of Israel.

Numbers 21

21

^1And the Canaanite, the king of Arad, who dwelt in the South, heard tell that Israel came by the way of Atharim; and he fought against Israel, and took some of them captive. ^2And Israel vowed a vow unto Jehovah, and said, If thou wilt indeed deliver this people into my hand, then I will utterly destroy their cities. ^3And Jehovah hearkened to the voice of Israel, and delivered up the Canaanites; and they utterly destroyed them and their cities: and the name of the place was called Hormah.

^4And they journeyed from mount Hor by the way to the Red Sea, to compass the land of Edom: and the soul of the people was much discouraged because of the way. ^5And the people spake against God, and against Moses, Wherefore have ye brought us up out of Egypt to die in the wilderness? for there is no bread, and there is no water; and our soul loatheth this light bread. ^6And Jehovah sent fiery serpents among the people, and they bit the people; and much people of Israel died. ^7And the people came to Moses, and said, We have sinned, because we have spoken against Jehovah, and against thee; pray unto Jehovah, that he take away the serpents from us. And Moses prayed for the people. ^8And Jehovah said unto Moses, Make thee a fiery serpent, and set it upon a standard: and it shall come to pass, that every one that is bitten, when he seeth it, shall live. ^9And Moses made a serpent of brass, and set it upon the standard: and it came to pass, that if a serpent had bitten any man, when he looked unto the serpent of brass, he lived.

^10And the children of Israel journeyed, and encamped in Oboth. ^11And they journeyed from Oboth, and encamped at Iyeabarim, in the wilderness which is before Moab, toward the sunrising. ^12From thence they journeyed, and encamped in the valley of Zered. ^13From thence they journeyed, and encamped on the other side of the Arnon, which is in the wilderness, that cometh out of the border of the Amorites: for the Arnon is the border of Moab, between Moab and the Amorites. ^14Wherefore it is said in the book of the Wars of Jehovah,

Vaheb in Suphah,

And the valleys of the Arnon,

^15And the slope of the valleys

That inclineth toward the dwelling of Ar,

And leaneth upon the border of Moab.

^16And from thence they journeyed to Beer: that is the well whereof Jehovah said unto Moses, Gather the people together, and I will give them water.

^17Then sang Israel this song:

Spring up, O well; sing ye unto it:

^18The well, which the princes digged,

Which the nobles of the people delved,

With the sceptre, and with their staves.

And from the wilderness they journeyed to Mattanah; ^19and from Mattanah to Nahaliel; and from Nahaliel to Bamoth; ^20and from Bamoth to the valley that is in the field of Moab, to the top of Pisgah, which looketh down upon the desert.

^21And Israel sent messengers unto Sihon king of the Amorites, saying, ^22Let me pass through thy land: we will not turn aside into field, or into vineyard; we will not drink of the water of the wells: we will go by the king's highway, until we have passed thy border. ^23And Sihon would not suffer Israel to pass through his border: but Sihon gathered all his people together, and went out against Israel into the wilderness, and came to Jahaz; and he fought against Israel. ^24And Israel smote him with the edge of the sword, and possessed his land from the Arnon unto the Jabbok, even unto the children of Ammon; for the border of the children of Ammon was strong. ^25And Israel took all these cities: and Israel dwelt in all the cities of the Amorites, in Heshbon, and in all the towns thereof. ^26For Heshbon was the city of Sihon the king of the Amorites, who had fought against the former king of Moab, and taken all his land out of his hand, even unto the Arnon. ^27Wherefore they that speak in proverbs say,

Come ye to Heshbon;

Let the city of Sihon be built and established:

^28For a fire is gone out of Heshbon,

A flame from the city of Sihon:

It hath devoured Ar of Moab,

The lords of the high places of the Arnon.

^29Woe to thee, Moab!

Thou art undone, O people of Chemosh:

He hath given his sons as fugitives,

And his daughters into captivity,

Unto Sihon king of the Amorites.

^30We have shot at them; Heshbon is perished even unto Dibon,

And we have laid waste even unto Nophah,

Which reacheth unto Medeba.

^31Thus Israel dwelt in the land of the Amorites. ^32And Moses sent to spy out Jazer; and they took the towns thereof, and drove out the Amorites that were there.

^33And they turned and went up by the way of Bashan: and Og the king of Bashan went out against them, he and all his people, to battle at Edrei. ^34And Jehovah said unto Moses, Fear him not: for I have delivered him into thy hand, and all his people, and his land; and thou shalt do to him as thou didst unto Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Heshbon. ^35So they smote him, and his sons and all his people, until there was none left him remaining: and they possessed his land.

Numbers 22

22

^1And the children of Israel journeyed, and encamped in the plains of Moab beyond the Jordan at Jericho.

^2And Balak the son of Zippor saw all that Israel had done to the Amorites. ^3And Moab was sore afraid of the people, because they were many: and Moab was distressed because of the children of Israel. ^4And Moab said unto the elders of Midian, Now will this multitude lick up all that is round about us, as the ox licketh up the grass of the field. And Balak the son of Zippor was king of Moab at that time. ^5And he sent messengers unto Balaam the son of Beor, to Pethor, which is by the River, to the land of the children of his people, to call him, saying, Behold, there is a people come out from Egypt: behold, they cover the face of the earth, and they abide over against me. ^6Come now therefore, I pray thee, curse me this people; for they are too mighty for me: peradventure I shall prevail, that we may smite them, and that I may drive them out of the land; for I know that he whom thou blessest is blessed, and he whom thou cursest is cursed.

^7And the elders of Moab and the elders of Midian departed with the rewards of divination in their hand; and they came unto Balaam, and spake unto him the words of Balak. ^8And he said unto them, Lodge here this night, and I will bring you word again, as Jehovah shall speak unto me: and the princes of Moab abode with Balaam. ^9And God came unto Balaam, and said, What men are these with thee? ^10And Balaam said unto God, Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, hath sent unto me, saying, ^11Behold, the people that is come out of Egypt, it covereth the face of the earth: now, come curse me them; peradventure I shall be able to fight against them, and shall drive them out. ^12And God said unto Balaam, Thou shalt not go with them; thou shalt not curse the people; for they are blessed. ^13And Balaam rose up in the morning, and said unto the princes of Balak, Get you into your land; for Jehovah refuseth to give me leave to go with you. ^14And the princes of Moab rose up, and they went unto Balak, and said, Balaam refuseth to come with us.

^15And Balak sent yet again princes, more, and more honorable than they. ^16And they came to Balaam, and said to him, Thus saith Balak the son of Zippor, Let nothing, I pray thee, hinder thee from coming unto me: ^17for I will promote thee unto very great honor, and whatsoever thou sayest unto me I will do: come therefore, I pray thee, curse me this people. ^18And Balaam answered and said unto the servants of Balak, If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I cannot go beyond the word of Jehovah my God, to do less or more. ^19Now therefore, I pray you, tarry ye also here this night, that I may know what Jehovah will speak unto me more. ^20And God came unto Balaam at night, and said unto him, If the men are come to call thee, rise up, go with them; but only the word which I speak unto thee, that shalt thou do.

^21And Balaam rose up in the morning, and saddled his ass, and went with the princes of Moab. ^22And God's anger was kindled because he went; and the angel of Jehovah placed himself in the way for an adversary against him. Now he was riding upon his ass, and his two servants were with him. ^23And the ass saw the angel of Jehovah standing in the way, with his sword drawn in his hand; and the ass turned aside out of the way, and went into the field: and Balaam smote the ass, to turn her into the way. ^24Then the angel of Jehovah stood in a narrow path between the vineyards, a wall being on this side, and a wall on that side. ^25And the ass saw the angel of Jehovah, and she thrust herself unto the wall, and crushed Balaam's foot against the wall: and he smote her again. ^26And the angel of Jehovah went further, and stood in a narrow place, where was no way to turn either to the right hand or to the left. ^27And the ass saw the angel of Jehovah, and she lay down under Balaam: and Balaam's anger was kindled, and he smote the ass with his staff. ^28And Jehovah opened the mouth of the ass, and she said unto Balaam, What have I done unto thee, that thou hast smitten me these three times? ^29And Balaam said unto the ass, Because thou hast mocked me, I would there were a sword in my hand, for now I had killed thee. ^30And the ass said unto Balaam, Am not I thine ass, upon which thou hast ridden all thy life long unto this day? was I ever wont to do so unto thee? and he said, Nay.

^31Then Jehovah opened the eyes of Balaam, and he saw the angel of Jehovah standing in the way, with his sword drawn in his hand; and he bowed his head, and fell on his face. ^32And the angel of Jehovah said unto him, Wherefore hast thou smitten thine ass these three times? behold, I am come forth for an adversary, because thy way is perverse before me: ^33and the ass saw me, and turned aside before me these three times: unless she had turned aside from me, surely now I had even slain thee, and saved her alive. ^34And Balaam said unto the angel of Jehovah, I have sinned; for I knew not that thou stoodest in the way against me: now therefore, if it displease thee, I will get me back again. ^35And the angel of Jehovah said unto Balaam, Go with the men; but only the word that I shall speak unto thee, that thou shalt speak. So Balaam went with the princes of Balak.

^36And when Balak heard that Balaam was come, he went out to meet him unto the City of Moab, which is on the border of the Arnon, which is in the utmost part of the border. ^37And Balak said unto Balaam, Did I not earnestly send unto thee to call thee? wherefore camest thou not unto me? am I not able indeed to promote thee to honor? ^38And Balaam said unto Balak, Lo, I am come unto thee: have I now any power at all to speak anything? the word that God putteth in my mouth, that shall I speak. ^39And Balaam went with Balak, and they came unto Kiriath-huzoth. ^40And Balak sacrificed oxen and sheep, and sent to Balaam, and to the princes that were with him.

^41And it came to pass in the morning, that Balak took Balaam, and brought him up into the high places of Baal; and he saw from thence the utmost part of the people.

Numbers 23

23

^1And Balaam said unto Balak, Build me here seven altars, and prepare me here seven bullocks and seven rams. ^2And Balak did as Balaam had spoken; and Balak and Balaam offered on every altar a bullock and a ram. ^3And Balaam said unto Balak, Stand by thy burnt-offering, and I will go: peradventure Jehovah will come to meet me; and whatsoever he showeth me I will tell thee. And he went to a bare height. ^4And God met Balaam: and he said unto him, I have prepared the seven altars, and I have offered up a bullock and a ram on every altar. ^5And Jehovah put a word in Balaam's mouth, and said, Return unto Balak, and thus thou shalt speak. ^6And he returned unto him, and, lo, he was standing by his burnt-offering, he, and all the princes of Moab. ^7And he took up his parable, and said, From Aram hath Balak brought me, The king of Moab from the mountains of the East: Come, curse me Jacob, And come, defy Israel. ^8How shall I curse, whom God hath not cursed? And how shall I defy, whom Jehovah hath not defied? ^9For from the top of the rocks I see him, And from the hills I behold him: lo, it is a people that dwelleth alone, And shall not be reckoned among the nations. ^10Who can count the dust of Jacob, Or number the fourth part of Israel? Let me die the death of the righteous, And let my last end be like his! ^11And Balak said unto Balaam, What hast thou done unto me? I took thee to curse mine enemies, and, behold, thou hast blessed them altogether. ^12And he answered and said, Must I not take heed to speak that which Jehovah putteth in my mouth?

^13And Balak said unto him, Come, I pray thee, with me unto another place, from whence thou mayest see them; thou shalt see but the utmost part of them, and shalt not see them all: and curse me them from thence. ^14And he took him into the field of Zophim, to the top of Pisgah, and built seven altars, and offered up a bullock and a ram on every altar. ^15And he said unto Balak, Stand here by thy burnt-offering, while I meet Jehovah yonder. ^16And Jehovah met Balaam, and put a word in his mouth, and said, Return unto Balak, and thus shalt thou speak. ^17And he came to him, and, lo, he was standing by his burnt-offering, and the princes of Moab with him. And Balak said unto him, What hath Jehovah spoken? ^18And he took up his parable, and said,

Rise up, Balak, and hear;

Hearken unto me, thou son of Zippor:

^19God is not a man, that he should lie,

Neither the son of man, that he should repent:

Hath he said, and will he not do it?

Or hath he spoken, and will he not make it good?

^20Behold, I have received commandment to bless:

And he hath blessed, and I cannot reverse it.

^21He hath not beheld iniquity in Jacob;

Neither hath he seen perverseness in Israel:

Jehovah his God is with him,

And the shout of a king is among them.

^22God bringeth them forth out of Egypt;

He hath as it were the strength of the wild-ox.

^23Surely there is no enchantment with Jacob;

Neither is there any divination with Israel:

Now shalt it be said of Jacob and of Israel,

What hath God wrought!

^24Behold, the people riseth up as a lioness,

And as a lion doth he lift himself up:

He shall not lie down until he eat of the prey,

And drink the blood of the slain.

^25And Balak said unto Balaam, Neither curse them at all, nor bless them at all. ^26But Balaam answered and said unto Balak, Told not I thee, saying, All that Jehovah speaketh, that I must do? ^27And Balak said unto Balaam, Come now, I will take thee unto another place; peradventure it will please God that thou mayest curse me them from thence. ^28And Balak took Balaam unto the top of Peor, that looketh down upon the desert. ^29And Balaam said unto Balak, Build me here seven altars, and prepare me here seven bullocks and seven rams. ^30And Balak did as Balaam had said, and offered up a bullock and a ram on every altar.

Numbers 25

25

^1And Israel abode in Shittim; and the people began to play the harlot with the daughters of Moab: ^2for they called the people unto the sacrifices of their gods; and the people did eat, and bowed down to their gods. ^3And Israel joined himself unto Baal-peor: and the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Israel. ^4And Jehovah said unto Moses, Take all the chiefs of the people, and hang them up unto Jehovah before the sun, that the fierce anger of Jehovah may turn away from Israel. ^5And Moses said unto the judges of Israel, Slay ye every one his men that have joined themselves unto Baal-peor.

^6And, behold, one of the children of Israel came and brought unto his brethren a Midianitish woman in the sight of Moses, and in the sight of all the congregation of the children of Israel, while they were weeping at the door of the tent of meeting. ^7And when Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, saw it, he rose up from the midst of the congregation, and took a spear in his hand; ^8and he went after the man of Israel into the pavilion, and thrust both of them through, the man of Israel, and the woman through her body. So the plague was stayed from the children of Israel. ^9And those that died by the plague were twenty and four thousand.

^10And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^11Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, hath turned my wrath away from the children of Israel, in that he was jealous with my jealousy among them, so that I consumed not the children of Israel in my jealousy. ^12Wherefore say, Behold, I give unto him my covenant of peace: ^13and it shall be unto him, and to his seed after him, the covenant of an everlasting priesthood; because he was jealous for his God, and made atonement for the children of Israel.

^14Now the name of the man of Israel that was slain, who was slain with the Midianitish woman, was Zimri, the son of Salu, a prince of a fathers' house among the Simeonites. ^15And the name of the Midianitish woman that was slain was Cozbi, the daughter of Zur; he was head of the people of a fathers' house in Midian.

^16And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^17Vex the Midianites, and smite them; ^18for they vex you with their wiles, wherewith they have beguiled you in the matter of Peor, and in the matter of Cozbi, the daughter of the prince of Midian, their sister, who was slain on the day of the plague in the matter of Peor.

Numbers 26

26

^1And it came to pass after the plague, that Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, saying, ^2Take the sum of all the congregation of the children of Israel, from twenty years old and upward, by their fathers' houses, all that are able to go forth to war in Israel. ^3And Moses and Eleazar the priest spake with them in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho, saying, ^4Take the sum of the people, from twenty years old and upward; as Jehovah commanded Moses and the children of Israel, that came forth out of the land of Egypt.

^5Reuben, the first-born of Israel; the sons of Reuben: of Hanoch, the family of the Hanochites; of Pallu, the family of the Palluites; ^6of Hezron, the family of the Hezronites; of Carmi, the family of the Carmites. ^7These are the families of the Reubenites; and they that were numbered of them were forty and three thousand and seven hundred and thirty. ^8And the sons of Pallu: Eliab. ^9And the sons of Eliab: Nemuel, and Dathan, and Abiram. These are that Dathan and Abiram, who were called of the congregation, who strove against Moses and against Aaron in the company of Korah, when they strove against Jehovah, ^10and the earth opened its mouth, and swallowed them up together with Korah, when that company died; what time the fire devoured two hundred and fifty men, and they became a sign. ^11Notwithstanding, the sons of Korah died not.

^12The sons of Simeon after their families: of Nemuel, the family of the Nemuelites; of Jamin, the family of the Jaminites; of Jachin, the family of the Jachinites; ^13of Zerah, the family of the Zerahites; of Shaul, the family of the Shaulites. ^14These are the families of the Simeonites, twenty and two thousand and two hundred.

^15The sons of Gad after their families: of Zephon, the family of the Zephonites; of Haggi, the family of the Haggites; of Shuni, the family of the Shunites; ^16of Ozni, the family of the Oznites; of Eri, the family of the Erites; ^17of Arod, the family of the Arodites; of Areli, the family of the Arelites. ^18These are the families of the sons of Gad according to those that were numbered of them, forty thousand and five hundred.

^19The sons of Judah: Er and Onan; and Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. ^20And the sons of Judah after their families were: of Shelah, the family of the Shelanites; of Perez, the family of the Perezites; of Zerah, the family of the Zerahites. ^21And the sons of Perez were: of Hezron, the family of the Hezronites; of Hamul, the family of the Hamulites. ^22These are the families of Judah according to those that were numbered of them, threescore and sixteen thousand and five hundred.

^23The sons of Issachar after their families: of Tola, the family of the Tolaites; of Puvah, the family of the Punites; ^24of Jashub, the family of the Jashubites; of Shimron, the family of the Shimronites. ^25These are the families of Issachar according to those that were numbered of them, threescore and four thousand and three hundred.

^26The sons of Zebulun after their families: of Sered, the family of the Seredites; of Elon, the family of the Elonites; of Jahleel, the family of the Jahleelites. ^27These are the families of the Zebulunites according to those that were numbered of them, threescore thousand and five hundred.

^28The sons of Joseph after their families: Manasseh and Ephraim. ^29The sons of Manasseh: of Machir, the family of the Machirites; and Machir begat Gilead; of Gilead, the family of the Gileadites. ^30These are the sons of Gilead: of Iezer, the family of the Iezerites; of Helek, the family of the Helekites; ^31and of Asriel, the family of the Asrielites; and of Shechem, the family of the Shechemites; ^32and of Shemida, the family of the Shemidaites; and of Hepher, the family of the Hepherites. ^33And Zelophehad the son of Hepher had no sons, but daughters: and the names of the daughters of Zelophehad were Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. ^34These are the families of Manasseh; and they that were numbered of them were fifty and two thousand and seven hundred.

^35These are the sons of Ephraim after their families: of Shuthelah, the family of the Shuthelahites; of Becher, the family of the Becherites; of Tahan, the family of the Tahanites. ^36And these are the sons of Shuthelah: of Eran, the family of the Eranites. ^37These are the families of the sons of Ephraim according to those that were numbered of them, thirty and two thousand and five hundred. These are the sons of Joseph after their families.

^38The sons of Benjamin after their families: of Bela, the family of the Belaites; of Ashbel, the family of the Ashbelites; of Ahiram, the family of the Ahiramites; ^39of Shephupham, the family of the Shuphamites; of Hupham, the family of the Huphamites. ^40And the sons of Bela were Ard and Naaman: of Ard, the family of the Ardites; of Naaman, the family of the Naamites. ^41These are the sons of Benjamin after their families; and they that were numbered of them were forty and five thousand and six hundred.

^42These are the sons of Dan after their families: of Shuham, the family of the Shuhamites. These are the families of Dan after their families. ^43All the families of the Shuhamites, according to those that were numbered of them, were threescore and four thousand and four hundred.

^44The sons of Asher after their families: of Imnah, the family of the Imnites; of Ishvi, the family of the Ishvites; of Beriah, the family of the Berites. ^45Of the sons of Beriah: of Heber, the family of the Heberites; of Malchiel, the family of the Malchielites. ^46And the name of the daughter of Asher was Serah. ^47These are the families of the sons of Asher according to those that were numbered of them, fifty and three thousand and four hundred.

^48The sons of Naphtali after their families: of Jahzeel, the family of the Jahzeelites; of Guni, the family of the Gunites; ^49of Jezer, the family of the Jezerites; of Shillem, the family of the Shillemites. ^50These are the families of Naphtali according to their families; and they that were numbered of them were forty and five thousand and four hundred.

^51These are they that were numbered of the children of Israel, six hundred thousand and a thousand seven hundred and thirty.

^52And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^53Unto these the land shall be divided for an inheritance according to the number of names. ^54To the more thou shalt give the more inheritance, and to the fewer thou shalt give the less inheritance: to every one according to those that were numbered of him shall his inheritance be given. ^55Notwithstanding, the land shall be divided by lot: according to the names of the tribes of their fathers they shall inherit. ^56According to the lot shall their inheritance be divided between the more and the fewer.

^57And these are they that were numbered of the Levites after their families: of Gershon, the family of the Gershonites; of Kohath, the family of the Kohathites; of Merari, the family of the Merarites. ^58These are the families of Levi: the family of the Libnites, the family of the Hebronites, the family of the Mahlites, the family of the Mushites, the family of the Korahites. And Kohath begat Amram. ^59And the name of Amram's wife was Jochebed, the daughter of Levi, who was born to Levi in Egypt: and she bare unto Amram Aaron and Moses, and Miriam their sister. ^60And unto Aaron were born Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. ^61And Nadab and Abihu died, when they offered strange fire before Jehovah. ^62And they that were numbered of them were twenty and three thousand, every male from a month old and upward: for they were not numbered among the children of Israel, because there was no inheritance given them among the children of Israel.

^63These are they that were numbered by Moses and Eleazar the priest, who numbered the children of Israel in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho. ^64But among these there was not a man of them that were numbered by Moses and Aaron the priest, who numbered the children of Israel in the wilderness of Sinai. ^65For Jehovah had said of them, They shall surely die in the wilderness. And there was not left a man of them, save Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun.

Numbers 27

27

^1Then drew near the daughters of Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, of the families of Manasseh the son of Joseph; and these are the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Tirzah. ^2And they stood before Moses, and before Eleazar the priest, and before the princes and all the congregation, at the door of the tent of meeting, saying, ^3Our father died in the wilderness, and he was not among the company of them that gathered themselves together against Jehovah in the company of Korah: but he died in his own sin; and he had no sons. ^4Why should the name of our father be taken away from among his family, because he had no son? Give unto us a possession among the brethren of our father. ^5And Moses brought their cause before Jehovah.

^6And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^7The daughters of Zelophehad speak right: thou shalt surely give them a possession of an inheritance among their father's brethren; and thou shalt cause the inheritance of their father to pass unto them. ^8And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a man die, and have no son, then ye shall cause his inheritance to pass unto his daughter. ^9And if he have no daughter, then ye shall give his inheritance unto his brethren. ^10And if he have no brethren, then ye shall give his inheritance unto his father's brethren. ^11And if his father have no brethren, then ye shall give his inheritance unto his kinsman that is next to him of his family, and he shall possess it: and it shall be unto the children of Israel a statute and ordinance, as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^12And Jehovah said unto Moses, Get thee up into this mountain of Abarim, and behold the land which I have given unto the children of Israel. ^13And when thou hast seen it, thou also shalt be gathered unto thy people, as Aaron thy brother was gathered; ^14because ye rebelled against my word in the wilderness of Zin, in the strife of the congregation, to sanctify me at the waters before their eyes. (These are the waters of Meribah of Kadesh in the wilderness of Zin.) ^15And Moses spake unto Jehovah, saying, ^16Let Jehovah, the God of the spirits of all flesh, appoint a man over the congregation, ^17who may go out before them, and who may come in before them, and who may lead them out, and who may bring them in; that the congregation of Jehovah be not as sheep which have no shepherd. ^18And Jehovah said unto Moses, Take thee Joshua the son of Nun, a man in whom is the Spirit, and lay thy hand upon him; ^19and set him before Eleazar the priest, and before all the congregation; and give him a charge in their sight. ^20And thou shalt put of thine honor upon him, that all the congregation of the children of Israel may obey. ^21And he shall stand before Eleazar the priest, who shall inquire for him by the judgment of the Urim before Jehovah: at his word shall they go out, and at his word they shall come in, both he, and all the children of Israel with him, even all the congregation. ^22And Moses did as Jehovah commanded him; and he took Joshua, and set him before Eleazar the priest, and before all the congregation: ^23and he laid his hands upon him, and gave him a charge, as Jehovah spake by Moses.

Numbers 28

28

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Command the children of Israel, and say unto them, My oblation, my food for my offerings made by fire, of a sweet savor unto me, shall ye observe to offer unto me in their due season. ^3And thou shalt say unto them, This is the offering made by fire which ye shall offer unto Jehovah: he-lambs a year old without blemish, two day by day, for a continual burnt-offering. ^4The one lamb shalt thou offer in the morning, and the other lamb shalt thou offer at even; ^5and the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a meal-offering, mingled with the fourth part of a hin of beaten oil. ^6It is a continual burnt-offering, which was ordained in mount Sinai for a sweet savor, an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^7And the drink-offering thereof shall be the fourth part of a hin for the one lamb: in the holy place shalt thou pour out a drink-offering of strong drink unto Jehovah. ^8And the other lamb shalt thou offer at even: as the meal-offering of the morning, and as the drink-offering thereof, thou shalt offer it, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah.

^9And on the sabbath day two he-lambs a year old without blemish, and two tenth parts of an ephah of fine flour for a meal-offering, mingled with oil, and the drink-offering thereof: ^10this is the burnt-offering of every sabbath, besides the continual burnt-offering, and the drink-offering thereof.

^11And in the beginnings of your months ye shall offer a burnt-offering unto Jehovah: two young bullocks, and one ram, seven he-lambs a year old without blemish; ^12and three tenth parts of an ephah of fine flour for a meal-offering, mingled with oil, for each bullock; and two tenth parts of fine flour for a meal-offering, mingled with oil, for the one ram; ^13and a tenth part of fine flour mingled with oil for a meal-offering unto every lamb; for a burnt-offering of a sweet savor, an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^14And their drink-offerings shall be half a hin of wine for a bullock, and the third part of a hin for the ram, and the fourth part of a hin for a lamb: this is the burnt-offering of every month throughout the months of the year. ^15And one he-goat for a sin-offering unto Jehovah; it shall be offered besides the continual burnt-offering, and the drink-offering thereof.

^16And in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, is Jehovah's passover. ^17And on the fifteenth day of this month shall be a feast: seven days shall unleavened bread be eaten. ^18In the first day shall be a holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work; ^19but ye shall offer an offering made by fire, a burnt-offering unto Jehovah: two young bullocks, and one ram, and seven he-lambs a year old; they shall be unto you without blemish; ^20and their meal-offering, fine flour mingled with oil: three tenth parts shall ye offer for a bullock, and two tenth parts for the ram; ^21a tenth part shalt thou offer for every lamb of the seven lambs; ^22and one he-goat for a sin-offering, to make atonement for you. ^23Ye shall offer these besides the burnt-offering of the morning, which is for a continual burnt-offering. ^24After this manner ye shall offer daily, for seven days, the food of the offering made by fire, of a sweet savor unto Jehovah: it shall be offered besides the continual burnt-offering, and the drink-offering thereof. ^25And on the seventh day ye shall have a holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work.

^26Also in the day of the first-fruits, when ye offer a new meal-offering unto Jehovah in your feast of weeks, ye shall have a holy convocation; ye shall do no servile work; ^27but ye shall offer a burnt-offering for a sweet savor unto Jehovah: two young bullocks, one ram, seven he-lambs a year old; ^28and their meal-offering, fine flour mingled with oil, three tenth parts for each bullock, two tenth parts for the one ram, ^29a tenth part for every lamb of the seven lambs; ^30one he-goat, to make atonement for you. ^31Besides the continual burnt-offering, and the meal-offering thereof, ye shall offer them (they shall be unto you without blemish), and their drink-offerings.

Numbers 30

30

^1And Moses spake unto the heads of the tribes of the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which Jehovah hath commanded. ^2When a man voweth a vow unto Jehovah, or sweareth an oath to bind his soul with a bond, he shall not break his word; he shall do according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth. ^3Also when a woman voweth a vow unto Jehovah, and bindeth herself by a bond, being in her father's house, in her youth, ^4and her father heareth her vow, and her bond wherewith she hath bound her soul, and her father holdeth his peace at her; then all her vows shall stand, and every bond wherewith she hath bound her soul shall stand. ^5But if her father disallow her in the day that he heareth, none of her vows, or of her bonds wherewith she hath bound her soul, shall stand: and Jehovah will forgive her, because her father disallowed her.

^6And if she be married to a husband, while her vows are upon her, or the rash utterance of her lips, wherewith she hath bound her soul, ^7and her husband hear it, and hold his peace at her in the day that he heareth it; then her vows shall stand, and her bonds wherewith she hath bound her soul shall stand. ^8But if her husband disallow her in the day that he heareth it, then he shall make void her vow which is upon her, and the rash utterance of her lips, wherewith she hath bound her soul: and Jehovah will forgive her. ^9But the vow of a widow, or of her that is divorced, even everything wherewith she hath bound her soul, shall stand against her. ^10And if she vowed in her husband's house, or bound her soul by a bond with an oath, ^11and her husband heard it, and held his peace at her, and disallowed her not; then all her vows shall stand, and every bond wherewith she bound her soul shall stand. ^12But if her husband made them null and void in the day that he heard them, then whatsoever proceeded out of her lips concerning her vows, or concerning the bond of her soul, shall not stand: her husband hath made them void; and Jehovah will forgive her.

^13Every vow, and every binding oath to afflict the soul, her husband may establish it, or her husband may make it void. ^14But if her husband altogether hold his peace at her from day to day, then he establisheth all her vows, or all her bonds, which are upon her: he hath established them, because he held his peace at her in the day that he heard them. ^15But if he shall make them null and void after that he hath heard them, then he shall bear her iniquity. ^16These are the statutes, which Jehovah commanded Moses, between a man and his wife, between a father and his daughter, being in her youth, in her father's house.

Numbers 31

31

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Avenge the children of Israel of the Midianites: afterward shalt thou be gathered unto thy people. ^3And Moses spake unto the people, saying, Arm ye men from among you for the war, that they may go against Midian, to execute Jehovah's vengeance on Midian. ^4Of every tribe a thousand, throughout all the tribes of Israel, shall ye send to the war. ^5So there were delivered, out of the thousands of Israel, a thousand of every tribe, twelve thousand armed for war. ^6And Moses sent them, a thousand of every tribe, to the war, them and Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, to the war, with the vessels of the sanctuary and the trumpets for the alarm in his hand. ^7And they warred against Midian, as Jehovah commanded Moses; and they slew every male. ^8And they slew the kings of Midian with the rest of their slain: Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, the five kings of Midian: Balaam also the son of Beor they slew with the sword. ^9And the children of Israel took captive the women of Midian and their little ones; and all their cattle, and all their flocks, and all their goods, they took for a prey. ^10And all their cities in the places wherein they dwelt, and all their encampments, they burnt with fire. ^11And they took all the spoil, and all the prey, both of man and of beast. ^12And they brought the captives, and the prey, and the spoil, unto Moses, and unto Eleazar the priest, and unto the congregation of the children of Israel, unto the camp at the plains of Moab, which are by the Jordan at Jericho.

^13And Moses, and Eleazar the priest, and all the princes of the congregation, went forth to meet them without the camp. ^14And Moses was wroth with the officers of the host, the captains of thousands and the captains of hundreds, who came from the service of the war. ^15And Moses said unto them, Have ye saved all the women alive? ^16Behold, these caused the children of Israel, through the counsel of Balaam, to commit trespass against Jehovah in the matter of Peor, and so the plague was among the congregation of Jehovah. ^17Now therefore kill every male among the little ones, and kill every woman that hath known man by lying with him. ^18But all the women-children, that have not known man by lying with him, keep alive for yourselves. ^19And encamp ye without the camp seven days: whosoever hath killed any person, and whosoever hath touched any slain, purify yourselves on the third day and on the seventh day, ye and your captives. ^20And as to every garment, and all that is made of skin, and all work of goats' hair, and all things made of wood, ye shall purify yourselves.

^21And Eleazar the priest said unto the men of war that went to the battle, This is the statute of the law which Jehovah hath commanded Moses: ^22howbeit the gold, and the silver, the brass, the iron, the tin, and the lead, ^23everything that may abide the fire, ye shall make to go through the fire, and it shall be clean; nevertheless it shall be purified with the water for impurity: and all that abideth not the fire ye shall make to go through the water. ^24And ye shall wash your clothes on the seventh day, and ye shall be clean; and afterward ye shall come into the camp.

^25And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^26Take the sum of the prey that was taken, both of man and of beast, thou, and Eleazar the priest, and the heads of the fathers' houses of the congregation; ^27and divide the prey into two parts: between the men skilled in war, that went out to battle, and all the congregation. ^28And levy a tribute unto Jehovah of the men of war that went out to battle: one soul of five hundred, both of the persons, and of the oxen, and of the asses, and of the flocks: ^29take it of their half, and give it unto Eleazar the priest, for Jehovah's heave-offering. ^30And of the children of Israel's half, thou shalt take one drawn out of every fifty, of the persons, of the oxen, of the asses, and of the flocks, even of all the cattle, and give them unto the Levites, that keep the charge of the tabernacle of Jehovah. ^31And Moses and Eleazar the priest did as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^32Now the prey, over and above the booty which the men of war took, was six hundred thousand and seventy thousand and five thousand sheep, ^33and threescore and twelve thousand oxen, ^34and threescore and one thousand asses, ^35and thirty and two thousand persons in all, of the women that had not known man by lying with him. ^36And the half, which was the portion of them that went out to war, was in number three hundred thousand and thirty thousand and seven thousand and five hundred sheep: ^37and Jehovah's tribute of the sheep was six hundred and threescore and fifteen. ^38And the oxen were thirty and six thousand; of which Jehovah's tribute was threescore and twelve. ^39And the asses were thirty thousand and five hundred; of which Jehovah's tribute was threescore and one. ^40And the persons were sixteen thousand; of whom Jehovah's tribute was thirty and two persons. ^41And Moses gave the tribute, which was Jehovah's heave-offering, unto Eleazar the priest, as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^42And of the children of Israel's half, which Moses divided off from the men that warred ^43(now the congregation's half was three hundred thousand and thirty thousand, seven thousand and five hundred sheep, ^44and thirty and six thousand oxen, ^45and thirty thousand and five hundred asses, ^46and sixteen thousand persons), ^47even of the children of Israel's half, Moses took one drawn out of every fifty, both of man and of beast, and gave them unto the Levites, that kept the charge of the tabernacle of Jehovah; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^48And the officers that were over the thousands of the host, the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, came near unto Moses; ^49and they said unto Moses, Thy servants have taken the sum of the men of war that are under our charge, and there lacketh not one man of us. ^50And we have brought Jehovah's oblation, what every man hath gotten, of jewels of gold, ankle-chains, and bracelets, signet-rings, ear-rings, and armlets, to make atonement for our souls before Jehovah. ^51And Moses and Eleazar the priest took the gold of them, even all wrought jewels. ^52And all the gold of the heave-offering that they offered up to Jehovah, of the captains of thousands, and of the captains of hundreds, was sixteen thousand seven hundred and fifty shekels. ^53(For the men of war had taken booty, every man for himself.) ^54And Moses and Eleazar the priest took the gold of the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and brought it into the tent of meeting, for a memorial for the children of Israel before Jehovah.

Numbers 32

32

^1Now the children of Reuben and the children of Gad had a very great multitude of cattle: and when they saw the land of Jazer, and the land of Gilead, that, behold, the place was a place for cattle; ^2the children of Gad and the children of Reuben came and spake unto Moses, and to Eleazar the priest, and unto the princes of the congregation, saying, ^3Ataroth, and Dibon, and Jazer, and Nimrah, and Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Sebam, and Nebo, and Beon, ^4the land which Jehovah smote before the congregation of Israel, is a land for cattle; and thy servants have cattle. ^5And they said, If we have found favor in thy sight, let this land be given unto thy servants for a possession; bring us not over the Jordan.

^6And Moses said unto the children of Gad, and to the children of Reuben, Shall your brethren go to the war, and shall ye sit here? ^7And wherefore discourage ye the heart of the children of Israel from going over into the land which Jehovah hath given them? ^8Thus did your fathers, when I sent them from Kadesh-barnea to see the land. ^9For when they went up unto the valley of Eshcol, and saw the land, they discouraged the heart of the children of Israel, that they should not go into the land which Jehovah had given them. ^10And Jehovah's anger was kindled in that day, and he sware, saying, ^11Surely none of the men that came up out of Egypt, from twenty years old and upward, shall see the land which I sware unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob; because they have not wholly followed me: ^12save Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite, and Joshua the son of Nun; because they have wholly followed Jehovah. ^13And Jehovah's anger was kindled against Israel, and he made them wander to and fro in the wilderness forty years, until all the generation, that had done evil in the sight of Jehovah, was consumed. ^14And, behold, ye are risen up in your fathers' stead, an increase of sinful men, to augment yet the fierce anger of Jehovah toward Israel. ^15For if ye turn away from after him, he will yet again leave them in the wilderness; and ye will destroy all this people.

^16And they came near unto him, and said, We will build sheepfolds here for our cattle, and cities for our little ones: ^17but we ourselves will be ready armed to go before the children of Israel, until we have brought them unto their place: and our little ones shall dwell in the fortified cities because of the inhabitants of the land. ^18We will not return unto our houses, until the children of Israel have inherited every man his inheritance. ^19For we will not inherit with them on the other side of the Jordan, and forward; because our inheritance is fallen to us on this side of the Jordan eastward.

^20And Moses said unto them, If ye will do this thing, if ye will arm yourselves to go before Jehovah to the war, ^21and every armed man of you will pass over the Jordan before Jehovah, until he hath driven out his enemies from before him, ^22and the land is subdued before Jehovah; then afterward ye shall return, and be guiltless towards Jehovah, and towards Israel; and this land shall be unto you for a possession before Jehovah. ^23But if ye will not do so, behold, ye have sinned against Jehovah; and be sure your sin will find you out. ^24Build you cities for your little ones, and folds for your sheep; and do that which hath proceeded out of your mouth. ^25And the children of Gad and the children of Reuben spake unto Moses, saying, Thy servants will do as my lord commandeth. ^26Our little ones, our wives, our flocks, and all our cattle, shall be there in the cities of Gilead; ^27but thy servants will pass over, every man that is armed for war, before Jehovah to battle, as my lord saith.

^28So Moses gave charge concerning them to Eleazar the priest, and to Joshua the son of Nun, and to the heads of the fathers' houses of the tribes of the children of Israel. ^29And Moses said unto them, If the children of Gad and the children of Reuben will pass with you over the Jordan, every man that is armed to battle, before Jehovah, and the land shall be subdued before you; then ye shall give them the land of Gilead for a possession: ^30but if they will not pass over with you armed, they shall have possessions among you in the land of Canaan. ^31And the children of Gad and the children of Reuben answered, saying, As Jehovah hath said unto thy servants, so will we do. ^32We will pass over armed before Jehovah into the land of Canaan, and the possession of our inheritance shall remain with us beyond the Jordan.

^33And Moses gave unto them, even to the children of Gad, and to the children of Reuben, and unto the half-tribe of Manasseh the son of Joseph, the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, and the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, the land, according to the cities thereof with their borders, even the cities of the land round about. ^34And the children of Gad built Dibon, and Ataroth, and Aroer, ^35and Atrothshophan, and Jazer, and Jogbehah, ^36and Beth-nimrah, and Beth-haran: fortified cities, and folds for sheep. ^37And the children of Reuben built Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Kiriathaim, ^38and Nebo, and Baal-meon, (their names being changed,) and Sibmah: and they gave other names unto the cities which they builded. ^39And the children of Machir the son of Manasseh went to Gilead, and took it, and dispossessed the Amorites that were therein. ^40And Moses gave Gilead unto Machir the son of Manasseh; and he dwelt therein. ^41And Jair the son of Manasseh went and took the towns thereof, and called them Havvoth-jair. ^42And Nobah went and took Kenath, and the villages thereof, and called it Nobah, after his own name.

Numbers 33

33

^1These are the journeys of the children of Israel, when they went forth out of the land of Egypt by their hosts under the hand of Moses and Aaron. ^2And Moses wrote their goings out according to their journeys by the commandment of Jehovah: and these are their journeys according to their goings out. ^3And they journeyed from Rameses in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month; on the morrow after the passover the children of Israel went out with a high hand in the sight of all the Egyptians, ^4while the Egyptians were burying all their first-born, whom Jehovah had smitten among them: upon their gods also Jehovah executed judgments.

^5And the children of Israel journeyed from Rameses, and encamped in Succoth. ^6And they journeyed from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, which is in the edge of the wilderness. ^7And they journeyed from Etham, and turned back unto Pihahiroth, which is before Baal-zephon: and they encamped before Migdol. ^8And they journeyed from before Hahiroth, and passed through the midst of the sea into the wilderness: and they went three days' journey in the wilderness of Etham, and encamped in Marah. ^9And they journeyed from Marah, and came unto Elim: and in Elim were twelve springs of water, and threescore and ten palm-trees; and they encamped there. ^10And they journeyed from Elim, and encamped by the Red Sea. ^11And they journeyed from the Red Sea, and encamped in the wilderness of Sin. ^12And they journeyed from the wilderness of Sin, and encamped in Dophkah. ^13And they journeyed from Dophkah, and encamped in Alush. ^14And they journeyed from Alush, and encamped in Rephidim, where was no water for the people to drink. ^15And they journeyed from Rephidim, and encamped in the wilderness of Sinai. ^16And they journeyed from the wilderness of Sinai, and encamped in Kibroth-hattaavah. ^17And they journeyed from Kibroth-hattaavah, and encamped in Hazeroth. ^18And they journeyed from Hazeroth, and encamped in Rithmah. ^19And they journeyed from Rithmah, and encamped in Rimmon-perez. ^20And they journeyed from Rimmon-perez, and encamped in Libnah. ^21And they journeyed from Libnah, and encamped in Rissah. ^22And they journeyed from Rissah, and encamped in Kehelathah. ^23And they journeyed from Kehelathah, and encamped in mount Shepher. ^24And they journeyed from mount Shepher, and encamped in Haradah. ^25And they journeyed from Haradah, and encamped in Makheloth. ^26And they journeyed from Makheloth, and encamped in Tahath. ^27And they journeyed from Tahath, and encamped in Terah. ^28And they journeyed from Terah, and encamped in Mithkah. ^29And they journeyed from Mithkah, and encamped in Hashmonah. ^30And they journeyed from Hashmonah, and encamped in Moseroth. ^31And they journeyed from Moseroth, and encamped in Bene-jaakan. ^32And they journeyed from Bene-jaakan, and encamped in Hor-haggidgad. ^33And they journeyed from Hor-haggidgad, and encamped in Jotbathah. ^34And they journeyed from Jotbathah, and encamped in Abronah. ^35And they journeyed from Abronah, and encamped in Ezion-geber. ^36And they journeyed from Ezion-geber, and encamped in the wilderness of Zin (the same is Kadesh). ^37And they journeyed from Kadesh, and encamped in mount Hor, in the edge of the land of Edom.

^38And Aaron the priest went up into mount Hor at the commandment of Jehovah, and died there, in the fortieth year after the children of Israel were come out of the land of Egypt, in the fifth month, on the first day of the month. ^39And Aaron was a hundred and twenty and three years old when he died in mount Hor.

^40And the Canaanite, the king of Arad, who dwelt in the South in the land of Canaan, heard of the coming of the children of Israel.

^41And they journeyed from mount Hor, and encamped in Zalmonah. ^42And they journeyed from Zalmonah, and encamped in Punon. ^43And they journeyed from Punon, and encamped in Oboth. ^44And they journeyed from Oboth, and encamped in Iye-abarim, in the border of Moab. ^45And they journeyed from Iyim, and encamped in Dibon-gad. ^46And they journeyed from Dibon-gad, and encamped in Almon-diblathaim. ^47And they journeyed from Almon-diblathaim, and encamped in the mountains of Abarim, before Nebo. ^48And they journeyed from the mountains of Abarim, and encamped in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho. ^49And they encamped by the Jordan, from Beth-jeshimoth even unto Abel-shittim in the plains of Moab.

^50And Jehovah spake unto Moses in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho, saying, ^51Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye pass over the Jordan into the land of Canaan, ^52then ye shall drive out all the inhabitants of the land from before you, and destroy all their figured stones, and destroy all their molten images, and demolish all their high places: ^53and ye shall take possession of the land, and dwell therein; for unto you have I given the land to possess it. ^54And ye shall inherit the land by lot according to your families; to the more ye shall give the more inheritance, and to the fewer thou shalt give the less inheritance: wheresoever the lot falleth to any man, that shall be his; according to the tribes of your fathers shall ye inherit. ^55But if ye will not drive out the inhabitants of the land from before you, then shall those that ye let remain of them be as pricks in your eyes, and as thorns in your sides, and they shall vex you in the land wherein ye dwell. ^56And it shall come to pass, that, as I thought to do unto them, so will I do unto you.

Numbers 34

34

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Command the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land of Canaan (this is the land that shall fall unto you for an inheritance, even the land of Canaan according to the borders thereof), ^3then your south quarter shall be from the wilderness of Zin along by the side of Edom, and your south border shall be from the end of the Salt Sea eastward; ^4and your border shall turn about southward of the ascent of Akrabbim, and pass along to Zin; and the goings out thereof shall be southward of Kadesh-barnea; and it shall go forth to Hazar-addar, and pass along to Azmon; ^5and the border shall turn about from Azmon unto the brook of Egypt, and the goings out thereof shall be at the sea.

^6And for the western border, ye shall have the great sea and the border thereof: this shall be your west border.

^7And this shall be your north border: from the great sea ye shall mark out for you mount Hor; ^8from mount Hor ye shall mark out unto the entrance of Hamath; and the goings out of the border shall be at Zedad; ^9and the border shall go forth to Ziphron, and the goings out thereof shall be at Hazar-enan: this shall be your north border.

^10And ye shall mark out your east border from Hazar-enan to Shepham; ^11and the border shall go down from Shepham to Riblah, on the east side of Ain; and the border shall go down, and shall reach unto the side of the sea of Chinnereth eastward; ^12and the border shall go down to the Jordan, and the goings out thereof shall be at the Salt Sea. This shall be your land according to the borders thereof round about.

^13And Moses commanded the children of Israel, saying, This is the land which ye shall inherit by lot, which Jehovah hath commanded to give unto the nine tribes, and to the half-tribe; ^14for the tribe of the children of Reuben according to their fathers' houses, and the tribe of the children of Gad according to their fathers' houses, have received, and the half-tribe of Manasseh have received, their inheritance: ^15the two tribes and the half-tribe have received their inheritance beyond the Jordan at Jericho eastward, toward the sunrising.

^16And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^17These are the names of the men that shall divide the land unto you for inheritance: Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun. ^18And ye shall take one prince of every tribe, to divide the land for inheritance. ^19And these are the names of the men: Of the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh. ^20And of the tribe of the children of Simeon, Shemuel the son of Ammihud. ^21Of the tribe of Benjamin, Elidad the son of Chislon. ^22And of the tribe of the children of Dan a prince, Bukki the son of Jogli. ^23Of the children of Joseph: of the tribe of the children of Manasseh a prince, Hanniel the son of Ephod. ^24And of the tribe of the children of Ephraim a prince, Kemuel the son of Shiphtan. ^25And of the tribe of the children of Zebulun a prince, Elizaphan the son of Parnach. ^26And of the tribe of the children of Issachar a prince, Paltiel the son of Azzan. ^27And of the tribe of the children of Asher a prince, Ahihud the son of Shelomi. ^28And of the tribe of the children of Naphtali a prince, Pedahel the son of Ammihud. ^29These are they whom Jehovah commanded to divide the inheritance unto the children of Israel in the land of Canaan.

Numbers 35

35

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho, saying, ^2Command the children of Israel, that they give unto the Levites of the inheritance of their possession cities to dwell in; and suburbs for the cities round about them shall ye give unto the Levites. ^3And the cities shall they have to dwell in; and their suburbs shall be for their cattle, and for their substance, and for all their beasts. ^4And the suburbs of the cities, which ye shall give unto the Levites, shall be from the wall of the city and outward a thousand cubits round about. ^5And ye shall measure without the city for the east side two thousand cubits, and for the south side two thousand cubits, and for the west side two thousand cubits, and for the north side two thousand cubits, the city being in the midst. This shall be to them the suburbs of the cities. ^6And the cities which ye shall give unto the Levites, they shall be the six cities of refuge, which ye shall give for the manslayer to flee unto: and besides them ye shall give forty and two cities. ^7All the cities which ye shall give to the Levites shall be forty and eight cities; them shall ye give with their suburbs. ^8And concerning the cities which ye shall give of the possession of the children of Israel, from the many ye shall take many; and from the few ye shall take few: every one according to his inheritance which he inheriteth shall give of his cities unto the Levites. ^9And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^10Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye pass over the Jordan into the land of Canaan, ^11then ye shall appoint you cities to be cities of refuge for you, that the manslayer that killeth any person unwittingly may flee thither. ^12And the cities shall be unto you for refuge from the avenger, that the manslayer die not, until he stand before the congregation for judgment. ^13And the cities which ye shall give shall be for you six cities of refuge. ^14Ye shall give three cities beyond the Jordan, and three cities shall ye give in the land of Canaan; they shall be cities of refuge. ^15For the children of Israel, and for the stranger and for the sojourner among them, shall these six cities be for refuge; that every one that killeth any person unwittingly may flee thither. ^16But if he smote him with an instrument of iron, so that he died, he is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death. ^17And if he smote him with a stone in the hand, whereby a man may die, and he died, he is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death. ^18Or if he smote him with a weapon of wood in the hand, whereby a man may die, and he died, he is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death. ^19The avenger of blood shall himself put the murderer to death: when he meeteth him, he shall put him to death. ^20And if he thrust him of hatred, or hurled at him, lying in wait, so that he died, ^21or in enmity smote him with his hand, so that he died; he that smote him shall surely be put to death; he is a murderer: the avenger of blood shall put the murderer to death, when he meeteth him.

^22But if he thrust him suddenly without enmity, or hurled upon him anything without lying in wait, ^23or with any stone, whereby a man may die, seeing him not, and cast it upon him, so that he died, and he was not his enemy, neither sought his harm; ^24then the congregation shall judge between the smiter and the avenger of blood according to these ordinances; ^25and the congregation shall deliver the manslayer out of the hand of the avenger of blood, and the congregation shall restore him to his city of refuge, whither he was fled: and he shall dwell therein until the death of the high priest, who was anointed with the holy oil. ^26But if the manslayer shall at any time go beyond the border of his city of refuge, whither he fleeth, ^27and the avenger of blood find him without the border of his city of refuge, and the avenger of blood slay the manslayer; he shall not be guilty of blood, ^28because he should have remained in his city of refuge until the death of the high priest: but after the death of the high priest the manslayer shall return into the land of his possession.

^29And these things shall be for a statute and ordinance unto you throughout your generations in all your dwellings. ^30Whoso killeth any person, the murderer shall be slain at the mouth of witnesses: but one witness shall not testify against any person that he die. ^31Moreover ye shall take no ransom for the life of a murderer, that is guilty of death; but he shall surely be put to death. ^32And ye shall take no ransom for him that is fled to his city of refuge, that he may come again to dwell in the land, until the death of the priest. ^33So ye shall not pollute the land wherein ye are: for blood, it polluteth the land; and no expiation can be made for the land for the blood that is shed therein, but by the blood of him that shed it. ^34And thou shalt not defile the land which ye inhabit, in the midst of which I dwell: for I, Jehovah, dwell in the midst of the children of Israel.

Numbers 36

36

^1And the heads of the fathers' houses of the family of the children of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, of the families of the sons of Joseph, came near, and spake before Moses, and before the princes, the heads of the fathers' houses of the children of Israel: ^2and they said, Jehovah commanded my lord to give the land for inheritance by lot to the children of Israel: and my lord was commanded by Jehovah to give the inheritance of Zelophehad our brother unto his daughters. ^3And if they be married to any of the sons of the other tribes of the children of Israel, then will their inheritance be taken away from the inheritance of our fathers, and will be added to the inheritance of the tribe whereunto they shall belong: so will it be taken away from the lot of our inheritance. ^4And when the jubilee of the children of Israel shall be, then will their inheritance be added unto the inheritance of the tribe whereunto they shall belong: so will their inheritance be taken away from the inheritance of the tribe of our fathers.

^5And Moses commanded the children of Israel according to the word of Jehovah, saying, The tribe of the sons of Joseph speaketh right. ^6This is the thing which Jehovah doth command concerning the daughters of Zelophehad, saying, Let them be married to whom they think best; only into the family of the tribe of their father shall they be married. ^7So shall no inheritance of the children of Israel remove from tribe to tribe; for the children of Israel shall cleave every one to the inheritance of the tribe of his fathers. ^8And every daughter, that possesseth an inheritance in any tribe of the children of Israel, shall be wife unto one of the family of the tribe of her father, that the children of Israel may possess every man the inheritance of his fathers. ^9So shall no inheritance remove from one tribe to another tribe; for the tribes of the children of Israel shall cleave every one to his own inheritance.

^10Even as Jehovah commanded Moses, so did the daughters of Zelophehad: ^11for Mahlah, Tirzah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Noah, the daughters of Zelophehad, were married unto their father's brothers' sons. ^12They were married into the families of the sons of Manasseh the son of Joseph; and their inheritance remained in the tribe of the family of their father.

^13These are the commandments and the ordinances which Jehovah commanded by Moses unto the children of Israel in the plains of Moab by the Jordan at Jericho.

Philippians 2

2

^1If there is therefore any exhortation in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any tender mercies and compassions, ^2make full my joy, that ye be of the same mind, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind; ^3doing nothing through faction or through vainglory, but in lowliness of mind each counting other better than himself; ^4not looking each of you to his own things, but each of you also to the things of others. ^5Have this mind in you, which was also in Christ Jesus: ^6who, existing in the form of God, counted not the being on an equality with God a thing to be grasped, ^7but emptied himself, taking the form of a servant, being made in the likeness of men; ^8and being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, becoming obedient even unto death, yea, the death of the cross. ^9Wherefore also God highly exalted him, and gave unto him the name which is above every name; ^10that in the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven and things on earth and things under the earth, ^11and that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father. ^12So then, my beloved, even as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling; ^13for it is God who worketh in you both to will and to work, for his good pleasure. ^14Do all things without murmurings and questionings: ^15that ye may become blameless and harmless, children of God without blemish in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, among whom ye are seen as lights in the world, ^16holding forth the word of life; that I may have whereof to glory in the day of Christ, that I did not run in vain neither labor in vain. ^17Yea, and if I am offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all: ^18and in the same manner do ye also joy, and rejoice with me. ^19But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state. ^20For I have no man likeminded, who will care truly for your state. ^21For they all seek their own, not the things of Jesus Christ. ^22But ye know the proof of him, that, as a child serveth a father, so he served with me in furtherance of the gospel. ^23Him therefore I hope to send forthwith, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me: ^24but I trust in the Lord that I myself also shall come shortly. ^25But I counted it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother and fellow-worker and fellow-soldier, and your messenger and minister to my need; ^26since he longed after you all, and was sore troubled, because ye had heard that he was sick: ^27for indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, that I might not have sorrow upon sorrow. ^28I have sent him therefore the more diligently, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful. ^29Receive him therefore in the Lord with all joy; and hold such in honor: ^30because for the work of Christ he came nigh unto death, hazarding his life to supply that which was lacking in your service toward me.

Philippians 3

3

^1Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed is not irksome, but for you it is safe. ^2Beware of the dogs, beware of the evil workers, beware of the concision: ^3for we are the circumcision, who worship by the Spirit of God, and glory in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh: ^4though I myself might have confidence even in the flesh: if any other man thinketh to have confidence in the flesh, I yet more: ^5circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee; ^6as touching zeal, persecuting the church; as touching the righteousness which is in the law, found blameless. ^7Howbeit what things were gain to me, these have I counted loss for Christ. ^8Yea verily, and I count all things to be loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I suffered the loss of all things, and do count them but refuse, that I may gain Christ, ^9and be found in him, not having a righteousness of mine own, even that which is of the law, but that which is through faith in Christ, the righteousness which is from God by faith: ^10that I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, becoming conformed unto his death; ^11if by any means I may attain unto the resurrection from the dead. ^12Not that I have already obtained, or am already made perfect: but I press on, if so be that I may lay hold on that for which also I was laid hold on by Christ Jesus. ^13Brethren, I could not myself yet to have laid hold: but one thing I do, forgetting the things which are behind, and stretching forward to the things which are before, ^14I press on toward the goal unto the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus. ^15Let us therefore, as many as are perfect, be thus minded: and if in anything ye are otherwise minded, this also shall God reveal unto you: ^16only, whereunto we have attained, by that same rule let us walk. ^17Brethren, be ye imitators together of me, and mark them that so walk even as ye have us for an ensample. ^18For many walk, of whom I told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the cross of Christ: ^19whose end is perdition, whose god is the belly, and whose glory is in their shame, who mind earthly things. ^20For our citizenship is in heaven; whence also we wait for a Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ: ^21who shall fashion anew the body of our humiliation, that it may be conformed to the body of his glory, according to the working whereby he is able even to subject all things unto himself.

Philippians 4

4

^1Wherefore, my brethren beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, my beloved. ^2I exhort Euodia, and I exhort Syntyche, to be of the same mind in the Lord. ^3Yea, I beseech thee also, true yokefellow, help these women, for they labored with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and the rest of my fellow-workers, whose names are in the book of life. ^4Rejoice in the Lord always: again I will say, Rejoice. ^5Let your forbearance be known unto all men. The Lord is at hand. ^6In nothing be anxious; but in everything by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known unto God. ^7And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall guard your hearts and your thoughts in Christ Jesus. ^8Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honorable, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, think on these things. ^9The things which ye both learned and received and heard and saw in me, these things do: and the God of peace shall be with you. ^10But I rejoice in the Lord greatly, that now at length ye have revived your thought for me; wherein ye did indeed take thought, but ye lacked opportunity. ^11Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, therein to be content. ^12I know how to be abased, and I know also how to abound: in everything and in all things have I learned the secret both to be filled and to be hungry, both to abound and to be in want. ^13I can do all things in him that strengtheneth me. ^14Howbeit ye did well that ye had fellowship with my affliction. ^15And ye yourselves also know, ye Philippians, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church had fellowship with me in the matter of giving and receiving but ye only; ^16for even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my need. ^17Not that I seek for the gift; but I seek for the fruit that increaseth to your account. ^18But I have all things, and abound: I am filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things that came from you, and odor of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to God. ^19And my God shall supply every need of yours according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus. ^20Now unto our God and Father be the glory for ever and ever. Amen. ^21Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren that are with me salute you. ^22All the saints salute you, especially they that are of Caesar's household. ^23The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.

Revelation 2

2

^1To the angel of the church in Ephesus write: These things saith he that holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, he that walketh in the midst of the seven golden candlesticks: ^2I know thy works, and thy toil and patience, and that thou canst not bear evil men, and didst try them that call themselves apostles, and they are not, and didst find them false; ^3and thou hast patience and didst bear for my name's sake, and hast not grown weary. ^4But I have this against thee, that thou didst leave thy first love. ^5Remember therefore whence thou art fallen, and repent and do the first works; or else I come to thee, and will move thy candlestick out of its place, except thou repent. ^6But this thou hast, that thou hatest the works of the Nicolaitans, which I also hate. ^7He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. To him that overcometh, to him will I give to eat of the tree of life, which is in the Paradise of God. ^8And to the angel of the church in Smyrna write: These things saith the first and the last, who was dead, and lived again: ^9I know thy tribulation, and thy poverty (but thou art rich), and the blasphemy of them that say they are Jews, and they art not, but are a synagogue of Satan. ^10Fear not the things which thou art about to suffer: behold, the devil is about to cast some of you into prison, that ye may be tried; and ye shall have tribulation ten days. Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee the crown of life. ^11He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. He that overcometh shall not be hurt of the second death. ^12and to the angel of the church in Pergamum write: These things saith he that hath the sharp two-edged sword: ^13I know where thou dwellest, even where Satan's throne is; and thou holdest fast my name, and didst not deny my faith, even in the days of Antipas my witness, my faithful one, who was killed among you, where Satan dwelleth. ^14But I have a few things against thee, because thou hast there some that hold the teaching of Balaam, who taught Balak to cast a stumblingblock before the children of Israel, to eat things sacrificed to idols, and to commit fornication. ^15So hast thou also some that hold the teaching of the Nicolaitans in like manner. ^16Repent therefore; or else I come to thee quickly, and I will make war against them with the sword of my mouth. ^17He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. To him that overcometh, to him will I give of the hidden manna, and I will give him a white stone, and upon the stone a new name written, which no one knoweth but he that receiveth it. ^18And to the angel of the church in Thyatira write: These things saith the Son of God, who hath his eyes like a flame of fire, and his feet are like unto burnished brass: ^19I know thy works, and thy love and faith and ministry and patience, and that thy last works are more than the first. ^20But I have this against thee, that thou sufferest the woman Jezebel, who calleth herself a prophetess; and she teacheth and seduceth my servants to commit fornication, and to eat things sacrificed to idols. ^21And I gave her time that she should repent; and she willeth not to repent of her fornication. ^22Behold, I cast her into a bed, and them that commit adultery with her into great tribulation, except they repent of her works. ^23And I will kill her children with death; and all the churches shall know that I am he that searcheth the reins and hearts: and I will give unto each one of you according to your works. ^24But to you I say, to the rest that are in Thyatira, as many as have not this teaching, who know not the deep things of Satan, as they are wont to say; I cast upon you none other burden. ^25Nevertheless that which ye have, hold fast till I come. ^26And he that overcometh, and he that keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give authority over the nations: ^27and he shall rule them with a rod of iron, as the vessels of the potter are broken to shivers; as I also have received of my Father: ^28and I will give him the morning star. ^29He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches.

Revelation 3

3

^1And to the angel of the church in Sardis write: These things saith he that hath the seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars: I know thy works, that thou hast a name that thou livest, and thou art dead. ^2Be thou watchful, and establish the things that remain, which were ready to die: for I have found no works of thine perfected before my God. ^3Remember therefore how thou hast received and didst hear; and keep it, and repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come as a thief, and thou shalt not know what hour I will come upon thee. ^4But thou hast a few names in Sardis that did not defile their garments: and they shall walk with me in white; for they are worthy. ^5He that overcometh shall thus be arrayed in white garments; and I will in no wise blot his name out of the book of life, and I will confess his name before my Father, and before his angels. ^6He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. ^7And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write: These things saith he that is holy, he that is true, he that hath the key of David, he that openeth and none shall shut, and that shutteth and none openeth: ^8I know thy works (behold, I have set before thee a door opened, which none can shut), that thou hast a little power, and didst keep my word, and didst not deny my name. ^9Behold, I give of the synagogue of Satan, of them that say they are Jews, and they are not, but do lie; behold, I will make them to come and worship before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee. ^10Because thou didst keep the word of my patience, I also will keep thee from the hour of trial, that hour which is to come upon the whole world, to try them that dwell upon the earth. ^11I come quickly: hold fast that which thou hast, that no one take thy crown. ^12He that overcometh, I will make him a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall go out thence no more: and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem, which cometh down out of heaven from my God, and mine own new name. ^13He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches. ^14And to the angel of the church in Laodicea write: These things saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God: ^15I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot: I would thou wert cold or hot. ^16So because thou art lukewarm, and neither hot nor cold, I will spew thee out of my mouth. ^17Because thou sayest, I am rich, and have gotten riches, and have need of nothing; and knowest not that thou art the wretched one and miserable and poor and blind and naked: ^18I counsel thee to buy of me gold refined by fire, that thou mayest become rich; and white garments, that thou mayest clothe thyself, and that the shame of thy nakedness be not made manifest; and eyesalve to anoint thine eyes, that thou mayest see. ^19As many as I love, I reprove and chasten: be zealous therefore, and repent. ^20Behold, I stand at the door and knock: if any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come in to him, and will sup with him, and he with me. ^21He that overcometh, I will give to him to sit down with me in my throne, as I also overcame, and sat down with my Father in his throne. ^22He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit saith to the churches.

Revelation 4

4

^1After these things I saw, and behold, a door opened in heaven, and the first voice that I heard, a voice as of a trumpet speaking with me, one saying, Come up hither, and I will show thee the things which must come to pass hereafter. ^2Straightway I was in the Spirit: and behold, there was a throne set in heaven, and one sitting upon the throne; ^3and he that sat was to look upon like a jasper stone and a sardius: and there was a rainbow round about the throne, like an emerald to look upon. ^4And round about the throne were four and twenty thrones: and upon the thrones I saw four and twenty elders sitting, arrayed in white garments; and on their heads crowns of gold. ^5And out of the throne proceed lightnings and voices and thunders. And there was seven lamps of fire burning before the throne, which are the seven Spirits of God; ^6and before the throne, as it were a sea of glass like a crystal; and in the midst of the throne, and round about the throne, four living creatures full of eyes before and behind. ^7And the first creature was like a lion, and the second creature like a calf, and the third creature had a face as of a man, and the fourth creature was like a flying eagle. ^8and the four living creatures, having each one of them six wings, are full of eyes round about and within: and they have no rest day and night, saying,

Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord God, the Almighty, who was and who is and who is to come.

^9And when the living creatures shall give glory and honor and thanks to him that sitteth on the throne, to him that liveth for ever and ever, ^10the four and twenty elders shall fall down before him that sitteth on the throne, and shall worship him that liveth for ever and ever, and shall cast their crowns before the throne, saying,

^11Worthy art thou, our Lord and our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power: for thou didst create all things, and because of thy will they were, and were created.

Revelation 5

5

^1And I saw in the right hand of him that sat on the throne a book written within and on the back, close sealed with seven seals. ^2And I saw a strong angel proclaiming with a great voice, Who is worthy to open the book, and to loose the seals thereof? ^3And no one in the heaven, or on the earth, or under the earth, was able to open the book, or to look thereon. ^4And I wept much, because no one was found worthy to open the book, or to look thereon: ^5and one of the elders saith unto me, Weep not; behold, the Lion that is of the tribe of Judah, the Root of David, hath overcome to open the book and the seven seals thereof. ^6And I saw in the midst of the throne and of the four living creatures, and in the midst of the elders, a Lamb standing, as though it had been slain, having seven horns, and seven eyes, which are the seven Spirits of God, sent forth into all the earth. ^7And he came, and he taketh it out of the right hand of him that sat on the throne. ^8And when he had taken the book, the four living creatures and the four and twenty elders fell down before the Lamb, having each one a harp, and golden bowls full of incense, which are the prayers of the saints. ^9And they sing a new song, saying,

Worthy art thou to take the book, and to open the seals thereof: for thou was slain, and didst purchase unto God with thy blood men of every tribe, and tongue, and people, and nation, ^10and madest them to be unto our God a kingdom and priests; and they reign upon earth.

^11And I saw, and I heard a voice of many angels round about the throne and the living creatures and the elders; and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands of thousands; ^12saying with a great voice,

Worthy is the Lamb that hath been slain to receive the power, and riches, and wisdom, and might and honor, and glory, and blessing.

^13And every created thing which is in the heaven, and on the earth, and under the earth, and on the sea, and all things are in them, heard I saying,

Unto him that sitteth on the throne, and unto the Lamb, be the blessing, and the honor, and the glory, and the dominion, for ever and ever.

^14And the four living creatures said, Amen. And the elders fell down and worshipped.

Revelation 6

6

^1And I saw when the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures saying as with a voice of thunder, Come. ^2And I saw, and behold, a white horse, and he that sat thereon had a bow; and there was given unto him a crown: and he came forth conquering, and to conquer. ^3And when he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying, Come. ^4And another horse came forth, a red horse: and to him that sat thereon it was given to take peace from the earth, and that they should slay one another: and there was given unto him a great sword. ^5And when he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying, Come. And I saw, and behold, a black horse; and he that sat thereon had a balance in his hand. ^6And I heard as it were a voice in the midst of the four living creatures saying, A measure of wheat for a shilling, and three measures of barley for a shilling; and the oil and the wine hurt thou not. ^7And when he opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth living creature saying, Come. ^8And I saw, and behold, a pale horse: and he that sat upon him, his name was Death; and Hades followed with him. And there was given unto them authority over the fourth part of the earth, to kill with sword, and with famine, and with death, and by the wild beasts of the earth. ^9And when he opened the fifth seal, I saw underneath the altar the souls of them that had been slain for the word of God, and for the testimony which they held: ^10and they cried with a great voice, saying, How long, O Master, the holy and true, dost thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth? ^11And there was given them to each one a white robe; and it was said unto them, that they should rest yet for a little time, until their fellow-servants also and their brethren, who should be killed even as they were, should have fulfilled their course. ^12And I saw when he opened the sixth seal, and there was a great earthquake; and the sun became black as sackcloth of hair, and the whole moon became as blood; ^13and the stars of the heaven fell unto the earth, as a fig tree casteth her unripe figs when she is shaken of a great wind. ^14And the heaven was removed as a scroll when it is rolled up; and every mountain and island were moved out of their places. ^15And the kings of the earth, and the princes, and the chief captains, and the rich, and the strong, and every bondman and freeman, hid themselves in the caves and in the rocks of the mountains; ^16and they say to the mountains and to the rocks, Fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that sitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb: ^17for the great day of their wrath is come; and who is able to stand?

Revelation 7

7

^1After this I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding the four winds of the earth, that no wind should blow on the earth, or on the sea, or upon any tree. ^2And I saw another angel ascend from the sunrising, having the seal of the living God: and he cried with a great voice to the four angels to whom it was given to hurt the earth and the sea, ^3saying, Hurt not the earth, neither the sea, nor the trees, till we shall have sealed the servants of our God on their foreheads. ^4And I heard the number of them that were sealed, a hundred and forty and four thousand, sealed out of every tribe of the children of Israel:

^5Of the tribe of Judah were sealed twelve thousand:

Of the tribe of Reuben twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Gad twelve thousand;

^6Of the tribe of Asher twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Naphtali twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Manasseh twelve thousand;

^7Of the tribe of Simeon twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Levi twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Issachar twelve thousand;

^8Of the tribe of Zebulun twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Joseph twelve thousand;

Of the tribe of Benjamin were sealed twelve thousand.

^9After these things I saw, and behold, a great multitude, which no man could number, out of every nation and of all tribes and peoples and tongues, standing before the throne and before the Lamb, arrayed in white robes, and palms in their hands; ^10and they cry with a great voice, saying,

Salvation unto our God who sitteth on the throne, and unto the Lamb.

^11And all the angels were standing round about the throne, and about the elders and the four living creatures; and they fell before the throne on their faces, and worshipped God, ^12saying,

Amen: Blessing, and glory, and wisdom, and thanksgiving, and honor, and power, and might, be unto our God for ever and ever. Amen.

^13And one of the elders answered, saying unto me, These that are arrayed in white robes, who are they, and whence came they? ^14And I say unto him, My lord, thou knowest. And he said to me, These are they that come of the great tribulation, and they washed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb. ^15Therefore are they before the throne of God; and they serve him day and night in his temple: and he that sitteth on the throne shall spread his tabernacle over them. ^16They shall hunger no more, neither thirst any more; neither shall the sun strike upon them, nor any heat: ^17for the Lamb that is in the midst of the throne shall be their shepherd, and shall guide them unto fountains of waters of life: and God shall wipe away every tear from their eyes.

Revelation 8

8

^1And when he opened the seventh seal, there followed a silence in heaven about the space of half an hour. ^2And I saw the seven angels that stand before God; and there were given unto them seven trumpets. ^3And another angel came and stood over the altar, having a golden censer; and there was given unto him much incense, that he should add it unto the prayers of all the saints upon the golden altar which was before the throne. ^4And the smoke of the incense, with the prayers of the saints, went up before God out of the angel's hand. ^5And the angel taketh the censer; and he filled it with the fire of the altar, and cast it upon the earth: and there followed thunders, and voices, and lightnings, and an earthquake. ^6And the seven angels that had the seven trumpets prepared themselves to sound. ^7And the first sounded, and there followed hail and fire, mingled with blood, and they were cast upon the earth: and the third part of the earth was burnt up, and the third part of the trees was burnt up, and all green grass was burnt up. ^8And the second angel sounded, and as it were a great mountain burning with fire was cast into the sea: and the third part of the sea became blood; ^9and there died the third part of the creatures which were in the sea, even they that had life; and the third part of the ships was destroyed. ^10And the third angel sounded, and there fell from heaven a great star, burning as a torch, and it fell upon the third part of the rivers, and upon the fountains of the waters; ^11and the name of the star is called Wormwood: and the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many men died of the waters, because they were made bitter. ^12And the fourth angel sounded, and the third part of the sun was smitten, and the third part of the moon, and the third part of the stars; that the third part of them should be darkened, and the day should not shine for the third part of it, and the night in like manner. ^13And I saw, and I heard an eagle, flying in mid heaven, saying with a great voice, Woe, woe, woe, for them that dwell on the earth, by reason of the other voices of the trumpet of the three angels, who are yet to sound.

Revelation 9

9

^1And the fifth angel sounded, and I saw a star from heaven fallen unto the earth: and there was given to him the key of the pit of the abyss. ^2And he opened the pit of the abyss; and there went up a smoke out of the pit, as the smoke of a great furnace; and the sun and the air were darkened by reason of the smoke of the pit. ^3And out of the smoke came forth locusts upon the earth; and power was given them, as the scorpions of the earth have power. ^4And it was said unto them that they should not hurt the grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree, but only such men as have not the seal of God on their foreheads. ^5And it was given them that they should not kill them, but that they should be tormented five months: and their torment was as the torment of a scorpion, when it striketh a man. ^6And in those days men shall seek death, and shall in no wise find it; and they shall desire to die, and death fleeth from them. ^7And the shapes of the locusts were like unto horses prepared for war; and upon their heads as it were crowns like unto gold, and their faces were as men's faces. ^8And they had hair as the hair of women, and their teeth were as teeth of lions. ^9And they had breastplates, as it were breastplates of iron; and the sound of their wings was as the sound of chariots, of many horses rushing to war. ^10And they have tails like unto scorpions, and stings; and in their tails is their power to hurt men five months. ^11They have over them as king the angel of the abyss: his name in Hebrew is Abaddon, and in the Greek tongue he hath the name Apollyon. ^12The first Woe is past: behold, there come yet two Woes hereafter. ^13And the sixth angel sounded, and I heard a voice from the horns of the golden altar which is before God, ^14one saying to the sixth angel that had one trumpet, Loose the four angels that are bound at the great river Euphrates. ^15And the four angels were loosed, that had been prepared for the hour and day and month and year, that they should kill the third part of men. ^16And the number of the armies of the horsemen was twice ten thousand times ten thousand: I heard the number of them. ^17And thus I saw the horses in the vision, and them that sat on them, having breastplates as of fire and of hyacinth and of brimstone: and the heads of lions; and out of their mouths proceedeth fire and smoke and brimstone. ^18By these three plagues was the third part of men killed, by the fire and the smoke and the brimstone, which proceeded out of their mouths. ^19For the power of the horses is in their mouth, and in their tails: for their tails are like unto serpents, and have heads; and with them they hurt. ^20And the rest of mankind, who were not killed with these plagues, repented not of the works of their hands, that they should not worship demons, and the idols of gold, and of silver, and of brass, and of stone, and of wood; which can neither see, nor hear, nor walk: ^21and they repented not of their murders, nor of their sorceries, nor of their fornication, nor of their thefts.

Revelation 10

10

^1And I saw another strong angel coming down out of heaven, arrayed with a cloud; and the rainbow was upon his head, and his face was as the sun, and his feet as pillars of fire; ^2and he had in his hand a little book open: and he set his right foot upon the sea, and his left upon the earth; ^3and he cried with a great voice, as a lion roareth: and when he cried, the seven thunders uttered their voices. ^4And when the seven thunders uttered their voices, I was about to write: and I heard a voice from heaven saying, Seal up the things which the seven thunders uttered, and write them not. ^5And the angel that I saw standing upon the sea and upon the earth lifted up his right hand to heaven, ^6and sware by him that liveth for ever and ever, who created the heaven and the things that are therein, and the earth and the things that are therein, and the sea and the things that are therein, that there shall be delay no longer: ^7but in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he is about to sound, then is finished the mystery of God, according to the good tidings which he declared to his servants the prophets. ^8And the voice which I heard from heaven, I heard it again speaking with me, and saying, Go, take the book which is open in the hand of the angel that standeth upon the sea and upon the earth. ^9And I went unto the angel, saying unto him that he should give me the little book. And he saith unto me, Take it, and eat it up; and it shall make thy belly bitter, but in thy mouth it shall be sweet as honey. ^10And I took the little book out of the angel's hand, and ate it up; and it was in my mouth sweet as honey: and when I had eaten it, my belly was made bitter. ^11And they say unto me, Thou must prophesy again over many peoples and nations and tongues and kings.

Revelation 11

11

^1And there was given me a reed like unto a rod: and one said, Rise, and measure the temple of God, and the altar, and them that worship therein. ^2And the court which is without the temple leave without, and measure it not; for it hath been given unto the nations: and the holy city shall they tread under foot forty and two months. ^3And I will give unto my two witnesses, and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred and threescore days, clothed in sackcloth. ^4These are the two olive trees and the two candlesticks, standing before the Lord of the earth. ^5And if any man desireth to hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth and devoureth their enemies; and if any man shall desire to hurt them, in this manner must he be killed. ^6These have the power to shut the heaven, that it rain not during the days of their prophecy: and they have power over the waters to turn them into blood, and to smite the earth with every plague, as often as they shall desire. ^7And when they shall have finished their testimony, the beast that cometh up out of the abyss shall make war with them, and overcome them, and kill them. ^8And their dead bodies lie in the street of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt, where also their Lord was crucified. ^9And from among the peoples and tribes and tongues and nations do men look upon their dead bodies three days and a half, and suffer not their dead bodies to be laid in a tomb. ^10And they that dwell on the earth rejoice over them, and make merry; and they shall send gifts one to another; because these two prophets tormented them that dwell on the earth. ^11And after the three days and a half the breath of life from God entered into them, and they stood upon their feet; and great fear fell upon them that beheld them. ^12And they heard a great voice from heaven saying unto them, Come up hither. And they went up into heaven in the cloud; and their enemies beheld them. ^13And in that hour there was a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the city fell; and there were killed in the earthquake seven thousand persons: and the rest were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of heaven. ^14The second Woe is past: behold, the third Woe cometh quickly. ^15And the seventh angel sounded; and there followed great voices in heaven, and they said,

The kingdom of the world is become the kingdom of our Lord, and of his Christ: and he shall reign for ever and ever.

^16And the four and twenty elders, who sit before God on their thrones, fell upon their faces and worshipped God, ^17saying,

We give thee thanks, O Lord God, the Almighty, who art and who wast; because thou hast taken thy great power, and didst reign. ^18And the nations were wroth, and thy wrath came, and the time of the dead to be judged, and the time to give their reward to thy servants the prophets, and to the saints, and to them that fear thy name, the small and the great; and to destroy them that destroy the earth.

^19And there was opened the temple of God that is in heaven; and there was seen in his temple the ark of his covenant; and there followed lightnings, and voices, and thunders, and an earthquake, and great hail.

Revelation 12

12

^1And a great sign was seen in heaven: a woman arrayed with the sun, and the moon under her feet, and upon her head a crown of twelve stars; ^2and she was the child; and she crieth out, travailing in birth, and in pain to be delivered. ^3And there was seen another sign in heaven: and behold, a great red dragon, having seven heads and ten horns, and upon his heads seven diadems. ^4And his tail draweth the third part of the stars of heaven, and did cast them to the earth: and the dragon standeth before the woman that is about to be delivered, that when she is delivered he may devour her child. ^5And she was delivered of a son, a man child, who is to rule all the nations with a rod of iron: and her child was caught up unto God, and unto his throne. ^6And the woman fled into the wilderness, where she hath a place prepared of God, that there they may nourish her a thousand two hundred and threescore days. ^7And there was war in heaven: Michael and his angels going forth to war with the dragon; and the dragon warred and his angels; ^8And they prevailed not, neither was their place found any more in heaven. ^9And the great dragon was cast down, the old serpent, he that is called the Devil and Satan, the deceiver of the whole world; he was cast down to the earth, and his angels were cast down with him. ^10And I heard a great voice in heaven, saying,

Now is come the salvation, and the power, and the kingdom of our God, and the authority of his Christ: for the accuser of our brethren is cast down, who accuseth them before our God day and night. ^11And they overcame him because of the blood of the Lamb, and because of the word of their testimony; and they loved not their life even unto death. ^12Therefore rejoice, O heavens, and ye that dwell in them. Woe for the earth and for the sea: because the devil is gone down unto you, having great wrath, knowing that he hath but a short time.

^13And when the dragon saw that he was cast down to the earth, he persecuted the woman that brought forth the man child. ^14And there were given to the woman the two wings of the great eagle, that she might fly into the wilderness unto her place, where she is nourished for a time, and times, and half a time, from the face of the serpent. ^15And the serpent cast out of his mouth after the woman water as a river, that he might cause her to be carried away by the stream. ^16And the earth helped the woman, and the earth opened her mouth and swallowed up the river which the dragon cast out of his mouth. ^17And the dragon waxed wroth with the woman, and went away to make war with the rest of her seed, that keep the commandments of God, and hold the testimony of Jesus:

Revelation 13

13

^1and he stood upon the sand of the sea. And I saw a beast coming up out of the sea, having ten horns, and seven heads, and on his horns ten diadems, and upon his heads names of blasphemy. ^2And the beast which I saw was like unto a leopard, and his feet were as the feet of a bear, and his mouth as the mouth of a lion: and the dragon gave him his power, and his throne, and great authority. ^3And I saw one of his heads as though it had been smitten unto death; and his death-stroke was healed: and the whole earth wondered after the beast; ^4and they worshipped the dragon, because he gave his authority unto the beast; and they worshipped the beast, saying, Who is like unto the beast? And who is able to war with him? ^5and there was given to him a mouth speaking great things and blasphemies; and there was given to him authority to continue forty and two months. ^6And he opened his mouth for blasphemies against God, to blaspheme his name, and his tabernacle, even them that dwell in the heaven. ^7And it was given unto him to make war with the saints, and to overcome them: and there was given to him authority over every tribe and people and tongue and nation. ^8And all that dwell on the earth shall worship him, every one whose name hath not been written from the foundation of the world in the book of life of the Lamb that hath been slain. ^9If any man hath an ear, let him hear. ^10If any man is for captivity, into captivity he goeth: if any man shall kill with the sword, with the sword must he be killed. Here is the patience and the faith of the saints. ^11And I saw another beast coming up out of the earth; and he had two horns like unto lamb, and he spake as a dragon. ^12And he exerciseth all the authority of the first beast in his sight. And he maketh the earth and them dwell therein to worship the first beast, whose death-stroke was healed. ^13And he doeth great signs, that he should even make fire to come down out of heaven upon the earth in the sight of men. ^14And he deceiveth them that dwell on the earth by reason of the signs which it was given him to do in the sight of the beast; saying to them that dwell on the earth, that they should make an image to the beast who hath the stroke of the sword and lived. ^15And it was given unto him to give breath to it, even to the image to the beast, that the image of the beast should both speak, and cause that as many as should not worship the image of the beast should be killed. ^16And he causeth all, the small and the great, and the rich and the poor, and the free and the bond, that there be given them a mark on their right hand, or upon their forehead; ^17and that no man should be able to buy or to sell, save he that hath the mark, even the name of the beast or the number of his name. ^18Here is wisdom. He that hath understanding, let him count the number of the beast; for it is the number of a man: and his number is Six hundred and sixty and six.

Revelation 14

14

^1And I saw, and behold, the Lamb standing on the mount Zion, and with him a hundred and forty and four thousand, having his name, and the name of his Father, written on their foreheads. ^2And I heard a voice from heaven, as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of a great thunder: and the voice which I heard was as the voice of harpers harping with their harps: ^3and they sing as it were a new song before the throne, and before the four living creatures and the elders: and no man could learn the song save the hundred and forty and four thousand, even they that had been purchased out of the earth. ^4These are they that were not defiled with women; for they are virgins. These are they that follow the Lamb whithersoever he goeth. These were purchased from among men, to be the firstfruits unto God and unto the Lamb. ^5And in their mouth was found no lie: they are without blemish. ^6And I saw another angel flying in mid heaven, having eternal good tidings to proclaim unto them that dwell on the earth, and unto every nation and tribe and tongue and people; ^7and he saith with a great voice, Fear God, and give him glory; for the hour of his judgment is come: and worship him that made the heaven and the earth and sea and fountains of waters. ^8And another, a second angel, followed, saying, Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great, that hath made all the nations to drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication. ^9And another angel, a third, followed them, saying with a great voice, If any man worshippeth the beast and his image, and receiveth a mark on his forehead, or upon his hand, ^10he also shall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is prepared unmixed in the cup of his anger; and he shall be tormented with fire and brimstone in the presence of the holy angels, and in the presence of the Lamb: ^11and the smoke of their torment goeth up for ever and ever; and they have no rest day and night, they that worship the beast and his image, and whoso receiveth the mark of his name. ^12Here is the patience of the saints, they that keep the commandments of God, and the faith of Jesus. ^13And I heard the voice from heaven saying, Write, Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord from henceforth: yea, saith the Spirit, that they may rest from their labors; for their works follow with them. ^14And I saw, and behold, a white cloud; and on the cloud I saw one sitting like unto a son of man, having on his head a golden crown, and in his hand sharp sickle. ^15And another angel came out from the temple, crying with a great voice to him that sat on the cloud, Send forth thy sickle, and reap: for the hour to reap is come; for the harvest of the earth is ripe. ^16And he that sat on the cloud cast his sickle upon the earth; and the earth was reaped. ^17Another angel came out from the temple which is in heaven, he also having a sharp sickle. ^18And another angel came out from the altar, he that hath power over fire; and he called with a great voice to him that had the sharp sickle, saying, Send forth thy sharp sickle, and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth; for her grapes are fully ripe. ^19And the angel cast his sickle into the earth, and gathered the vintage of the earth, and cast it into the winepress, the great winepress, of the wrath of God. ^20And the winepress are trodden without the city, and there came out blood from the winepress, even unto the bridles of the horses, as far as a thousand and six hundred furlongs.

Revelation 15

15

^1And I saw another sign in heaven, great and marvellous, seven angels having seven plagues, which are the last, for in them is finished the wrath of God. ^2And I saw as it were a sea of glass mingled with fire; and them that come off victorious from the beast, and from his image, and from the number of his name, standing by the sea of glass, having harps of God. ^3And they sing the song of Moses the servant of God, and the song of the Lamb, saying,

Great and marvellous are thy works, O Lord God, the Almighty; righteous and true are thy ways, thou King of the ages. ^4Who shall not fear, O Lord, and glorify thy name? for thou only art holy; for all the nations shall come and worship before thee; for thy righteous acts have been made manifest.

^5And after these things I saw, and the temple of the tabernacle of the testimony in heaven was opened: ^6and there came out from the temple the seven angels that had the seven plagues, arrayed with precious stone, pure and bright, and girt about their breasts with golden girdles. ^7And one of the four living creatures gave unto the seven angels seven golden bowls full of the wrath of God, who liveth for ever and ever. ^8And the temple was filled with smoke from the glory of God, and from his power; and none was able to enter into the temple, till the seven plagues of the seven angels should be finished.

Revelation 16

16

^1And I heard a great voice out of the temple, saying to the seven angels, Go ye, and pour out the seven bowls of the wrath of God into the earth. ^2And the first went, and poured out his bowl into the earth; and it became a noisome and grievous sore upon the men that had the mark of the beast, and that worshipped his image. ^3And the second poured out his bowl into the sea; and it became blood as of a dead man; and every living soul died, even the things that were in the sea. ^4And the third poured out his bowl into the rivers and the fountains of the waters; and it became blood. ^5And I heard the angel of the waters saying, Righteous art thou, who art and who wast, thou Holy One, because thou didst thus judge: ^6for they poured out the blood of the saints and the prophets, and blood hast thou given them to drink: they are worthy. ^7And I heard the altar saying, Yea, O Lord God, the Almighty, true and righteous are thy judgments. ^8And the fourth poured out his bowl upon the sun; and it was given unto it to scorch men with fire. ^9And men were scorched men with great heat: and they blasphemed the name of God who hath the power over these plagues; and they repented not to give him glory. ^10And the fifth poured out his bowl upon the throne of the beast; and his kingdom was darkened; and they gnawed their tongues for pain, ^11and they blasphemed the God of heaven because of their pains and their sores; and they repented not of their works. ^12And the sixth poured out his bowl upon the great river, the river Euphrates; and the water thereof was dried up, that the way might by made ready for the kings that come from the sunrising. ^13And I saw coming out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beast, and out of the mouth of the false prophet, three unclean spirits, as it were frogs: ^14for they are spirits of demons, working signs; which go forth unto the kings of the whole world, to gather them together unto the war of the great day of God, the Almighty. ^15(Behold, I come as a thief. Blessed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, lest he walked naked, and they see his shame.) ^16And they gathered them together into the place which is called in Hebrew Har-magedon. ^17And the seventh poured out his bowl upon the air; and there came forth a great voice out of the temple, from the throne, saying, It is done: ^18and there were lightnings, and voices, and thunders; and there was a great earthquake, such as was not since there were men upon the earth, so great an earthquake, so mighty. ^19And the great city was divided into three parts, and the cities of the nations fell: and Babylon the great was remembered in the sight of God, to give unto her the cup of the wine of the fierceness of his wrath. ^20And every island fled away, and the mountains were not found. ^21And great hail, every stone about the weight of a talent, cometh down out of heaven upon men: and men blasphemed God because of the plague of the hail; for the plague thereof is exceeding great.

Revelation 17

17

^1And there came one of the seven angels that had the seven bowls, and spake with me, saying, Come hither, I will show thee the judgment of the great harlot that sitteth upon many waters; ^2with whom the kings of the earth committed fornication, and they that dwell in the earth were made drunken with the wine of her fornication. ^3And he carried me away in the Spirit into a wilderness: and I saw a woman sitting upon a scarlet-colored beast, full of names of blasphemy, having seven heads and ten horns. ^4And the woman was arrayed in purple and scarlet, and decked with gold and precious stone and pearls, having in her hand a golden cup full of abominations, even the unclean things of her fornication, ^5and upon her forehead a name written, MYSTERY, BABYLON THE GREAT, THE MOTHER OF THE HARLOTS AND OF THE ABOMINATIONS OF THE EARTH. ^6And I saw the woman drunken with the blood of the saints, and with the blood of the martyrs of Jesus. And when I saw her, I wondered with a great wonder. ^7And the angel said unto me, Wherefore didst thou wonder? I will tell thee the mystery of the woman, and of the beast that carrieth her, which hath the seven heads and the ten horns. ^8The beast that thou sawest was, and is not; and is about to come up out of the abyss, and to go into perdition. And they that dwell on the earth shall wonder, they whose name hath not been written in the book of life from the foundation of the world, when they behold the beast, how that he was, and is not, and shall come. ^9Here is the mind that hath wisdom. The seven heads are seven mountains, on which the woman sitteth: ^10and they are seven kings; the five are fallen, the one is, the other is not yet come; and when he cometh, he must continue a little while. ^11And the beast that was, and is not, is himself also an eighth, and is of the seven; and he goeth into perdition. ^12And the ten horns that thou sawest are ten kings, who have received no kingdom as yet; but they receive authority as kings, with the beast, for one hour. ^13These have one mind, and they give their power and authority unto the beast. ^14These shall war against the Lamb, and the Lamb shall overcome them, for he is Lord of lords, and King of kings; and they also shall overcome that are with him, called and chosen and faithful. ^15And he saith unto me, The waters which thou sawest, where the harlot sitteth, are peoples, and multitudes, and nations, and tongues. ^16And the ten horns which thou sawest, and the beast, these shall hate the harlot, and shall make her desolate and naked, and shall eat her flesh, and shall burn her utterly with fire. ^17For God did put in their hearts to do his mind, and to come to one mind, and to give their kingdom unto the beast, until the words of God should be accomplished. ^18And the woman whom thou sawest is the great city, which reigneth over the kings of the earth.

Revelation 18

18

^1After these things I saw another angel coming down out of heaven, having great authority; and the earth was lightened with his glory. ^2And he cried with a mighty voice, saying, Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great, and is become a habitation of demons, and a hold of every unclean spirit, and a hold of every unclean and hateful bird. ^3For by the wine of the wrath of her fornication all the nations are fallen; and the kings of the earth committed fornication with her, and the merchants of the earth waxed rich by the power of her wantonness. ^4And I heard another voice from heaven, saying, Come forth, my people, out of her, that ye have no fellowship with her sins, and that ye receive not of her plagues: ^5for her sins have reached even unto heaven, and God hath remembered her iniquities. ^6Render unto her even as she rendered, and double unto her the double according to her works: in the cup which she mingled, mingle unto her double. ^7How much soever she glorified herself, and waxed wanton, so much give her of torment and mourning: for she saith in her heart, I sit a queen, and am no widow, and shall in no wise see mourning. ^8Therefore in one day shall her plagues come, death, and mourning, and famine; and she shall be utterly burned with fire; for strong is the Lord God who judged her. ^9And the kings of the earth, who committed fornication and lived wantonly with her, shall weep and wail over her, when they look upon the smoke of her burning, ^10standing afar off for the fear of her torment, saying, Woe, woe, the great city, Babylon, the strong city! for in one hour is thy judgment come. ^11And the merchants of the earth weep and mourn over her, for no man buyeth their merchandise any more; ^12merchandise of gold, and silver, and precious stone, and pearls, and fine linen, and purple, and silk, and scarlet; and all thyine wood, and every vessel of ivory, and every vessel made of most precious wood, and of brass, and iron, and marble; ^13and cinnamon, and spice, and incense, and ointment, and frankincense, and wine, and oil, and fine flour, and wheat, and cattle, and sheep; and merchandise of horses and chariots and slaves; and souls of men. ^14And the fruits which thy soul lusted after are gone from thee, and all things that were dainty and sumptuous are perished from thee, and men shall find them no more at all. ^15The merchants of these things, who were made rich by her, shall stand afar off for the fear of her torment, weeping and mourning; ^16saying, Woe, woe, the great city, she that was arrayed in fine linen and purple and scarlet, and decked with gold and precious stone and pearl! ^17for in an hour so great riches is made desolate. And every shipmaster, and every one that saileth any wither, and mariners, and as many as gain their living by sea, stood afar off, ^18and cried out as they looked upon the smoke of her burning, saying, What city is like the great city? ^19And they cast dust on their heads, and cried, weeping and mourning, saying, Woe, woe, the great city, wherein all that had their ships in the sea were made rich by reason of her costliness! for in one hour is she made desolate. ^20Rejoice over her, thou heaven, and ye saints, and ye apostles, and ye prophets; for God hath judged your judgment on her. ^21And a strong angel took up a stone as it were a great millstone and cast it into the sea, saying, Thus with a mighty fall shall Babylon, the great city, be cast down, and shall be found no more at all. ^22And the voice of harpers and minstrels and flute-players and trumpeters shall be heard no more at all in thee; and no craftsman, of whatsoever craft, shall be found any more at all in thee; and the voice of a mill shall be heard no more at all in thee; ^23and the light of a lamp shall shine no more at all in thee; and the voice of the bridegroom and of the bride shall be heard no more at all in thee: for thy merchants were the princes of the earth; for with thy sorcery were all the nations deceived. ^24And in her was found the blood of prophets and of saints, and of all that have been slain upon the earth.

Revelation 19

19

^1After these things I heard as it were a great voice of a great multitude in heaven, saying,

Hallelujah; Salvation, and glory, and power, belong to our God: ^2for true and righteous are his judgments; for he hath judged the great harlot, her that corrupted the earth with her fornication, and he hath avenged the blood of his servants at her hand.

^3And a second time they say, Hallelujah. And her smoke goeth up for ever and ever. ^4And the four and twenty elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshipped God that sitteth on the throne, saying, Amen; Hallelujah. ^5And a voice came forth from the throne, saying,

Give praise to our God, all ye his servants, ye that fear him, the small and the great.

^6And I heard as it were the voice of a great multitude, and as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of mighty thunders, saying,

Hallelujah: for the Lord our God, the Almighty, reigneth. ^7Let us rejoice and be exceeding glad, and let us give the glory unto him: for the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his wife hath made herself ready. ^8And it was given unto her that she should array herself in fine linen, bright and pure: for the fine linen is the righteous acts of the saints.

^9And he saith unto me, Write, Blessed are they that are bidden to the marriage supper of the Lamb. And he saith unto me, These are true words of God. ^10And I fell down before his feet to worship him. And he saith unto me, See thou do it not: I am a fellow-servant with thee and with thy brethren that hold the testimony of Jesus: worship God; for the testimony of Jesus is the spirit of prophecy. ^11And I saw the heaven opened; and behold, a white horse, and he that sat thereon called Faithful and True; and in righteous he doth judge and make war. ^12And his eyes are a flame of fire, and upon his head are many diadems; and he hath a name written which no one knoweth but he himself. ^13And he is arrayed in a garment sprinkled with blood: and his name is called The Word of God. ^14And the armies which are in heaven followed him upon white horses, clothed in fine linen, white and pure. ^15And out of his mouth proceedeth a sharp sword, that with it he should smite the nations: and he shall rule them with a rod of iron: and he treadeth the winepress of the fierceness of the wrath of God, the Almighty. ^16And he hath on his garment and on his thigh a name written, KINGS OF KINGS, AND LORD OF LORDS. ^17And I saw an angel standing in the sun; and he cried with a loud voice, saying to all the birds that fly in mid heaven, Come and be gathered together unto the great supper of God; ^18that ye may eat the flesh of kings, and the flesh of captains, and the flesh of mighty men, and the flesh of horses and of them that sit thereon, and the flesh of all men, both free and bond, and small and great. ^19And I saw the beast, and the kings of the earth, and their armies, gathered together to make war against him that sat upon the horse, and against his army. ^20And the beast was taken, and with him the false prophet that wrought the signs in his sight, wherewith he deceived them that had received the mark of the beast and them that worshipped his image: they two were cast alive into the lake of fire that burneth with brimstone: ^21and the rest were killed with the sword of him that sat upon the horse, even the sword which came forth out of his mouth: and all the birds were filled with their flesh.

Revelation 20

20

^1And I saw an angel coming down out of heaven, having the key of the abyss and a great chain in his hand. ^2And he laid hold on the dragon, the old serpent, which is the Devil and Satan, and bound him for a thousand years, ^3and cast him into the abyss, and shut it, and sealed it over him, that he should deceive the nations no more, until the thousand years should be finished: after this he must be loosed for a little time. ^4And I saw thrones, and they sat upon them, and judgment was given unto them: and I saw the souls of them that had been beheaded for the testimony of Jesus, and for the word of God, and such as worshipped not the beast, neither his image, and received not the mark upon their forehead and upon their hand; and they lived, and reigned with Christ a thousand years. ^5The rest of the dead lived not until the thousand years should be finished. This is the first resurrection. ^6Blessed and holy is he that hath part in the first resurrection: over these the second death hath no power; but they shall be priests of God and of Christ, and shall reign with him a thousand years. ^7And when the thousand years are finished, Satan shall be loosed out of his prison, ^8and shall come forth to deceive the nations which are in the four corners of the earth, Gog and Magog, to gather them together to the war: the number of whom is as the sand of the sea. ^9And they went up over the breadth of the earth, and compassed the camp of the saints about, and the beloved city: and fire came down out of heaven, and devoured them. ^10And the devil that deceived them was cast into the lake of fire and brimstone, where are also the beast and the false prophet; and they shall be tormented day and night for ever and ever. ^11And I saw a great white throne, and him that sat upon it, from whose face the earth and the heaven fled away; and there was found no place for them. ^12And I saw the dead, the great and the small, standing before the throne; and books were opened: and another book was opened, which is the book of life: and the dead were judged out of the things which were written in the books, according to their works. ^13And the sea gave up the dead that were in it; and death and Hades gave up the dead that were in them: and they were judged every man according to their works. ^14And death and Hades were cast into the lake of fire. This is the second death, even the lake of fire. ^15And if any was not found written in the book of life, he was cast into the lake of fire.

Revelation 21

21

^1And I saw a new heaven and a new earth: for the first heaven and the first earth are passed away; and the sea is no more. ^2And I saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven of God, made ready as a bride adorned for her husband. ^3And I heard a great voice out of the throne saying, Behold, the tabernacle of God is with men, and he shall dwell with them, and they shall be his peoples, and God himself shall be with them, and be their God: ^4and he shall wipe away every tear from their eyes; and death shall be no more; neither shall there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain, any more: the first things are passed away. ^5And he that sitteth on the throne said, Behold, I make all things new. And he saith, Write: for these words are faithful and true. ^6And he said unto me, They are come to pass. I am the Alpha and the Omega, the beginning and the end. I will give unto him that is athirst of the fountain of the water of life freely. ^7He that overcometh shall inherit these things; and I will be his God, and he shall be my son. ^8But for the fearful, and unbelieving, and abominable, and murderers, and fornicators, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all liars, their part shall be in the lake that burneth with fire and brimstone; which is the second death. ^9And there came one of the seven angels who had the seven bowls, who were laden with the seven last plagues; and he spake with me, saying, Come hither, I will show thee the bride, the wife of the Lamb. ^10And he carried me away in the Spirit to a mountain great and high, and showed me the holy city Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, ^11having the glory of God: her light was like unto a stone most precious, as it were a jasper stone, clear as crystal: ^12having a wall great and high; having twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels; and names written thereon, which are the names of the twelve tribes of the children of Israel: ^13on the east were three gates; and on the north three gates; and on the south three gates; and on the west three gates. ^14And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and on them twelve names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb. ^15And he that spake with me had for a measure a golden reed to measure the city, and the gates thereof, and the wall thereof. ^16And the city lieth foursquare, and the length thereof is as great as the breadth: and he measured the city with the reed, twelve thousand furlongs: the length and the breadth and the height thereof are equal. ^17And he measured the wall thereof, a hundred and forty and four cubits, according to the measure of a man, that is, of an angel. ^18And the building of the wall thereof was jasper: and the city was pure gold, like unto pure glass. ^19The foundations of the wall of the city were adorned with all manner of precious stones. The first foundation was jasper; the second, sapphire; the third, chalcedony; the fourth, emerald; ^20the fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, sardius; the seventh, chrysolite; the eighth, beryl; the ninth, topaz; the tenth, chrysoprase; the eleventh, jacinth; the twelfth, amethyst. ^21And the twelve gates were twelve pearls; each one of the several gates was of one pearl: and the street of the city was pure gold, as it were transparent glass. ^22And I saw no temple therein: for the Lord God the Almighty, and the Lamb, are the temple thereof. ^23And the city hath no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine upon it: for the glory of God did lighten it, and the lamp thereof is the Lamb. ^24And the nations shall walk amidst the light thereof: and the kings of the earth bring their glory into it. ^25And the gates thereof shall in no wise be shut by day (for there shall be no night there): ^26and they shall bring the glory and the honor of the nations into it: ^27and there shall in no wise enter into it anything unclean, or he that maketh an abomination and a lie: but only they that are written in the Lamb's book of life.

Revelation 22

22

^1And he showed me a river of water of life, bright as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lamb, ^2in the midst of the street thereof. And on this side of the river and on that was the tree of life, bearing twelve manner of fruits, yielding its fruit every month: and the leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations. ^3And there shall be no curse any more: and the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be therein: and his servants shall serve him; ^4and they shall see his face; and his name shall be on their foreheads. ^5And there shall be night no more; and they need no light of lamp, neither light of sun; for the Lord God shall give them light: and they shall reign for ever and ever. ^6And he said unto me, These words are faithful and true: and the Lord, the God of the spirits of the prophets, sent his angels to show unto his servants the things which must shortly come to pass. ^7And behold, I come quickly. Blessed is he that keepeth the words of the prophecy of this book. ^8And I John am he that heard and saw these things. And when I heard and saw, I fell down to worship before the feet of the angel that showed me these things. ^9And he saith unto me, See thou do it not: I am a fellow-servant with thee and with thy brethren the prophets, and with them that keep the words of this book: worship God. ^10And he saith unto me, Seal not up the words of the prophecy of this book; for the time is at hand. ^11He that is unrighteous, let him do unrighteousness still: and he that is filthy, let him be made filthy still: and he that is righteous, let him do righteousness still: and he that is holy, let him be made holy still. ^12Behold, I come quickly; and my reward is with me, to render to each man according as his work is. ^13I am the Alpha and the Omega, the first and the last, the beginning and the end. ^14Blessed are they that wash their robes, that they may have the right to come to the tree of life, and may enter in by the gates into the city. ^15Without are the dogs, and the sorcerers, and the fornicators, and the murderers, and the idolaters, and every one that loveth and maketh a lie. ^16I Jesus have sent mine angel to testify unto you these things for the churches. I am the root and the offspring of David, the bright, the morning star. ^17And the Spirit and the bride say, Come. And he that heareth, let him say, Come. And he that is athirst, let him come: he that will, let him take the water of life freely. ^18I testify unto every man that heareth the words of the prophecy of this book, if any man shall add unto them, God shall add unto him the plagues which are written in this book: ^19and if any man shall take away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God shall take away his part from the tree of life, and out of the holy city, which are written in this book. ^20He who testifieth these things saith, Yea: I come quickly. Amen: come, Lord Jesus. ^21The grace of the Lord Jesus be with the saints. Amen.

Romans 2

2

^1Wherefore thou art without excuse, O man, whosoever thou art that judgest: for wherein thou judges another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest dost practise the same things. ^2And we know that the judgment of God is according to truth against them that practise such things. ^3And reckonest thou this, O man, who judgest them that practise such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God? ^4Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness and forbearance and longsuffering, not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance? ^5but after thy hardness and impenitent heart treasurest up for thyself wrath in the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous judgment of God; ^6who will render to every man according to his works: ^7to them that by patience in well-doing seek for glory and honor and incorruption, eternal life: ^8but unto them that are factious, and obey not the truth, but obey unrighteousness, shall be wrath and indignation, ^9tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man that worketh evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Greek; ^10but glory and honor and peace to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek: ^11for there is no respect of persons with God. ^12For as many as have sinned without law shall also perish without the law: and as many as have sinned under the law shall be judged by the law; ^13for not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified: ^14(for when Gentiles that have not the law do by nature the things of the law, these, not having the law, are the law unto themselves; ^15in that they show the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience bearing witness therewith, and their thoughts one with another accusing or else excusing them); ^16in the day when God shall judge the secrets of men, according to my gospel, by Jesus Christ. ^17But if thou bearest the name of a Jew, and restest upon the law, and gloriest in God, ^18and knowest his will, and approvest the things that are excellent, being instructed out of the law, ^19and art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them that are in darkness, ^20a corrector of the foolish, a teacher of babes, having in the law the form of knowledge and of the truth; ^21thou therefore that teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal? ^22thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou rob temples? ^23thou who gloriest in the law, through thy transgression of the law dishonorest thou God? ^24For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you, even as it is written. ^25For circumcision indeed profiteth, if thou be a doer of the law: but if thou be a transgressor of the law, thy circumcision is become uncircumcision. ^26If therefore the uncircumcision keep the ordinances of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be reckoned for circumcision? ^27and shall not the uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfil the law, judge thee, who with the letter and circumcision art a transgressor of the law? ^28For he is not a Jew who is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision which is outward in the flesh: ^29but he is a Jew who is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit not in the letter; whose praise is not of men, but of God.

Romans 3

3

^1What advantage then hath the Jew? or what is the profit of circumcision? ^2Much every way: first of all, that they were intrusted with the oracles of God. ^3For what if some were without faith? shall their want of faith make of none effect the faithfulness of God? ^4God forbid: yea, let God be found true, but every man a liar; as it is written,

That thou mightest be justified in thy words,

And mightest prevail when thou comest into judgment.

^5But if our righteousness commendeth the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who visiteth with wrath? (I speak after the manner of men.) ^6God forbid: for then how shall God judge the world? ^7But if the truth of God through my lie abounded unto his glory, why am I also still judged as a sinner? ^8and why not (as we are slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say), Let us do evil, that good may come? whose condemnation is just. ^9What then? are we better than they? No, in no wise: for we before laid to the charge both of Jews and Greeks, that they are all under sin; ^10as it is written,

There is none righteous, no, not one;

^11There is none that understandeth,

There is none that seeketh after God;

^12They have all turned aside, they are together become unprofitable;

There is none that doeth good, no, not, so much as one:

^13Their throat is an open sepulchre;

With their tongues they have used deceit:

The poison of asps is under their lips:

^14Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness:

^15Their feet are swift to shed blood;

^16Destruction and misery are in their ways;

^17And the way of peace have they not known:

^18There is no fear of God before their eyes.

^19Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it speaketh to them that are under the law; that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may be brought under the judgment of God: ^20because by the works of the law shall no flesh be justified in his sight; for through the law cometh the knowledge of sin. ^21But now apart from the law a righteousness of God hath been manifested, being witnessed by the law and the prophets; ^22even the righteousness of God through faith in Jesus Christ unto all them that believe; for there is no distinction; ^23for all have sinned, and fall short of the glory of God; ^24being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus: ^25whom God set forth to be a propitiation, through faith, in his blood, to show his righteousness because of the passing over of the sins done aforetime, in the forbearance of God; ^26for the showing, I say, of his righteousness at this present season: that he might himself be just, and the justifier of him that hath faith in Jesus. ^27Where then is the glorying? It is excluded. By what manner of law? of works? Nay: but by a law of faith. ^28We reckon therefore that a man is justified by faith apart from the works of the law. ^29Or is God the God of Jews only? is he not the God of Gentiles also? Yea, of Gentiles also: ^30if so be that God is one, and he shall justify the circumcision by faith, and the uncircumcision through faith. ^31Do we then make the law of none effect through faith? God forbid: nay, we establish the law.

Romans 4

4

^1What then shall we say that Abraham, our forefather, hath found according to the flesh? ^2For if Abraham was justified by works, he hath whereof to glory; but not toward God. ^3For what saith the span? And Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness. ^4Now to him that worketh, the reward is not reckoned as of grace, but as of debt. ^5But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is reckoned for righteousness. ^6Even as David also pronounceth blessing upon the man, unto whom God reckoneth righteousness apart from works, ^7saying,

Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven,

And whose sins are covered.

^8Blessed is the man to whom, the Lord will not reckon sin.

^9Is this blessing then pronounced upon the circumcision, or upon the uncircumcision also? for we say, To Abraham his faith was reckoned for righteousness. ^10How then was it reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision: ^11and he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had while he was in uncircumcision; that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they be in uncircumcision, that righteousness might be reckoned unto them; ^12and the father of circumcision to them who not only are of the circumcision, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham which he had in uncircumcision. ^13For not through the law was the promise to Abraham or to his seed that he should be heir of the world, but through the righteousness of faith. ^14For if they that are of the law are heirs, faith is made void, and the promise is made of none effect: ^15for the law worketh wrath; but where there is no law, neither is there transgression. ^16For this cause it is of faith, that it may be according to grace; to the end that the promise may be sure to all the seed; not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all ^17(as it is written, A father of many nations have I made thee) before him whom he believed, even God, who giveth life to the dead, and calleth the things that are not, as though they were. ^18Who in hope believed against hope, to the end that he might become a father of many nations, according to that which had been spoken, So shall thy seed be. ^19And without being weakened in faith he considered his own body now as good as dead (he being about a hundred years old), and the deadness of Sarah's womb; ^20yet, looking unto the promise of God, he wavered not through unbelief, but waxed strong through faith, giving glory to God, ^21and being fully assured that what he had promised, he was able also to perform. ^22Wherefore also it was reckoned unto him for righteousness. ^23Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was reckoned unto him; ^24but for our sake also, unto whom it shall be reckoned, who believe on him that raised Jesus our Lord from the dead, ^25who was delivered up for our trespasses, and was raised for our justification.

Romans 5

5

^1Being therefore justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ; ^2through whom also we have had our access by faith into this grace wherein we stand; and we rejoice in hope of the glory of God. ^3And not only so, but we also rejoice in our tribulations: knowing that tribulation worketh stedfastness; ^4and stedfastness, approvedness; and approvedness, hope: ^5and hope putteth not to shame; because the love of God hath been shed abroad in our hearts through the Holy Spirit which was given unto us. ^6For while we were yet weak, in due season Christ died for the ungodly. ^7For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: for peradventure for the good man some one would even dare to die. ^8But God commendeth his own love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us. ^9Much more then, being now justified by his blood, shall we be saved from the wrath of God through him. ^10For if, while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, shall we be saved by his life; ^11and not only so, but we also rejoice in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received the reconciliation. ^12Therefore, as through one man sin entered into the world, and death through sin; and so death passed unto all men, for that all sinned:-- ^13for until the law sin was in the world; but sin is not imputed when there is no law. ^14Nevertheless death reigned from Adam until Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the likeness of Adam's transgression, who is a figure of him that was to come. ^15But not as the trespass, so also is the free gift. For if by the trespass of the one the many died, much more did the grace of God, and the gift by the grace of the one man, Jesus Christ, abound unto the many. ^16And not as through one that sinned, so is the gift: for the judgment came of one unto condemnation, but the free gift came of many trespasses unto justification. ^17For if, by the trespass of the one, death reigned through the one; much more shall they that receive the abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness reign in life through the one, even Jesus Christ. ^18So then as through one trespass the judgment came unto all men to condemnation; even so through one act of righteousness the free gift came unto all men to justification of life. ^19For as through the one man's disobedience the many were made sinners, even so through the obedience of the one shall the many be made righteous. ^20And the law came in besides, that the trespass might abound; but where sin abounded, grace did abound more exceedingly: ^21that, as sin reigned in death, even so might grace reign through righteousness unto eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.

Romans 6

6

^1What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound? ^2God forbid. We who died to sin, how shall we any longer live therein? ^3Or are ye ignorant that all we who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death? ^4We were buried therefore with him through baptism unto death: that like as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so we also might walk in newness of life. ^5For if we have become united with him in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection; ^6knowing this, that our old man was crucified with him, that the body of sin might be done away, that so we should no longer be in bondage to sin; ^7for he that hath died is justified from sin. ^8But if we died with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him; ^9knowing that Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; death no more hath dominion over him. ^10For the death that he died, he died unto sin once: but the life that he liveth, he liveth unto God. ^11Even so reckon ye also yourselves to be dead unto sin, but alive unto God in Christ Jesus. ^12Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey the lusts thereof: ^13neither present your members unto sin as instruments of unrighteousness; but present yourselves unto God, as alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God. ^14For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under law, but under grace. ^15What then? shall we sin, because we are not under law, but under grace? God forbid. ^16Know ye not, that to whom ye present yourselves as servants unto obedience, his servants ye are whom ye obey; whether of sin unto death, or of obedience unto righteousness? ^17But thanks be to God, that, whereas ye were servants of sin, ye became obedient from the heart to that form of teaching whereunto ye were delivered; ^18and being made free from sin, ye became servants of righteousness. ^19I speak after the manner of men because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye presented your members as servants to uncleanness and to iniquity unto iniquity, even so now present your members as servants to righteousness unto sanctification. ^20For when ye were servants of sin, ye were free in regard of righteousness. ^21What fruit then had ye at that time in the things whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death. ^22But now being made free from sin and become servants to God, ye have your fruit unto sanctification, and the end eternal life. ^23For the wages of sin is death; but the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 7

7

^1Or are ye ignorant, brethren (for I speak to men who know the law), that the law hath dominion over a man for so long time as he liveth? ^2For the woman that hath a husband is bound by law to the husband while he liveth; but if the husband die, she is discharged from the law of the husband. ^3So then if, while the husband liveth, she be joined to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if the husband die, she is free from the law, so that she is no adulteress, though she be joined to another man. ^4Wherefore, my brethren, ye also were made dead to the law through the body of Christ; that ye should be joined to another, even to him who was raised from the dead, that we might bring forth fruit unto God. ^5For when we were in the flesh, the sinful passions, which were through the law, wrought in our members to bring forth fruit unto death. ^6But now we have been discharged from the law, having died to that wherein we were held; so that we serve in newness of the spirit, and not in oldness of the letter. ^7What shall we say then? Is the law sin? God forbid. Howbeit, I had not known sin, except through the law: for I had not known coveting, except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet: ^8but sin, finding occasion, wrought in me through the commandment all manner of coveting: for apart from the law sin is dead. ^9And I was alive apart from the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died; ^10and the commandment, which was unto life, this I found to be unto death: ^11for sin, finding occasion, through the commandment beguiled me, and through it slew me. ^12So that the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and righteous, and good. ^13Did then that which is good become death unto me? God forbid. But sin, that it might be shown to be sin, by working death to me through that which is good; --that through the commandment sin might become exceeding sinful. ^14For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin. ^15For that which I do I know not: for not what I would, that do I practise; but what I hate, that I do. ^16But if what I would not, that I do, I consent unto the law that it is good. ^17So now it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwelleth in me. ^18For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me, but to do that which is good is not. ^19For the good which I would I do not: but the evil which I would not, that I practise. ^20But if what I would not, that I do, it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwelleth in me. ^21I find then the law, that, to me who would do good, evil is present. ^22For I delight in the law of God after the inward man: ^23but I see a different law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity under the law of sin which is in my members. ^24Wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me out of the body of this death? ^25I thank God through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then I of myself with the mind, indeed, serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin.

Romans 8

8

^1There is therefore now no condemnation to them that are in Christ Jesus. ^2For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus made me free from the law of sin and of death. ^3For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God, sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh and for sin, condemned sin in the flesh: ^4that the ordinance of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit. ^5For they that are after the flesh mind the things of the flesh; but they that are after the Spirit the things of the Spirit. ^6For the mind of the flesh is death; but the mind of the Spirit is life and peace: ^7because the mind of the flesh is enmity against God; for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can it be: ^8and they that are in the flesh cannot please God. ^9But ye are not in the flesh but in the Spirit, if so be that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you. But if any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his. ^10And if Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the spirit is life because of righteousness. ^11But if the Spirit of him that raised up Jesus from the dead dwelleth in you, he that raised up Christ Jesus from the dead shall give life also to your mortal bodies through his Spirit that dwelleth in you. ^12So then, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh: ^13for if ye live after the flesh, ye must die; but if by the Spirit ye put to death the deeds of the body, ye shall live. ^14For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are sons of God. ^15For ye received not the spirit of bondage again unto fear; but ye received the spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father. ^16The Spirit himself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are children of God: ^17and if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if so be that we suffer with him, that we may be also glorified with him. ^18For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed to us-ward. ^19For the earnest expectation of the creation waiteth for the revealing of the sons of God. ^20For the creation was subjected to vanity, not of its own will, but by reason of him who subjected it, in hope ^21that the creation itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the liberty of the glory of the children of God. ^22For we know that the whole creation groaneth and travaileth in pain together until now. ^23And not only so, but ourselves also, who have the first-fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for our adoption, to wit, the redemption of our body. ^24For in hope were we saved: but hope that is seen is not hope: for who hopeth for that which he seeth? ^25But if we hope for that which we see not, then do we with patience wait for it. ^26And in like manner the Spirit also helpeth our infirmity: for we know not how to pray as we ought; but the Spirit himself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered; ^27and he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, because he maketh intercession for the saints according to the will of God. ^28And we know that to them that love God all things work together for good, even to them that are called according to his purpose. ^29For whom he foreknew, he also foreordained to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brethren: ^30and whom he foreordained, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified. ^31What then shall we say to these things? If God is for us, who is against us? ^32He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not also with him freely give us all things? ^33Who shall lay anything to the charge of God's elect? It is God that justifieth; ^34who is he that condemneth? It is Christ Jesus that died, yea rather, that was raised from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us. ^35Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? shall tribulation, or anguish, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword? ^36Even as it is written, For thy sake we are killed all the day long; We were accounted as sheep for the slaughter. ^37Nay, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him that loved us. ^38For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, ^39nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 9

9

^1I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience bearing witness with me in the Holy Spirit, ^2that I have great sorrow and unceasing pain in my heart. ^3For I could wish that I myself were anathema from Christ for my brethren's sake, my kinsmen according to the flesh: ^4who are Israelites; whose is the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service of God, and the promises; ^5whose are the fathers, and of whom is Christ as concerning the flesh, who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen. ^6But it is not as though the word of God hath come to nought. For they are not all Israel, that are of Israel: ^7neither, because they are Abraham's seed, are they all children: but, In Isaac shall thy seed be called. ^8That is, it is not the children of the flesh that are children of God; but the children of the promise are reckoned for a seed. ^9For this is a word of promise, According to this season will I come, and Sarah shall have a son. ^10And not only so; but Rebecca also having conceived by one, even by our father Isaac-- ^11for the children being not yet born, neither having done anything good or bad, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth, ^12it was said unto her, The elder shall serve the younger. ^13Even as it is written, Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated. ^14What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? God forbid. ^15For he saith to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion. ^16So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that hath mercy. ^17For the span saith unto Pharaoh, For this very purpose did I raise thee up, that I might show in thee my power, and that my name might be published abroad in all the earth. ^18So then he hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will be hardeneth. ^19Thou wilt say then unto me, Why doth he still find fault? For who withstandeth his will? ^20Nay but, O man, who art thou that repliest against God? Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it, Why didst thou make me thus? ^21Or hath not the potter a right over the clay, from the same lump to make one part a vessel unto honor, and another unto dishonor? ^22What if God, willing to show his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much longsuffering vessels of wrath fitted unto destruction: ^23and that he might make known the riches of his glory upon vessels of mercy, which he afore prepared unto glory, ^24even us, whom he also called, not from the Jews only, but also from the Gentiles? ^25As he saith also in Hosea,

I will call that my people, which was not my people;

And her beloved, that was not beloved.

^26And it shall be, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people,

There shall they be called sons of the living God.

^27And Isaiah crieth concerning Israel, If the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, it is the remnant that shall be saved: ^28for the Lord will execute his word upon the earth, finishing it and cutting it short. ^29And, as Isaiah hath said before,

Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed,

We had become as Sodom, and had been made like unto Gomorrah.

^30What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, who followed not after righteousness, attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith: ^31but Israel, following after a law of righteousness, did not arrive at that law. ^32Wherefore? Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by works. They stumbled at the stone of stumbling; ^33even as it is written,

Behold, I lay in Zion a stone of stumbling and a rock of offence:

And he that believeth on him shall not be put to shame.

Romans 10

10

^1Brethren, my heart's desire and my supplication to God is for them, that they may be saved. ^2For I bear them witness that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge. ^3For being ignorant of God's righteousness, and seeking to establish their own, they did not subject themselves to the righteousness of God. ^4For Christ is the end of the law unto righteousness to every one that believeth. ^5For Moses writeth that the man that doeth the righteousness which is of the law shall live thereby. ^6But the righteousness which is of faith saith thus, Say not in thy heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down:) ^7or, Who shall descend into the abyss? (That is, to bring Christ up from the dead.) ^8But what saith it? The word is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach: ^9because if thou shalt confess with thy mouth Jesus as Lord, and shalt believe in thy heart that God raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved: ^10for with the heart man believeth unto righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation. ^11For the span saith, Whosoever believeth on him shall not be put to shame. ^12For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek: for the same Lord is Lord of all, and is rich unto all that call upon him: ^13for, Whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. ^14How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher? ^15and how shall they preach, except they be sent? even as it is written, How beautiful are the feet of them that bring glad tidings of good things! ^16But they did not all hearken to the glad tidings. For Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report? ^17So belief cometh of hearing, and hearing by the word of Christ. ^18But I say, Did they not hear? Yea, verily,

Their sound went out into all the earth,

And their words unto the ends of the world.

^19But I say, Did Israel not know? First Moses saith,

I will provoke you to jealousy with that which is no nation,

With a nation void of understanding will I anger you.

^20And Isaiah is very bold, and saith,

I was found of them that sought me not;

I became manifest unto them that asked not of me.

^21But as to Israel he saith, All the day long did I spread out my hands unto a disobedient and gainsaying people.

Romans 11

11

^1I say then, Did God cast off his people? God forbid. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. ^2God did not cast off his people which he foreknew. Or know ye not what the span saith of Elijah? how he pleadeth with God against Israel: ^3Lord, they have killed thy prophets, they have digged down thine altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life. ^4But what saith the answer of God unto him? I have left for myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to Baal. ^5Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace. ^6But if it is by grace, it is no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace. ^7What then? that which Israel seeketh for, that he obtained not; but the election obtained it, and the rest were hardened: ^8according as it is written, God gave them a spirit of stupor, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear, unto this very day. ^9And David saith,

Let their table be made a snare, and a trap,

And a stumblingblock, and a recompense unto them:

^10Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see,

And bow thou down their back always.

^11I say then, Did they stumble that they might fall? God forbid: but by their fall salvation is come unto the Gentiles, to provoke them to jealousy. ^12Now if their fall, is the riches of the world, and their loss the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fulness? ^13But I speak to you that are Gentiles. Inasmuch then as I am an apostle of Gentiles, I glorify my ministry; ^14if by any means I may provoke to jealousy them that are my flesh, and may save some of them. ^15For if the casting away of them is the reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be, but life from the dead? ^16And if the firstfruit is holy, so is the lump: and if the root is holy, so are the branches. ^17But if some of the branches were broken off, and thou, being a wild olive, wast grafted in among them, and didst become partaker with them of the root of the fatness of the olive tree; ^18glory not over the branches: but if thou gloriest, it is not thou that bearest the root, but the root thee. ^19Thou wilt say then, Branches were broken off, that I might be grafted in. ^20Well; by their unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by thy faith. Be not highminded, but fear: ^21for if God spared not the natural branches, neither will he spare thee. ^22Behold then the goodness and severity of God: toward them that fell, severity; but toward thee, God's goodness, if thou continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off. ^23And they also, if they continue not in their unbelief, shall be grafted in: for God is able to graft them in again. ^24For if thou wast cut out of that which is by nature a wild olive tree, and wast grafted contrary to nature into a good olive tree; how much more shall these, which are the natural branches, be grafted into their own olive tree? ^25For I would not, brethren, have you ignorant of this mystery, lest ye be wise in your own conceits, that a hardening in part hath befallen Israel, until the fulness of the Gentiles be come in; ^26and so all Israel shall be saved: even as it is written,

There shall come out of Zion the Deliverer;

He shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob:

^27And this is my covenant unto them,

When I shall take away their sins.

^28As touching the gospel, they are enemies for your sake: but as touching the election, they are beloved for the fathers' sake. ^29For the gifts and the calling of God are not repented of. ^30For as ye in time past were disobedient to God, but now have obtained mercy by their disobedience, ^31even so have these also now been disobedient, that by the mercy shown to you they also may now obtain mercy. ^32For God hath shut up all unto disobedience, that he might have mercy upon all. ^33O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and the knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past tracing out! ^34For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counsellor? ^35or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed unto him again? ^36For of him, and through him, and unto him, are all things. To him be the glory for ever. Amen.

Romans 12

12

^1I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your spiritual service. ^2And be not fashioned according to this world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, and ye may prove what is the good and acceptable and perfect will of God. ^3For I say, through the grace that was given me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but to think as to think soberly, according as God hath dealt to each man a measure of faith. ^4For even as we have many members in one body, and all the members have not the same office: ^5so we, who are many, are one body in Christ, and severally members one of another. ^6And having gifts differing according to the grace that was given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of our faith; ^7or ministry, let us give ourselves to our ministry; or he that teacheth, to his teaching; ^8or he that exhorteth, to his exhorting: he that giveth, let him do it with liberality; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that showeth mercy, with cheerfulness. ^9Let love be without hypocrisy. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good. ^10In love of the brethren be tenderly affectioned one to another; in honor preferring one another; ^11in diligence not slothful; fervent in spirit; serving the Lord; ^12rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing stedfastly in prayer; ^13communicating to the necessities of the saints; given to hospitality. ^14Bless them that persecute you; bless, and curse not. ^15Rejoice with them that rejoice; weep with them that weep. ^16Be of the same mind one toward another. Set not your mind on high things, but condescend to things that are lowly. Be not wise in your own conceits. ^17Render to no man evil for evil. Take thought for things honorable in the sight of all men. ^18If it be possible, as much as in you lieth, be at peace with all men. ^19Avenge not yourselves, beloved, but give place unto the wrath of God: for it is written, Vengeance belongeth unto me; I will recompense, saith the Lord. ^20But if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst, give him to drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head. ^21Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.

Romans 13

13

^1Let every soul be in subjection to the higher powers: for there is no power but of God; and the powers that be are ordained of God. ^2Therefore he that resisteth the power, withstandeth the ordinance of God: and they that withstand shall receive to themselves judgment. ^3For rulers are not a terror to the good work, but to the evil. And wouldest thou have no fear of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise from the same: ^4for he is a minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is a minister of God, an avenger for wrath to him that doeth evil. ^5Wherefore ye must needs be in subjection, not only because of the wrath, but also for conscience' sake. ^6For this cause ye pay tribute also; for they are ministers of God's service, attending continually upon this very thing. ^7Render to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honor to whom honor. ^8Owe no man anything, save to love one another: for he that loveth his neighbor hath fulfilled the law. ^9For this, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not covet, and if there be any other commandment, it is summed up in this word, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. ^10Love worketh no ill to his neighbor: love therefore is the fulfilment of the law. ^11And this, knowing the season, that already it is time for you to awake out of sleep: for now is salvation nearer to us than when we first believed. ^12The night is far spent, and the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armor of light. ^13Let us walk becomingly, as in the day; not in revelling and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and jealousy. ^14But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts thereof.

Romans 14

14

^1But him that is weak in faith receive ye, yet not for decision of scruples. ^2One man hath faith to eat all things: but he that is weak eateth herbs. ^3Let not him that eateth set at nought him that eateth not; and let not him that eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him. ^4Who art thou that judgest the servant of another? to his own lord he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be made to stand; for the Lord hath power to make him stand. ^5One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day alike. Let each man be fully assured in his own mind. ^6He that regardeth the day, regardeth it unto the Lord: and he that eateth, eateth unto the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, unto the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks. ^7For none of us liveth to himself, and none dieth to himself. ^8For whether we live, we live unto the Lord; or whether we die, we die unto the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord's. ^9For to this end Christ died and lived again, that he might be Lord of both the dead and the living. ^10But thou, why dost thou judge thy brother? or thou again, why dost thou set at nought thy brother? for we shall all stand before the judgment-seat of God. ^11For it is written,

As I live, saith the Lord, to me every knee shall bow,

And every tongue shall confess to God.

^12So then each one of us shall give account of himself to God. ^13Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge ye this rather, that no man put a stumblingblock in his brother's way, or an occasion of falling. ^14I know, and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus, that nothing is unclean of itself: save that to him who accounteth anything to be unclean, to him it is unclean. ^15For if because of meat thy brother is grieved, thou walkest no longer in love. Destroy not with thy meat him for whom Christ died. ^16Let not then your good be evil spoken of: ^17for the kingdom of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness and peace and joy in the Holy Spirit. ^18For he that herein serveth Christ is well-pleasing to God, and approved of men. ^19So then let us follow after things which make for peace, and things whereby we may edify one another. ^20Overthrow not for meat's sake the work of God. All things indeed are clean; howbeit it is evil for that man who eateth with offence. ^21It is good not to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor to do anything whereby thy brother stumbleth. ^22The faith which thou hast, have thou to thyself before God. Happy is he that judgeth not himself in that which he approveth. ^23But he that doubteth is condemned if he eat, because he eateth not of faith; and whatsoever is not of faith is sin.

Romans 15

15

^1Now we that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves. ^2Let each one of us please his neighbor for that which is good, unto edifying. ^3For Christ also pleased not himself; but, as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell upon me. ^4For whatsoever things were written aforetime were written for our learning, that through patience and through comfort of the spans we might have hope. ^5Now the God of patience and of comfort grant you to be of the same mind one with another according to Christ Jesus: ^6that with one accord ye may with one mouth glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. ^7Wherefore receive ye one another, even as Christ also received you, to the glory of God. ^8For I say that Christ hath been made a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, that he might confirm the promises given unto the fathers, ^9and that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written,

Therefore will I give praise unto thee among the Gentiles,

And sing unto thy name.

^10And again he saith,

Rejoice, ye Gentiles, with his people.

^11And again,

Praise the Lord, all ye Gentiles;

And let all the peoples praise him.

^12And again, Isaiah saith,

There shall be the root of Jesse,

And he that ariseth to rule over the Gentiles;

On him shall the Gentiles hope.

^13Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, in the power of the Holy Spirit. ^14And I myself also am persuaded of you, my brethren, that ye yourselves are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another. ^15But I write the more boldly unto you in some measure, as putting you again in remembrance, because of the grace that was given me of God, ^16that I should be a minister of Christ Jesus unto the Gentiles, ministering the gospel of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be made acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Spirit. ^17I have therefore my glorifying in Christ Jesus in things pertaining to God. ^18For I will not dare to speak of any things save those which Christ wrought through me, for the obedience of the Gentiles, by word and deed, ^19in the power of signs and wonders, in the power of the Holy Spirit; so that from Jerusalem, and round about even unto Illyricum, I have fully preached the gospel of Christ; ^20yea, making it my aim so to preach the gospel, not where Christ was already named, that I might not build upon another man's foundation; ^21but, as it is written,

They shall see, to whom no tidings of him came,

And they who have not heard shall understand.

^22Wherefore also I was hindered these many times from coming to you: ^23but now, having no more any place in these regions, and having these many years a longing to come unto you, ^24whensoever I go unto Spain (for I hope to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first in some measure I shall have been satisfied with your company)-- ^25but now, I say, I go unto Jerusalem, ministering unto the saints. ^26For it hath been the good pleasure of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor among the saints that are at Jerusalem. ^27Yea, it hath been their good pleasure; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, they owe it to them also to minister unto them in carnal things. ^28When therefore I have accomplished this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will go on by you unto Spain. ^29And I know that, when I come unto you, I shall come in the fulness of the blessing of Christ. ^30Now I beseech you, brethren, by our Lord Jesus Christ, and by the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me; ^31that I may be delivered from them that are disobedient in Judaea, and that my ministration which I have for Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints; ^32that I may come unto you in joy through the will of God, and together with you find rest. ^33Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

Romans 16

16

^1I commend unto you Phoebe our sister, who is a servant of the church that is at Cenchreae: ^2that ye receive her in the Lord, worthily of the saints, and that ye assist her in whatsoever matter she may have need of you: for she herself also hath been a helper of many, and of mine own self. ^3Salute Prisca and Aquila my fellow-workers in Christ Jesus, ^4who for my life laid down their own necks; unto whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles: ^5and salute the church that is in their house. Salute Epaenetus my beloved, who is the first-fruits of Asia unto Christ. ^6Salute Mary, who bestowed much labor on you. ^7Salute Andronicus and Junias, my kinsmen, and my fellow-prisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also have been in Christ before me. ^8Salute Ampliatus my beloved in the Lord. ^9Salute Urbanus our fellow-worker in Christ, and Stachys my beloved. ^10Salute Apelles the approved in Christ. Salute them that are of the household of Aristobulus. ^11Salute Herodion my kinsman. Salute them of the household of Narcissus, that are in the Lord. ^12Salute Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Salute Persis the beloved, who labored much in the Lord. ^13Salute Rufus the chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine. ^14Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brethren that are with them. ^15Salute Philologus and Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints that are with them. ^16Salute one another with a holy kiss. All the churches of Christ salute you. ^17Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them that are causing the divisions and occasions of stumbling, contrary to the doctrine which ye learned: and turn away from them. ^18For they that are such serve not our Lord Christ, but their own belly; and by their smooth and fair speech they beguile the hearts of the innocent. ^19For your obedience is come abroad unto all men. I rejoice therefore over you: but I would have you wise unto that which is good, and simple unto that which is evil. ^20And the God of peace shall bruise Satan under your feet shortly. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. ^21Timothy my fellow-worker saluteth you; and Lucius and Jason and Sosipater, my kinsmen. ^22I Tertius, who write the epistle, salute you in the Lord. ^23Gaius my host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the treasurer of the city saluteth you, and Quartus the brother. ^24The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen. ^25Now to him that is able to establish you according to my gospel and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery which hath been kept in silence through times eternal, ^26but now is manifested, and by the spans of the prophets, according to the commandment of the eternal God, is made known unto all the nations unto obedience of faith: ^27to the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to whom be the glory for ever. Amen.

Ruth 2

2

^1And Naomi had a kinsman of her husband's, a mighty man of wealth, of the family of Elimelech, and his name was Boaz. ^2And Ruth the Moabitess said unto Naomi, Let me now go to the field, and glean among the ears of grain after him in whose sight I shall find favor. And she said unto her, Go, my daughter. ^3And she went, and came and gleaned in the field after the reapers: and her hap was to light on the portion of the field belonging unto Boaz, who was of the family of Elimelech. ^4And, behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem, and said unto the reapers, Jehovah be with you. And they answered him, Jehovah bless thee. ^5Then said Boaz unto his servant that was set over the reapers, Whose damsel is this? ^6And the servant that was set over the reapers answered and said, It is the Moabitish damsel that came back with Naomi out of the country of Moab: ^7And she said, Let me glean, I pray you, and gather after the reapers among the sheaves. So she came, and hath continued even from the morning until now, save that she tarried a little in the house.

^8Then said Boaz unto Ruth, Hearest thou not, my daughter? Go not to glean in another field, neither pass from hence, but abide here fast by my maidens. ^9Let thine eyes be on the field that they do reap, and go thou after them: have I not charged the young men that they shall not touch thee? and when thou art athirst, go unto the vessels, and drink of that which the young men have drawn. ^10Then she fell on her face, and bowed herself to the ground, and said unto him, Why have I found favor in thy sight, that thou shouldest take knowledge of me, seeing I am a foreigner? ^11And Boaz answered and said unto her, It hath fully been showed me, all that thou hast done unto thy mother-in-law since the death of thy husband; and how thou hast left thy father and thy mother, and the land of thy nativity, and art come unto a people that thou knewest not heretofore. ^12Jehovah recompense thy work, and a full reward be given thee of Jehovah, the God of Israel, under whose wings thou art come to take refuge. ^13Then she said, Let me find favor in thy sight, my lord, for that thou hast comforted me, and for that thou hast spoken kindly unto thy handmaid, though I be not as one of thy handmaidens.

^14And at meal-time Boaz said unto her, Come hither, and eat of the bread, and dip thy morsel in the vinegar. And she sat beside the reapers, and they reached her parched grain, and she did eat, and was sufficed, and left thereof. ^15And when she was risen up to glean, Boaz commanded his young men, saying, Let her glean even among the sheaves, and reproach her not. ^16And also pull out some for her from the bundles, and leave it, and let her glean, and rebuke her not.

^17So she gleaned in the field until even; and she beat out that which she had gleaned, and it was about an ephah of barley. ^18And she took it up, and went into the city; and her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned: and she brought forth and gave to her that which she had left after she was sufficed. ^19And her mother-in-law said unto her, Where hast thou gleaned to-day? and where hast thou wrought? blessed be he that did take knowledge of thee. And she showed her mother-in-law with whom she had wrought, and said, The man's name with whom I wrought to-day is Boaz. ^20And Naomi said unto her daughter-in-law, Blessed be he of Jehovah, who hath not left off his kindness to the living and to the dead. And Naomi said unto her, The man is nigh of kin unto us, one of our near kinsmen. ^21And Ruth the Moabitess said, Yea, he said unto me, Thou shalt keep fast by my young men, until they have ended all my harvest. ^22And Naomi said unto Ruth her daughter-in-law, It is good, my daughter, that thou go out with his maidens, and that they meet thee not in any other field. ^23So she kept fast by the maidens of Boaz, to glean unto the end of barley harvest and of wheat harvest; and she dwelt with her mother-in-law.

Ruth 3

3

^1And Naomi her mother-in-law said unto her, My daughter, shall I not seek rest for thee, that it may be well with thee? ^2And now is not Boaz our kinsman, with whose maidens thou wast? Behold, he winnoweth barley to-night in the threshing-floor. ^3Wash thyself therefore, and anoint thee, and put thy raiment upon thee, and get thee down to the threshing-floor, but make not thyself known unto the man, until he shall have done eating and drinking. ^4And it shall be, when he lieth down, that thou shalt mark the place where he shall lie, and thou shalt go in, and uncover his feet, and lay thee down; and he will tell thee what thou shalt do. ^5And she said unto her, All that thou sayest I will do.

^6And she went down unto the threshing-floor, and did according to all that her mother-in-law bade her. ^7And when Boaz had eaten and drunk, and his heart was merry, he went to lie down at the end of the heap of grain: and she came softly, and uncovered his feet, and laid her down. ^8And it came to pass at midnight, that the man was afraid, and turned himself; and, behold, a woman lay at his feet. ^9And he said, Who art thou? And she answered, I am Ruth thy handmaid: spread therefore thy skirt over thy handmaid; for thou art a near kinsman. ^10And he said, Blessed be thou of Jehovah, my daughter: thou hast showed more kindness in the latter end than at the beginning, inasmuch as thou followedst not young men, whether poor or rich. ^11And now, my daughter, fear not; I will do to thee all that thou sayest; for all the city of my people doth know that thou art a worthy woman. ^12And now it is true that I am a near kinsman; howbeit there is a kinsman nearer than I. ^13Tarry this night, and it shall be in the morning, that if he will perform unto thee the part of a kinsman, well; let him do the kinsman's part: but if he will not do the part of a kinsman to thee, then will I do the part of a kinsman to thee, as Jehovah liveth: lie down until the morning.

^14And she lay at his feet until the morning. And she rose up before one could discern another. For he said, Let it not be known that the woman came to the threshing-floor. ^15And he said, Bring the mantle that is upon thee, and hold it; and she held it; and he measured six measures of barley, and laid it on her: and he went into the city. ^16And when she came to her mother-in-law, she said, Who art thou, my daughter? And she told her all that the man had done to her. ^17And she said, These six measures of barley gave he me; for he said, Go not empty unto thy mother-in-law. ^18Then said she, Sit still, my daughter, until thou know how the matter will fall; for the man will not rest, until he have finished the thing this day.

Ruth 4

4

^1Now Boaz went up to the gate, and sat him down there: and, behold, the near kinsman of whom Boaz spake came by; unto whom he said, Ho, such a one! turn aside, sit down here. And he turned aside, and sat down. ^2And he took ten men of the elders of the city, and said, Sit ye down here. And they sat down. ^3And he said unto the near kinsman, Naomi, that is come again out of the country of Moab, selleth the parcel of land, which was our brother Elimelech's: ^4And I thought to disclose it unto thee, saying, Buy it before them that sit here, and before the elders of my people. If thou wilt redeem it, redeem it: but if thou wilt not redeem it, then tell me, that I may know; for there is none to redeem it besides thee; and I am after thee. And he said, I will redeem it. ^5Then said Boaz, What day thou buyest the field of the hand of Naomi, thou must buy it also of Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of the dead, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance. ^6And the near kinsman said, I cannot redeem it for myself, lest I mar mine own inheritance: take thou my right of redemption on thee; for I cannot redeem it.

^7Now this was the custom in former time in Israel concerning redeeming and concerning exchanging, to confirm all things: a man drew off his shoe, and gave it to his neighbor; and this was the manner of attestation in Israel. ^8So the near kinsman said unto Boaz, Buy it for thyself. And he drew off his shoe. ^9And Boaz said unto the elders, and unto all the people, Ye are witnesses this day, that I have bought all that was Elimelech's, and all that was Chilion's and Mahlon's, of the hand of Naomi. ^10Moreover Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of Mahlon, have I purchased to be my wife, to raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance, that the name of the dead be not cut off from among his brethren, and from the gate of his place: ye are witnesses this day. ^11And all the people that were in the gate, and the elders, said, We are witnesses. Jehovah make the woman that is come into thy house like Rachel and like Leah, which two did build the house of Israel: and do thou worthily in Ephrathah, and be famous in Bethlehem: ^12and let thy house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bare unto Judah, of the seed which Jehovah shall give thee of this young woman.

^13So Boaz took Ruth, and she became his wife; and he went in unto her, and Jehovah gave her conception, and she bare a son. ^14And the women said unto Naomi, Blessed be Jehovah, who hath not left thee this day without a near kinsman; and let his name be famous in Israel. ^15And he shall be unto thee a restorer of life, and a nourisher of thine old age, for thy daughter-in-law, who loveth thee, who is better to thee than seven sons, hath borne him. ^16And Naomi took the child, and laid it in her bosom, and became nurse unto it. ^17And the women her neighbors gave it a name, saying, There is a son born to Naomi; and they called his name Obed: he is the father of Jesse, the father of David.

^18Now these are the generations of Perez: Perez begat Hezron, ^19and Hezron begat Ram, and Ram begat Amminadab, ^20and Amminadab begat Nahshon, and Nahshon begat Salmon, ^21and Salmon begat Boaz, and Boaz begat Obed, ^22and Obed begat Jesse, and Jesse begat David.

Titus 3

3

^1Put them in mind to be in subjection to rulers, to authorities, to be obedient, to be ready unto every good work, ^2to speak evil of no man, not to be contentious, to be gentle, showing all meekness toward all men. ^3For we also once were foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving divers lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, hating one another. ^4But when the kindness of God our Saviour, and his love toward man, appeared, ^5not by works done in righteousness, which we did ourselves, but according to his mercy he saved us, through the washing of regeneration and renewing of the Holy Spirit, ^6which he poured out upon us richly, through Jesus Christ our Saviour; ^7that, being justified by his grace, we might be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life. ^8Faithful is the saying, and concerning these things I desire that thou affirm confidently, to the end that they who have believed God may be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable unto men: ^9but shun foolish questionings, and genealogies, and strifes, and fightings about law; for they are unprofitable and vain. ^10A factious man after a first and second admonition refuse; ^11knowing that such a one is perverted, and sinneth, being self-condemned. ^12When I shall send Artemas unto thee, or Tychicus, give diligence to come unto me to Nicopolis: for there I have determined to winter. ^13Set forward Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey diligently, that nothing be wanting unto them. ^14And let our people also learn to maintain good works for necessary uses, that they be not unfruitful. ^15All that are with me salute thee. Salute them that love us in faith. Grace be with you all.

Zechariah 2

2

^1And I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, a man with a measuring line in his hand. ^2Then said I, Whither goest thou? And he said unto me, To measure Jerusalem, to see what is the breadth thereof, and what is the length thereof. ^3And, behold, the angel that talked with me went forth, and another angel went out to meet him, ^4and said unto him, Run, speak to this young man, saying, Jerusalem shall be inhabited as villages without walls, by reason of the multitude of men and cattle therein. ^5For I, saith Jehovah, will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and I will be the glory in the midst of her. ^6Ho, ho, flee from the land of the north, saith Jehovah; for I have spread you abroad as the four winds of the heavens, saith Jehovah. ^7Ho Zion, escape, thou that dwellest with the daughter of Babylon. ^8For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: After glory hath he sent me unto the nations which plundered you; for he that toucheth you toucheth the apple of his eye. ^9For, behold, I will shake my hand over them, and they shall be a spoil to those that served them; and ye shall know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me. ^10Sing and rejoice, O daughter of Zion; for, lo, I come, and I will dwell in the midst of thee, saith Jehovah. ^11And many nations shall join themselves to Jehovah in that day, and shall be my people; and I will dwell in the midst of thee, and thou shalt know that Jehovah of hosts has sent me unto thee. ^12And Jehovah shall inherit Judah as his portion in the holy land, and shall yet choose Jerusalem. ^13Be silent, all flesh, before Jehovah; for he is waked up out of his holy habitation.

Zechariah 3

3

^1And he showed me Joshua the high priest standing before the angel of Jehovah, and Satan standing at his right hand to be his adversary. ^2And Jehovah said unto Satan, Jehovah rebuke thee, O Satan; yea, Jehovah that hath chosen Jerusalem rebuke thee: is not this a brand plucked out of the fire? ^3Now Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and was standing before the angel. ^4And he answered and spake unto those that stood before him, saying, Take the filthy garments from off him. And unto him he said, Behold, I have caused thine iniquity to pass from thee, and I will clothe thee with rich apparel. ^5And I said, Let them set a clean mitre upon his head. So they set a clean mitre upon his head, and clothed him with garments; and the angel of Jehovah was standing by. ^6And the angel of Jehovah protested unto Joshua, saying, ^7Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: If thou wilt walk in my ways, and if thou wilt keep my charge, then thou also shalt judge my house, and shalt also keep my courts, and I will give thee a place of access among these that stand by. ^8Hear now, O Joshua the high priest, thou and thy fellows that sit before thee; for they are men that are a sign: for, behold, I will bring forth my servant the Branch. ^9For, behold, the stone that I have set before Joshua; upon one stone are seven eyes: behold, I will engrave the graving thereof, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day. ^10In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, shall ye invite every man his neighbor under the vine and under the fig-tree.

Zechariah 4

4

^1And the angel that talked with me came again, and waked me, as a man that is wakened out of his sleep. ^2And he said unto me, What seest thou? And I said, I have seen, and, behold, a candlestick all of gold, with its bowl upon the top of it, and its seven lamps thereon; there are seven pipes to each of the lamps, which are upon the top thereof; ^3and two olive-trees by it, one upon the right side of the bowl, and the other upon the left side thereof. ^4And I answered and spake to the angel that talked with me, saying, What are these, my lord? ^5Then the angel that talked with me answered and said unto me, Knowest thou not what these are? And I said, No, my lord. ^6Then he answered and spake unto me, saying, This is the word of Jehovah unto Zerubbabel, saying, Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^7Who art thou, O great mountain? before Zerubbabel thou shalt become a plain; and he shall bring forth the top stone with shoutings of Grace, grace, unto it. ^8Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^9The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this house; his hands shall also finish it; and thou shalt know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto you. ^10For who hath despised the day of small things? for these seven shall rejoice, and shall see the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel; these are the eyes of Jehovah, which run to and fro through the whole earth. ^11Then answered I, and said unto him, What are these two olive-trees upon the right side of the candlestick and upon the left side thereof? ^12And I answered the second time, and said unto him, What are these two olive-branches, which are beside the two golden spouts, that empty the golden oil out of themselves? ^13And he answered me and said, Knowest thou not what these are? And I said, No, my lord. ^14Then said he, These are the two anointed ones, that stand by the Lord of the whole earth.

Zechariah 5

5

^1Then again I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, a flying roll. ^2And he said unto me, What seest thou? And I answered, I see a flying roll; the length thereof is twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof ten cubits. ^3Then said he unto me, This is the curse that goeth forth over the face of the whole land: for every one that stealeth shall be cut off on the one side according to it; and every one that sweareth shall be cut off on the other side according to it. ^4I will cause it to go forth, saith Jehovah of hosts, and it shall enter into the house of the thief, and into the house of him that sweareth falsely by my name; and it shall abide in the midst of his house, and shall consume it with the timber thereof and the stones thereof. ^5Then the angel that talked with me went forth, and said unto me, Lift up now thine eyes, and see what is this that goeth forth. ^6And I said, What is it? And he said, This is the ephah that goeth forth. He said moreover, This is their appearance in all the land ^7(and, behold, there was lifted up a talent of lead); and this is a woman sitting in the midst of the ephah. ^8And he said, This is Wickedness: and he cast her down into the midst of the ephah; and he cast the weight of lead upon the mouth thereof. ^9Then lifted I up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, there came forth two women, and the wind was in their wings; now they had wings like the wings of a stork; and they lifted up the ephah between earth and heaven. ^10Then said I to the angel that talked with me, Whither do these bear the ephah? ^11And he said unto me, To build her a house in the land of Shinar: and when it is prepared, she shall be set there in her own place.

Zechariah 6

6

^1And again I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, there came four chariots out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of brass. ^2In the first chariot were red horses; and in the second chariot black horses; ^3and in the third chariot white horses; and in the fourth chariot grizzled strong horses. ^4Then I answered and said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these, my lord? ^5And the angel answered and said unto me, These are the four winds of heaven, which go forth from standing before the Lord of all the earth. ^6The chariot wherein are the black horses goeth forth toward the north country; and the white went forth after them; and the grizzled went forth toward the south country. ^7And the strong went forth, and sought to go that they might walk to and fro through the earth: and he said, Get you hence, walk to and fro through the earth. So they walked to and fro through the earth. ^8Then cried he to me, and spake unto me, saying, Behold, they that go toward the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country. ^9And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^10Take of them of the captivity, even of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah; and come thou the same day, and go into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah, whither they are come from Babylon; ^11yea, take of them silver and gold, and make crowns, and set them upon the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest; ^12and speak unto him, saying, Thus speaketh Jehovah of hosts, saying, Behold, the man whose name is the Branch: and he shall grow up out of his place; and he shall build the temple of Jehovah; ^13even he shall build the temple of Jehovah; and he shall bear the glory, and shall sit and rule upon his throne; and he shall be a priest upon his throne; and the counsel of peace shall be between them both. ^14And the crowns shall be to Helem, and to Tobijah, and to Jedaiah, and to Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in the temple of Jehovah. ^15And they that are far off shall come and build in the temple of Jehovah; and ye shall know that Jehovah of hosts hath sent me unto you. And this shall come to pass, if ye will diligently obey the voice of Jehovah your God.

Zechariah 7

7

^1And it came to pass in the fourth year of king Darius, that the word of Jehovah came unto Zechariah in the fourth day of the ninth month, even in Chislev. ^2Now they of Beth-el had sent Sharezer and Regem-melech, and their men, to entreat the favor of Jehovah, ^3and to speak unto the priests of the house of Jehovah of hosts, and to the prophets, saying, Should I weep in the fifth month, separating myself, as I have done these so many years? ^4Then came the word of Jehovah of hosts unto me, saying, ^5Speak unto all the people of the land, and to the priests, saying, When ye fasted and mourned in the fifth and in the seventh month, even these seventy years, did ye at all fast unto me, even to me? ^6And when ye eat, and when ye drink, do not ye eat for yourselves, and drink for yourselves? ^7Should ye not hear the words which Jehovah cried by the former prophets, when Jerusalem was inhabited and in prosperity, and the cities thereof round about her, and the South and the lowland were inhabited? ^8And the word of Jehovah came unto Zechariah, saying, ^9Thus hath Jehovah of hosts spoken, saying, Execute true judgment, and show kindness and compassion every man to his brother; ^10and oppress not the widow, nor the fatherless, the sojourner, nor the poor; and let none of you devise evil against his brother in your heart. ^11But they refused to hearken, and pulled away the shoulder, and stopped their ears, that they might not hear. ^12Yea, they made their hearts as an adamant stone, lest they should hear the law, and the words which Jehovah of hosts had sent by his Spirit by the former prophets: therefore there came great wrath from Jehovah of hosts. ^13And it is come to pass that, as he cried, and they would not hear, so they shall cry, and I will not hear, said Jehovah of hosts; ^14but I will scatter them with a whirlwind among all the nations which they have not known. Thus the land was desolate after them, so that no man passed through nor returned: for they laid the pleasant land desolate.

Zechariah 8

8

^1And the word of Jehovah of hosts came to me, saying, ^2Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: I am jealous for Zion with great jealousy, and I am jealous for her with great wrath. ^3Thus saith Jehovah: I am returned unto Zion, and will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem: and Jerusalem shall be called The city of truth; and the mountain of Jehovah of hosts, The holy mountain. ^4Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: There shall yet old men and old women dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, every man with his staff in his hand for very age. ^5And the streets of the city shall be full of boys and girls playing in the streets thereof. ^6Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: If it be marvellous in the eyes of the remnant of this people in those days, should it also be marvellous in mine eyes? saith Jehovah of hosts. ^7Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Behold, I will save my people from the east country, and from the west country; ^8and I will bring them, and they shall dwell in the midst of Jerusalem; and they shall be my people, and I will be their God, in truth and in righteousness. ^9Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Let your hands be strong, ye that hear in these days these words from the mouth of the prophets that were in the day that the foundation of the house of Jehovah of hosts was laid, even the temple, that it might be built. ^10For before those days there was no hire for man, nor any hire for beast; neither was there any peace to him that went out or came in, because of the adversary: for I set all men every one against his neighbor. ^11But now I will not be unto the remnant of this people as in the former days, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^12For there shall be the seed of peace; the vine shall give its fruit, and the ground shall give its increase, and the heavens shall give their dew; and I will cause the remnant of this people to inherit all these things. ^13And it shall come to pass that, as ye were a curse among the nations, O house of Judah and house of Israel, so will I save you, and ye shall be a blessing. Fear not, but let your hands be strong. ^14For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: As I thought to do evil unto you, when your fathers provoked me to wrath, saith Jehovah of hosts, and I repented not; ^15so again have I thought in these days to do good unto Jerusalem and to the house of Judah: fear ye not. ^16These are the things that ye shall do: speak ye every man the truth with his neighbor; execute the judgment of truth and peace in your gates; ^17and let none of you devise evil in your hearts against his neighbor; and love no false oath: for all these are things that I hate, saith Jehovah. ^18And the word of Jehovah of hosts came unto me, saying, ^19Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: The fast of the fourth month, and the fast of the fifth, and the fast of the seventh, and the fast of the tenth, shall be to the house of Judah joy and gladness, and cheerful feasts; therefore love truth and peace. ^20Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: It shall yet come to pass, that there shall come peoples, and the inhabitants of many cities; ^21and the inhabitants of one city shall go to another, saying, Let us go speedily to entreat the favor of Jehovah, and to seek Jehovah of hosts: I will go also. ^22Yea, many peoples and strong nations shall come to seek Jehovah of hosts in Jerusalem, and to entreat the favor of Jehovah. ^23Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: In those days it shall come to pass, that ten men shall take hold, out of all the languages of the nations, they shall take hold of the skirt of him that is a Jew, saying, We will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you.

Zechariah 9

9

^1The burden of the word of Jehovah upon the land of Hadrach, and Damascus shall be its resting-place (for the eye of man and of all the tribes of Israel is toward Jehovah); ^2and Hamath, also, which bordereth thereon; Tyre and Sidon, because they are very wise. ^3And Tyre did build herself a stronghold, and heaped up silver as the dust, and fine gold as the mire of the streets. ^4Behold, the Lord will dispossess her, and he will smite her power in the sea; and she shall be devoured with fire. ^5Ashkelon shall see it, and fear; Gaza also, and shall be sore pained; and Ekron, for her expectation shall be put to shame; and the king shall perish from Gaza, and Ashkelon shall not be inhabited. ^6And a bastard shall dwell in Ashdod, and I will cut off the pride of the Philistines. ^7And I will take away his blood out of his mouth, and his abominations from between his teeth; and he also shall be a remnant for our God; and he shall be as a chieftain in Judah, and Ekron as a Jebusite. ^8And I will encamp about my house against the army, that none pass through or return; and no oppressor shall pass through them any more: for now have I seen with mine eyes. ^9Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion; shout, O daughter of Jerusalem: behold, thy king cometh unto thee; he is just, and having salvation; lowly, and riding upon an ass, even upon a colt the foal of an ass. ^10And I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim, and the horse from Jerusalem; and the battle bow shall be cut off; and he shall speak peace unto the nations: and his dominion shall be from sea to sea, and from the River to the ends of the earth. ^11As for thee also, because of the blood of thy covenant I have set free thy prisoners from the pit wherein is no water. ^12Turn you to the stronghold, ye prisoners of hope: even to-day do I declare that I will render double unto thee. ^13For I have bent Judah for me, I have filled the bow with Ephraim; and I will stir up thy sons, O Zion, against thy sons, O Greece, and will make thee as the sword of a mighty man. ^14And Jehovah shall be seen over them; and his arrow shall go forth as the lightning; and the Lord Jehovah will blow the trumpet, and will go with whirlwinds of the south. ^15Jehovah of hosts will defend them; and they shall devour, and shall tread down the sling-stones; and they shall drink, and make a noise as through wine; and they shall be filled like bowls, like the corners of the altar. ^16And Jehovah their God will save them in that day as the flock of his people; for they shall be as the stones of a crown, lifted on high over his land. ^17For how great is his goodness, and how great is his beauty! grain shall make the young men flourish, and new wine the virgins.

Zechariah 10

10

^1Ask ye of Jehovah rain in the time of the latter rain, even of Jehovah that maketh lightnings; and he will give them showers of rain, to every one grass in the field. ^2For the teraphim have spoken vanity, and the diviners have seen a lie; and they have told false dreams, they comfort in vain: therefore they go their way like sheep, they are afflicted, because there is no shepherd. ^3Mine anger is kindled against the shepherds, and I will punish the he-goats; for Jehovah of hosts hath visited his flock, the house of Judah, and will make them as his goodly horse in the battle. ^4From him shall come forth the corner-stone, from him the nail, from him the battle bow, from him every ruler together. ^5And they shall be as mighty men, treading down their enemies in the mire of the streets in the battle; and they shall fight, because Jehovah is with them; and the riders on horses shall be confounded. ^6And I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph, and I will bring them back; for I have mercy upon them; and they shall be as though I had not cast them off: for I am Jehovah their God, and I will hear them. ^7And they of Ephraim shall be like a mighty man, and their heart shall rejoice as through wine; yea, their children shall see it, and rejoice; their heart shall be glad in Jehovah. ^8I will hiss for them, and gather them; for I have redeemed them; and they shall increase as they have increased. ^9And I will sow them among the peoples; and they shall remember me in far countries; and they shall live with their children, and shall return. ^10I will bring them again also out of the land of Egypt, and gather them out of Assyria; and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon; and place shall not be found for them. ^11And he will pass through the sea of affliction, and will smite the waves in the sea, and all the depths of the Nile shall dry up; and the pride of Assyria shall be brought down, and the sceptre of Egypt shall depart. ^12And I will strengthen them in Jehovah; and they shall walk up and down in his name, saith Jehovah.

Zechariah 11

11

^1Open thy doors, O Lebanon, that the fire may devour thy cedars. ^2Wail, O fir-tree, for the cedar is fallen, because the goodly ones are destroyed: wail, O ye oaks of Bashan, for the strong forest is come down. ^3A voice of the wailing of the shepherds! for their glory is destroyed: a voice of the roaring of young lions! for the pride of the Jordan is laid waste. ^4Thus said Jehovah my God: Feed the flock of slaughter; ^5whose possessors slay them, and hold themselves not guilty; and they that sell them say, Blessed be Jehovah, for I am rich; and their own shepherds pity them not. ^6For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land, saith Jehovah; but, lo, I will deliver the men every one into his neighbor's hand, and into the hand of his king; and they shall smite the land, and out of their hand I will not deliver them. ^7So I fed the flock of slaughter, verily the poor of the flock. And I took unto me two staves; the one I called Beauty, and the other I called Bands; and I fed the flock. ^8And I cut off the three shepherds in one month; for my soul was weary of them, and their soul also loathed me. ^9Then said I, I will not feed you: that which dieth, let it die; and that which is to be cut off, let it be cut off; and let them that are left eat every one the flesh of another. ^10And I took my staff Beauty, and cut it asunder, that I might break my covenant which I had made with all the peoples. ^11And it was broken in that day; and thus the poor of the flock that gave heed unto me knew that it was the word of Jehovah. ^12And I said unto them, If ye think good, give me my hire; and if not, forbear. So they weighed for my hire thirty pieces of silver. ^13And Jehovah said unto me, Cast it unto the potter, the goodly price that I was prized at by them. And I took the thirty pieces of silver, and cast them unto the potter, in the house of Jehovah. ^14Then I cut asunder mine other staff, even Bands, that I might break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel. ^15And Jehovah said unto me, Take unto thee yet again the instruments of a foolish shepherd. ^16For, lo, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, who will not visit those that are cut off, neither will seek those that are scattered, nor heal that which is broken, nor feed that which is sound; but he will eat the flesh of the fat sheep, and will tear their hoofs in pieces. ^17Woe to the worthless shepherd that leaveth the flock! the sword shall be upon his arm, and upon his right eye: his arm shall be clean dried up, and his right eye shall be utterly darkened.

Zechariah 12

12

^1The burden of the word of Jehovah concerning Israel. Thus saith Jehovah, who stretcheth forth the heavens, and layeth the foundation of the earth, and formeth the spirit of man within him: ^2behold, I will make Jerusalem a cup of reeling unto all the peoples round about, and upon Judah also shall it be in the siege against Jerusalem. ^3And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will make Jerusalem a burdensome stone for all the peoples; all that burden themselves with it shall be sore wounded; and all the nations of the earth shall be gathered together against it. ^4In that day, saith Jehovah, I will smite every horse with terror, and his rider with madness; and I will open mine eyes upon the house of Judah, and will smite every horse of the peoples with blindness. ^5And the chieftains of Judah shall say in their heart, The inhabitants of Jerusalem are my strength in Jehovah of hosts their God. ^6In that day will I make the chieftains of Judah like a pan of fire among wood, and like a flaming torch among sheaves; and they shall devour all the peoples round about, on the right hand and on the left; and they of Jerusalem shall yet again dwell in their own place, even in Jerusalem. ^7Jehovah also shall save the tents of Judah first, that the glory of the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem be not magnified above Judah. ^8In that day shall Jehovah defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem: and he that is feeble among them at that day shall be as David; and the house of David shall be as God, as the angel of Jehovah before them. ^9And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will seek to destroy all the nations that come against Jerusalem. ^10And I will pour upon the house of David, and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the spirit of grace and of supplication; and they shall look unto me whom they have pierced; and they shall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only son, and shall be in bitterness for him, as one that is in bitterness for his first-born. ^11In that day shall there be a great mourning in Jerusalem, as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon. ^12And the land shall mourn, every family apart; the family of the house of David apart, and their wives apart; the family of the house of Nathan apart, and their wives apart; ^13the family of the house of Levi apart, and their wives apart; the family of the Shimeites apart, and their wives apart; ^14all the families that remain, every family apart, and their wives apart.

Zechariah 13

13

^1In that day there shall be a fountain opened to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, for sin and for uncleanness. ^2And it shall come to pass in that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, that I will cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they shall no more be remembered; and also I will cause the prophets and the unclean spirit to pass out of the land. ^3And it shall come to pass that, when any shall yet prophesy, then his father and his mother that begat him shall say unto him, Thou shalt not live; for thou speakest lies in the name of Jehovah; and his father and his mother that begat him shall thrust him through when he prophesieth. ^4And it shall come to pass in that day, that the prophets shall be ashamed every one of his vision, when he prophesieth; neither shall they wear a hairy mantle to deceive: ^5but he shall say, I am no prophet, I am a tiller of the ground; for I have been made a bondman from my youth. ^6And one shall say unto him, What are these wounds between thine arms? Then he shall answer, Those with which I was wounded in the house of my friends. ^7Awake, O sword, against my shepherd, and against the man that is my fellow, saith Jehovah of hosts: smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered; and I will turn my hand upon the little ones. ^8And it shall come to pass, that in all the land, saith Jehovah, two parts therein shall be cut off and die; but the third shall be left therein. ^9And I will bring the third part into the fire, and will refine them as silver is refined, and will try them as gold is tried. They shall call on my name, and I will hear them: I will say, It is my people; and they shall say, Jehovah is my God.

Zechariah 14

14

^1Behold, a day of Jehovah cometh, when thy spoil shall be divided in the midst of thee. ^2For I will gather all nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city shall be taken, and the houses rifled, and the women ravished; and half of the city shall go forth into captivity, and the residue of the people shall not be cut off from the city. ^3Then shall Jehovah go forth, and fight against those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle. ^4And his feet shall stand in that day upon the mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem on the east; and the mount of Olives shall be cleft in the midst thereof toward the east and toward the west, and there shall be a very great valley; and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north, and half of it toward the south. ^5And ye shall flee by the valley of my mountains; for the valley of the mountains shall reach unto Azel; yea, ye shall flee, like as ye fled from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah; and Jehovah my God shall come, and all the holy ones with thee. ^6And it shall come to pass in that day, that there shall not be light; the bright ones shall withdraw themselves: ^7but it shall be one day which is known unto Jehovah; not day, and not night; but it shall come to pass, that at evening time there shall be light. ^8And it shall come to pass in that day, that living waters shall go out from Jerusalem; half of them toward the eastern sea, and half of them toward the western sea: in summer and in winter shall it be. ^9And Jehovah shall be King over all the earth: in that day shall Jehovah be one, and his name one. ^10All the land shall be made like the Arabah, from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem; and she shall be lifted up, and shall dwell in her place, from Benjamin's gate unto the place of the first gate, unto the corner gate, and from the tower of Hananel unto the king's wine-presses. ^11And men shall dwell therein, and there shall be no more curse; but Jerusalem shall dwell safely. ^12And this shall be the plague wherewith Jehovah will smite all the peoples that have warred against Jerusalem: their flesh shall consume away while they stand upon their feet, and their eyes shall consume away in their sockets, and their tongue shall consume away in their mouth. ^13And it shall come to pass in that day, that a great tumult from Jehovah shall be among them; and they shall lay hold every one on the hand of his neighbor, and his hand shall rise up against the hand of his neighbor. ^14And Judah also shall fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the nations round about shall be gathered together, gold, and silver, and apparel, in great abundance. ^15And so shall be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camel, and of the ass, and of all the beasts that shall be in those camps, as that plague. ^16And it shall come to pass, that every one that is left of all the nations that came against Jerusalem shall go up from year to year to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, and to keep the feast of tabernacles. ^17And it shall be, that whoso of all the families of the earth goeth not up unto Jerusalem to worship the King, Jehovah of hosts, upon them there shall be no rain. ^18And if the family of Egypt go not up, and come not, neither shall it be upon them; there shall be the plague wherewith Jehovah will smite the nations that go not up to keep the feast of tabernacles. ^19This shall be the punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all the nations that go not up to keep the feast of tabernacles. ^20In that day shall there be upon the bells of the horses, HOLY UNTO JEHOVAH; and the pots in Jehovah's house shall be like the bowls before the altar. ^21Yea, every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah shall be holy unto Jehovah of hosts; and all they that sacrifice shall come and take of them, and boil therein: and in that day there shall be no more a Canaanite in the house of Jehovah of hosts.

Zephaniah 2

2

^1Gather yourselves together, yea, gather together, O nation that hath no shame; ^2before the decree bring forth, before the day pass as the chaff, before the fierce anger of Jehovah come upon you, before the day of Jehovah's anger come upon you. ^3Seek ye Jehovah, all ye meek of the earth, that have kept his ordinances; seek righteousness, seek meekness: it may be ye will be hid in the day of Jehovah's anger. ^4For Gaza shall be forsaken, and Ashkelon a desolation; they shall drive out Ashdod at noonday, and Ekron shall be rooted up. ^5Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea-coast, the nation of the Cherethites! The word of Jehovah is against you, O Canaan, the land of the Philistines; I will destroy thee, that there shall be no inhabitant. ^6And the sea-coast shall be pastures, with cottages for shepherds and folds for flocks. ^7And the coast shall be for the remnant of the house of Judah; they shall feed their flocks thereupon; in the houses of Ashkelon shall they lie down in the evening; for Jehovah their God will visit them, and bring back their captivity. ^8I have heard the reproach of Moab, and the revilings of the children of Ammon, wherewith they have reproached my people, and magnified themselves against their border. ^9Therefore as I live, saith Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, Surely Moab shall be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, a possession of nettles, and saltpits, and a perpetual desolation: the residue of my people shall make a prey of them, and the remnant of my nation shall inherit them. ^10This shall they have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of Jehovah of hosts. ^11Jehovah will be terrible unto them; for he will famish all the gods of the earth; and men shall worship him, every one from his place, even all the isles of the nations. ^12Ye Ethiopians also, ye shall be slain by my sword. ^13And he will stretch out his hand against the north, and destroy Assyria, and will make Nineveh a desolation, and dry like the wilderness. ^14And herds shall lie down in the midst of her, all the beasts of the nations: both the pelican and the porcupine shall lodge in the capitals thereof; their voice shall sing in the windows; desolation shall be in the thresholds: for he hath laid bare the cedar-work. ^15This is the joyous city that dwelt carelessly, that said in her heart, I am, and there is none besides me: how is she become a desolation, a place for beasts to lie down in! every one that passeth by her shall hiss, and wag his hand.

Zephaniah 3

3

^1Woe to her that is rebellious and polluted! to the oppressing city! ^2She obeyed not the voice; she received not correction; she trusted not in Jehovah; she drew not near to her God. ^3Her princes in the midst of her are roaring lions; her judges are evening wolves; they leave nothing till the morrow. ^4Her prophets are light and treacherous persons; her priests have profaned the sanctuary, they have done violence to the law. ^5Jehovah in the midst of her is righteous; he will not do iniquity; every morning doth he bring his justice to light, he faileth not; but the unjust knoweth no shame. ^6I have cut off nations; their battlements are desolate; I have made their streets waste, so that none passeth by; their cities are destroyed, so that there is no man, so that there is no inhabitant. ^7I said, Only fear thou me; receive correction; so her dwelling shall not be cut off, according to all that I have appointed concerning her: but they rose early and corrupted all their doings. ^8Therefore wait ye for me, saith Jehovah, until the day that I rise up to the prey; for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may assemble the kingdoms, to pour upon them mine indignation, even all my fierce anger; for all the earth shall be devoured with the fire of my jealousy. ^9For then will I turn to the peoples of a pure language, that they may all call upon the name of Jehovah, to serve him with one consent. ^10From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia my suppliants, even the daughter of my dispersed, shall bring mine offering. ^11In that day shalt thou not be put to shame for all thy doings, wherein thou hast transgressed against me; for then I will take away out of the midst of thee thy proudly exulting ones, and thou shalt no more be haughty in my holy mountain. ^12But I will leave in the midst of thee an afflicted and poor people, and they shall take refuge in the name of Jehovah. ^13The remnant of Israel shall not do iniquity, nor speak lies; neither shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth; for they shall feed and lie down, and none shall make them afraid. ^14Sing, O daughter of Zion; shout, O Israel; be glad and rejoice with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem. ^15Jehovah hath taken away thy judgments, he hath cast out thine enemy: the King of Israel, even Jehovah, is in the midst of thee; thou shalt not fear evil any more. ^16In that day it shall be said to Jerusalem, Fear thou not; O Zion, let not thy hands be slack. ^17Jehovah thy God is in the midst of thee, a mighty one who will save; he will rejoice over thee with joy; he will rest in his love; he will joy over thee with singing. ^18I will gather them that sorrow for the solemn assembly, who were of thee; to whom the burden upon her was a reproach. ^19Behold, at that time I will deal with all them that afflict thee; and I will save that which is lame, and gather that which was driven away; and I will make them a praise and a name, whose shame hath been in all the earth. ^20At that time will I bring you in, and at that time will I gather you; for I will make you a name and a praise among all the peoples of the earth, when I bring back your captivity before your eyes, saith Jehovah.